<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: berlin02.xml,v 1.1 2006/04/08 14:53:21 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Notes on - Freedom and its Betrayal"
       created="2006-2-20"
       description="Notes on Isaiah Berlin's 1952 radio talks on six enemies of Liberty."
       keywords="philosophy"
       class="bib"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center"><image name="lgnote.gif"/> by <image name="rbjin1.gif"/> on<br/>Freedom and its betrayal<br/>by <a href="b.htm#Berlin" target="_top">Isaiah Berlin</a></maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction" />
<secref title="Helvetius" />
<secref title="Rousseau" />
<secref title="Fichte" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Hegel" />
<secref title="Saint-Simon" />
<secref title="Maistre" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Some things that these six thinkers have in common, and a tiny history of political philosophy in the form of answers to the question: "Why should anyone obey anyone else?".
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="What they had in common">
<ul>
<li>All born at the dawn of liberal democracy, i.e. around the French revolution the beginning of the 19th Century.</li>
<li>All visionary thinkers, whose vision impressed upon readers a complete change of world-view.</li>
<li>All champions of "liberty" whose doctrines were in fact detrimental to liberty as is it usually understood.</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Why Should Anyone Obey Anyone Else?">
Berlin provides a highly condensed long list of answers which had been given to this question.
I shalln't attempt to precis his list, its a couple of pages which can't be further condensed.
<p/>
The point of it is that the contrast between the recent achievements of Newton in physics and the proliferation of irresolvably conflicting view on matters of politics and ethics was a source of dissatisfaction.
People wanted to see the sucesses of Newton emulated in politics and ethics.
They sought a simple principle on the basis of which the facts and values of social life could be brought to order.
<p/>
To quote Condorcet:
<blockquote>
"As one meditates on the nature of the moral sciences one really cannot avoid the conclusion that since, like the physical sciences, they rest upon observation of the facts, they ought to follow the same methods, acquire a language no less exact and precise, and so attain to the same degree of certainty."
</blockquote>

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Helvetius">
<abstract>
Helvetius came up with a principle intended to perform for the social sciences the role which Newton's laws of motion peformed for physics.
The pleasure principle.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Principle">
Presented as the word of God to man (though Helvetius was an atheist):
<blockquote>
"I endow thee with sensibility.
It is by this alone that thou, blind tool of my wishes, incapable of plumbing my aims, thou must, without knowing it, fulfil my purposes.
Over thee I set pleasure and pain; the one and the other will watch over thy thoughts and acts, excite thy aversions, friendships, tender sentiments, joys, set on fire thy desires, fears, hopes, reveal to thee truths, plunge thee into error, and after causing thee to generate a million vatious absurd systems of morals and legislation, will one day disclose to thee the simple principles on the development of which depend the order and happiness of the moral world."
</blockquote>
which Berlin takes as a formulation of utilitarianism.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Factual to Moral">
It appears that Helivetius believed that from his <i>factual</i> or <i>descriptive</i>
 principle (that men in fact seek pleasure and avoid pain) the <i>evaluative</i> or <i>moral</i> principle (that men <i>should</i> do so) followed.
So far as it is put by Berlin it would seem to be on the ground that they cannot be expected to do something which is not possible, though surely if these considerations totally determine behaviour, moral vocabulary becomes gratuitous.

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Fichte">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Freedom">
Berlin says (p. 61):
<blockquote>
"Autonomy, true freedom, consists in issuing orders to myself which I,
being free to do as I will, obey."
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
"This is Rousseau's concept of moral freedom, and it is Kant's"
</blockquote>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
