<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: carnap63III.II.xml,v 1.1 2014/11/08 19:43:26 rbj Exp $"
       title="Language, Modal Logic and Semantics"
       created="2013-10-21"
       description="Notes on The Philosophy of Rudolf Carnap"
       keywords="philosophy logic history semantics empiricism Carnap "
       class="bib"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center"><image name="lgnote.gif"/> by <image name="rbjin1.gif"/> on<br/>Metaphysics, Realism and Physicalism<br/> Part III section II of <a href="c.htm#Carnap63" target="_top">The Philosophy of Rudolf Carnap</a></maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Notes on Carnap's replies to essays by other philosophers concerning his views on Metaphysics, Realism and Physicalism
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="4. My Views on Ontological Problems of Existence" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="5. Paul Henle on Meaning and Verifiability" />
<subsec title="6. K.R.Popper on the Demarcation between Science and Metaphysics" />
<subsec title="7. Herbert Feigl on Physicalism" />
<subsec title="8. A.J.Ayer on Other Minds" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="4. My Views on Ontological Problems of Existence" tag="4">
<abstract>
This is Carnap's mature statement of his position in relation to metaphysics.
It falls into two parts.
<ul>
<li>
A. The first corresponds to the early invectives against pseudo-statements which form an important part of the "manifesto", primarily concerned with condemning certain philosophical theses as lacking cognitive context (at that time, as meaningless).
This also explains how these problems can be transformed into pragmatic decisions about language.
</li>
<li>
B. The second present Carnap's treatment of abstract entities (particularly their use in semntics)
</li>
</ul>
</abstract>
<secbody title="A. The Realism Controversy">
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
Surpisingly stable aspect of Carnap's philosophy, unchanged except by
moderation of terminology since 1928.
The theses of realism lack cognitive content (originally, are meaningless).
</p><p>
Three specific kinds of realism are single out for condemnation:
<ol>
<li>
the external world
</li>
<li>
other minds
</li>
<li>
abstract entities
</li>
</ol>
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Who and When?">
Carnap uses the collective "we" in talking about these view, which I take to
indicate his belief in there having been a consensus at that time in the
Schlick (Vienna) circle.
He refers to the first edition of "Pseudoproblems in Philosophy", published in 1928 (in german) as
documenting the position.
</subsec>
</sbcol><sbcol>
<subsec title="What Are the Issues?">
<p>
The following claims are held to lack "cognitive content".
<ol>
<li>The assertion of the reality of the external world, and its various
  denials, including solipsism various kinds of idealism.</li>
<li>The assertion of the reality of other minds and its denial.</li>
<li>The assertion of the existence of abstract entities and its denial.</li>
</ol>
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Choice of Language">
<p>
Though the claims lack cognitive content, there are closely related practical
questions about choice of language which are of importance.
The list of languages mentioned here differs somewhat from the languages
mentioned earlier in Schilpp volume:
<ul>
<li>phenomenalistic language</li>
<li>the thing language</li>
<li>physical language</li>
<li>dualistic language</li>
</ul>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="B. The Problem of Abstract Objects">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Same as `Empiricism Semantics and Ontology'">
<p>
Carnap considered this problem not long before the Schilpp volume and wrote the
paper `Empiricism Semantics and Ontology' <bibref name="Carnap50"/> (in second edition of meaning and necessity).
He refers to that paper, but provides an example illustrating his position.
His position is explained through the distinction between internal and external
questions.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Internal Questions">
<p>
These are ontological questions expressed in a language whose semantics has
been defined, and they are settled by the semantic rules for the language.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="External Questions">
These are ontological question asked out of context, i.e. in some language
which has no definite semantics (often in the context of defining some
language).
These have no cognitive content.
The question of legitimacy of a language definition which employs such entities
is to be resolved not by answering the external question, but on pragmatic considerations.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Pragmatic Exemplar">
Carnap describes a couple of simple languages, and gives some internal and
external questions in relation the languages and states his position in
relation to them and gives some suggestions on the pragmatic considerations
which might be considered.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



