<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: CQ90LOC.xml,v 1.1 2009/12/16 21:55:38 rbj Exp $"
       title="Notes on: Dear Carnap, Dear Van - Lectures on Carnap"
       created="2009/11/28"
       description="Notes on the published volume of correspondence between Carnap and Quine, covering Quine's 1934 lectures on Carnap's Philosophy of Logical Syntax"
       keywords="philosophy logic history semantics empiricism positivism Carnap Quine syntax"
       class="bib"
       up="carnapquine90.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center"><image name="lgnote.gif"/> by
  <image name="rbjin1.gif"/> on<br/>Quine's lectures on Carnap's Philosophy of Logical Syntax</maintitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Quine gave three lectures on Carnap's Philosophy of Logical Syntax at Harvard in 1934.
The first of these lectures provided the basis for the paper <i>Truth by Convention [<bibref name="Quine36"/></i>].
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Background"/>
<secref title="Lecture I: The A Priori"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Lecture II: Syntax"/>
<secref title="Lecture III: Philosophy as Syntax"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Background">
<abstract>
A few words placing the lectures in historical context.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol><subsec title="">
<p>
On completing his doctoral dissertation (in just two years) Quine obtained a Sheldon Travelling Fellowship (for one year) and went to Vienna in the fall of 1932.
Carnap had then taken up a position in Prague, so after attending lectures by Schlick in Vienna Quine went on to Prague in the spring, meeting Carnap in March 1933.
Carnap was then writing <i>Logische Syntax Der Sprache [<bibref name="Carnap34"/>]</i>, and Quine had the opportunity to read the book as it was typed up by Ina Carnap.
</p>
<p>
Quine's reservations about the analytic/synthetic distinction date from this first acquaintance with Carnap's work. 
</p>
</subsec></sbcol>
<sbcol><subsec>
<p>
Quine was elected a junior fellow of Harvard while in Europe.
His doctoral dissertation was being prepared for publication, but Quine's European travels resulted in his wishing to make substantial changes, the completion of which occupied the greater part of his time during the first year of his three year fellowship.
He was also asked to prepare three lectures on the philosophy of Carnap, which were delivered in November 1934.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Lecture I: The A Priori" tag="I">
<abstract>
Quine's first lecture addresses primarily the concept of analyticity and also the a priori, not professing to be an account of Carnap's philosophy, but rather as providing introductory background prior to an account of Carnap's philosophy of logical syntax in the second and third lectures.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Definitions of Analyticity and the A Priori">
<p>
This lecture is devoted to a discussion of "the analytic character of the a priori".
Quine begins by reference to Kant, citing first Kants view that analytic judgements are a proper subset of the a priori, and quoting the definition of a priori as having "the character of inward necessity".
"and holds independently of any possible experience".
</p><p>
He provides multiple characterisations of (or claims about) analyticity as follows:
<ol>
<li>a judgement the truth of which can be established directly by analysis of the concepts involved</li>
<li>an analytic judgement can do no more than call our attention to something already contained in the definitions of our terms</li>
<li>consequences of definitions, conventions as to the uses of words</li>
<li>consequences of linguistic fiat</li>
</ol>
and observes that among them "are to be reckoned" logic and "the bulk, at least" of mathematics.
</p><p>
Quine then notes Kant's view that there are judgements which are synthetic but a priori (e.g. those of geometry), and the more recent grounds for rejecting this claim (by showing that the whole of mathematics, including geometry, is analytic), and the doctrine that all a priori judgements are analytic.
To examine this claim Quine proposes to examine in detail "the nature of the analytic".
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Commentary">
<p>
On the face of it the first item is offered as a definition and subsequent items are clarifications, but these by no means follow.
Possibly his intention is that we should read them conjointly as defining the concept.
</p><p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Definitions">
<p>
Quine begins by distinguishing two kinds of definition, <i>explicit</i> definitions, which are "merely a convention of abbreviation", and <i>implicit</i> definitions, which are sets of rules specifying that certain sentences in which the word (say 'K') being defined occur and which are to be accepted by convention as true, "their truth constitutes the meaning of 'K'".
Quine observes that definitions have often been construed as exclusively of the kind he calls "explicit", but that it is convenient in the present context to adopt the broader usage (noting that there is precedent for it).
</p><p>
Quine then tells us that analyticity depends on (nothing more than) definitions.
This leads to an extended expansion of his explanation of analyticity based around examples of how this process of defining a language might proceed.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Commentary">
<p>
Note first that Quine's canonical notion of definition, his "explicit" definitions, are syntactic in character, they are syntactic abbreviations, and Quine does not appear here to have a notion of definition as assigning meaning to or denotation for a new name.
</p><p>
Note also that Quine does not mention here that his explicit definitions are eliminable, whereas his implicit definitions may not be.
</p><p>
It may be helpful to consider to what extent Quine's arguments depend upon his particular conception of definition and to what extent the arguments remain sound if we adopt, for example, a conception of definition as introducing a new name (constant) by conservative extension to an existing language or theory.
</p><p>
Quine's conception of analyticity makes it dependent not on meanings, but on definitions.
This conception he applies to natural languages not merely to formally defined languages, so one might get the impression that analyticity only arises in natural languages once the language has been partly or wholly augmented by definitions of the words of the language.
</p><p>
This makes Quine's conception of analyticity dependent on a process of formalisation which is potentially more problematic than the identification of analytic sentences in natural languages on unmediated operation of our intuitions about their meaning, without the need to deliver definitions of all the terms involved.
</p><p>
The cases in which the concept is most readily applicable are those in which a sentence in a natural language is considered in which there is no significant difficulty of comprehension, or a sentence in a formal language whose subject matter is straightforward and whose semantics can be presented unambiguously (for example the first order language of arithmetic).
Quine's subsequent explication of the idea of analyticity through a process of providing definitions for terms originating in a natural language is the least plausible context for a successful outcome.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Lecture II: Syntax" tag="II">
<abstract>
On Carnap's syntactic methods and the method of arithmetisation.
</abstract>
<secbody title="Formally Describing Languages using Syntactic Rules">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Semantics and Syntax">
<p>
Quine begins with a discussion of the meaning of the word "semantic", which apparently was then in use not only by Pierce to talk about menaing, but aslo by Chistwick in a sense which embraced syntax.
Quine presents Carnap's use of the term "syntax" as a means of avoiding this ambiguity in the term "semantic".
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Kinds of Rules">
<p>
We next hear that Carnap divides his rules of syntax into two kinds rules of <i>formation</i> and of <i>transformation</i>.
The formation rules are concerned with grammar and tell us what are the meaningful sentences.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Formation Rules">
<p>
Quine notes the complexity of a full account of the formation rules for natural languages and cites this as the reason why Carnap choses an artificial language as object for syntactic study.
He then goes on to describe the formation rules for an artificial language, somewhat, but not entirely, like the one used by Carnap.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Transformation Rules">
<p>
The transformation rules "specify the conditions under which a sentence may be <i>inferred</i>".
They "answer to" what Quine described in his first lecture as <i>implicit definitions</i>.
Quine replays the formal system from the first lecture, which covers the propositional calculus and unspecified other areas, offering these as examples of transformation rules (among which he appears to include axiom schemata).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="Defining the Simple System">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Formation Rules">
<p>
Quine gives a lightweigh description of a simple language similar to one formally defined by Carnap.
</p><p>
The formation rules are rules governing how sentences may be constructed.
This involves primitive symbols (not defined, or given <i>implicit</i> definitions),
a range of defined logical or mathematical operators, and various <i>descriptive</i> operators
which permit the construction of <i>empirical sentences</i>.
</p><p>
Since explicit definitions are regarded as syntactic abbreviations, they fall under the heading of formation rules.
</p><p>
The formation rules define the notion of <i>sentence</i> for the language in question.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Transformation Rules">
<p>
The purpose of the transformation rules is to infer rather than to construct sentences,
and they serve as implicit definitions of the primitive symbols,
However, Quine says we can go as far as we like with these transformation rules,
"Where we stop in this process is an arbitrary matter to be decided by pragmatic considerations"
(i.e. not confined to what would normally be considered definition?).
</p><p>
The transformation rules define a relation of <i>immediate consequence</i> between sets of
sentences (the premises) and sentences (the conclusion).
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Quine's Blurring of Consequence">
<p>Quine confesses that he is blurring over the distinction in Carnap between to
difference kinds of transformation rule, those defining consequence and those
defining deducibility.
The relation which Quine is calling <i>consequence</i> is Carnap's derivability,
Quine claims.
</p><p>
The divergence with Carnap is worse than Quine admits in that case.
Carnap has a set of d-terms which arise from the notion of derivability and
a set of c-terms which arise from the broader notion of consequence (which
is are syntactic surrogates for semantic properties).
Most of the derived notions mentioned by Quine are defined in terms of
consequence, not in terms of derivation, i.e. they are <i>c-terms</i>, not
<i>d-terms</i> as Quine seems to be suggesting.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Derivative Notions">
<p>
Various <i>derivative notions</i> then become definable for each language in terms
of the notions of <i>sentence</i> and <i>immediate consequence</i>.
</p><p>
These include:
<ul>
<li>analytic - a sentence which is a consequence of every sentence</li>
<li>contradictory - a sentence of which every other sentence is a consequence</li>
<li>synthetic - a sentence which is neither analytic nor contradicatory</li>
<li>syntactic category - a group of syntactically interchangeable expressions, salva well-formedness</li>
<li>synonymity - symbols whose interchange yields mutually derivable sentences</li>
<li>content - the set of non-analytic consequences of a sentence</li>
<li></li>
</ul>
</p><p>
Quine makes a particular point of the arbitrary nature of analytic truth here stating that
"it is a matter of linguistic convention what truths turn out to be analytic and what ones do
not, it depends how we frame our definitions".
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Truth of Synthetic Propositions">
Page 79 last para.
Quine here says "in fact, the separation of synthetic proposition into into true and false cannot
be carried out at all within a more formally syntactic approach such as I am now engaged in".
And generally, I have found no mention in Quine of Carnap's P-rules the purpose of which is to formulate
empirical scientific laws or facts.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Arithmetisation of Syntax">
Quine provides a sketch of the method of arithmetisation used by Carnap to formalise the syntactic
concepts in his language (at least, the d-concepts, though Quine doesn't go into that).
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>


</section>

<section title="Lecture III: Philosophy as Syntax">
<abstract>
Here Quine tells the story of how these syntactic methods are to transform philosophy.
</abstract>

<secbody title="Recap of General Background">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="the recap">
<p>
Quine begins with the "expository fiction" that we have to hand that collection
of sentences which we accept as true and are embarking on the construction of an
explicit formalization of the language.
</p><p>
This is to be a set of implicit and explicit definitions consistent with the past
usage represented by the set of accepted truths.
</p><p>
We are reminded that this process can go as far as we find convenient, and that how
far we go determines the extent to which the analytic is extended
"at the expense of the synthetic".
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Some commentary">
<p>
We are reminded here that the process involves making a choice about which sentences
are to be analytic, and that as we do so we add rules the effect of which is to
render analytic sentences which had hitherto been synthetic.
</p><p>
I don't think that this is the way in which Carnap saw the process.
</p><p>
The main bulk of the definitions of the transformation rules is in lock-step
with additions to the formation rules, since it is done by explicit definitions
which introduce new constants and give explicit values for those constants.
This does not result in the reclassification of sentences which were previosly
synthetic as analytic, but rather introduces new sentences of which those which
are true are analytic truths.
</p><p>
Carnap's definition of synthetic truth is clearly framed in the expectation
that abstract entities are defined completely (explicitly, except for the few
primitive logical constants) on introduction of the terms, so that there are no
sentences only involving abstract entities which are synthetic.
</p><p>
Synthetic sentences only appear when descriptive constants are introduced.
Primitive descriptive constants are given P-rules rather than L-rules as
implicit "definitions", though it is more appropriate to think of these
as fundamental physical laws than as definitions, and there are therefore
no new analytic sentences except those involving only vacuous occurrences
of those new constants.
Non-primitive descriptive constants are defined explicitly in terms of
primitive descriptive constants,
This will introduce new analytic and new synthetic truths, but only
truths which are mere abbreviations of previously available analytic
or synthetic truths.
This does not result in any reclassifications of sentences.
</p><p>
Quine's explanatory fiction is widely out of line with any reasonable
approach to formalising the language of mathematics and science, and
is very misleading in its suggestion that the epistemic status of sentences
is arbitrarily selected. 
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="Quine's Concern in this Lecture">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
In a single paragraph (top of page 88) Quine gives an illuminating
concise statement of what is concerned with in the third of his lectures,
which I will precis here, and comment on.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Precis">
<p>
Quine first remarks that in our general thinking "we seem invariably" to come against
non-empirical philosophic problems which cannot permanently be "swept aside",
If philosophy is syntax then we must either solve these problems using syntactic
methods or throwing them out as illusory meaningless questions.
</p>
<p>
He proposes to test whether philosophy as syntax is a constructive or a "merely negative"
doctrine by showing in detail how these problems appear when approached from the syntactic
viewpoint.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Commentary">
<p>
Quine has laid the ground here for an critique of Carnap's method along the
lines that it rejects as meaningless substantive philosophical problems.
</p><p>
In the context of Quine's own account of the method so far it is hard to see
how such a criticism could be established, for Quine has made it appear that
Carnap's method can be used to bring into the syntactic fold pretty much any
problem at all, by putting forward rules which render analytic whatever answer
may be preferred. 
</p><p>
If however, one takes seriously (despite Quine not having even mentioned these
constraints), that L-rules should serve only to capture the <i>meanings</i>
of the terms introduced, and that any synthetic facts or laws should be
expressed by P-rules (which Quine has not mentioned) which in turn should be
empirically based, then there might be the possibility of a criticism for failure
to address some problem in metaphysics.
</p><p>
The constraint of L-rules to meaning is hard to maintain however at this stage in
the development of Carnap's philosophy, it is more arguable that it is a weakness
at this stage that that constraint is not presented, leaving open the criticism
that the syntactic methods allow the arbitrary misclassification of synthetic
propositions as logical truths.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="Syntactic and Quasi Syntactic properties">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Narrative">
<p>
Quine now addresses what may be thought the core of Carnap's Logical Syntax via
the ideas of syntactic and quasi syntactic properties, and the way in which
talk of semantic notions such as meaning can be replaced by talk about syntactic
properties.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Commentary">
<p>
I have the impression here, for the first time in these lectures, that Quine really
is onboard, and really does like elimination of concepts such as "meaning" in favour
of syntactic properties, at pretty much every stage hitherto I see Quine as giving
qualified assent, or even as (possibly unwittingly) offering a caricature.
</p><p>
Sadly, for the possibility of a rapprochement, these are the very elements of Carnap's
Logical Syntax which are discarded when Carnap (possibly under the influence of Quine's
critique both here and in "Truth by Convention") moved on from Logical Syntax to embrace
semantics, and thence admit abstract entities in a wholehearted pragmatic
(rather than metaphysical) way.
(Arguably this is needed to make clear the character which L-rules must have and thereby
defend against the suggestion by Quine that the formulation of L-rules arbitrarily
reclassifies synthetic sentences as analytic.)
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

</xldoc>



