<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: forster92.xml,v 1.1 2006/10/22 13:38:39 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Notes on: Set Theory with a Universal Set"
       created="2006-06-16"
       description="Notes on Forster's 'Set Theory with a Universal Set'."
       keywords="logic set theory universal set"
       class="bib"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center">Notes by RBJ on<br/>Set Theory with a Universal Set - Exploring an Untyped Universe<br/>by Thomas Forster</maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
This is an essay about certain kinds of set theory, not an introduction, a tutorial or even a textbook.
It is written for people who already have quite a good knowledge of logic and set theory (better than mine).
These notes are not likely to be much use to anyone else, I'm definitely out of my league here.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title=""/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
This is a technical rather than an informal introduction, except for the first few pages, and includes annotated definitions, motivation, axioms, a survey, a discussion of paradox avoidance and a chronology.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Preliminaries">
<p>
The intial discussion has a couple of asides which struck me, neither central.
</p><p>
He says that the viewpoint that sets are predicates in extension is one "which tends to be held by logicists", and leads one "naturally" to want the universe to be a set.
</p><p>
The second point I note is his observation of well founded set theories that "whatever we startd off trying to say, the result is always liable to be (equivalent to) a large cardinal axiom".
If you change that to "equiconsistent with" it becomes more solid, but less impressive.
Otherwise, there are these things which interest me and which I am inclined to call fatness or width axioms (but which don't seem to have an accepted general name).
</p> 
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
