<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: kripke1980.xml,v 1.2 2009/12/16 21:55:38 rbj Exp $"
       title="Notes on - Naming and Necessity"
       created="2009-03-19"
       description="Notes on Saul Kripke's Naming and Necessity"
       keywords="philosophy Kripke epistemology necessity priori reference"
       class="bib"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center"><image name="lgnote.gif"/>
  by <xlink href="../../rbj.htm"><image name="rbjin1.gif" border="0"/></xlink>
  on<br/>Naming and Necessity<br/>by Saul Kripke</maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>.
Notes on selected parts of Kripke's celebrated lectures.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Preface" />
<secref title="Lecture I" />
<secref title="Lecture II" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Lecture III" />
<subsec title="Addenda" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
My comments initially are on the parts which were selected for publication in a
collection called "A Priori knowledge" edited by Paul K.Moser.
These are: pp34-39, 48-60, 53-58, 99-105 and 108-109.
They are clearly identified below, in the context of the lecture of which they
are a part. 
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Lecture I" tag="LI">
<abstract>
pp22-70::
A Priori, Necessary, Analytic.
Rigid Designators, Transworld Identity, Stipulation.
Names, Descriptions and Rigid Designation.
</abstract>
<secbody title="pp21-33: Names, Descriptions and Rigid Designation">
<sbcol/>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
Here Kripke discusses philosophical theories in which names are held
to behave like descriptions or clusters of descriptions, and the contrary
idea that names are "rigid designators", referring to the same thing in
every possible world.
</p><p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol/>

</secbody>
<secbody title="pp34-39: A Priori, Necessary, Analytic">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="A Priori">
<p>
Kripke devotes one paragraph to explaining the concept of the <i>a priori</i>
and ends with the view that it might be best:
<quote>".. to stick to the question of whether a particular person or knower
  knows something <i>a priori</i> or believes it true on the basis of <i>a
    priori</i> evidence." 
</quote>
He has abandoned, <i>ab inito</i> any attempt to make sense of the <i>a
  priori</i> as an objective classification of propositions.
So we might wonder what relevance the sequel might have to anyone whose interest is
confined to these concepts as classifications for propositions, and wonder what is the
point in comparing these concepts with that of necessity if they do not classify propositions.
</p>
<p>
Not content with failing to provide an account of <i>a priori</i> as a
classifier of propositions he then devotes one paragraph to arguing, in effect
that this cannot be done.
i.e. he rejects the idea that if something can be known <i>a priori</i> then it
cannot be known <i>a posteriori</i>.
</p>
<p>
In arguing the case his examples glide effortlessly between observations about
a priori <i>belief</i> and a priori <i>knowledge</i> in such a way as to make
me suspect that he considers the epistemic status of knowledge to be the same
as the epistemic status of the belief.
</p>
<p>
He does not appear to consider the possibility that the <i>justification</i>
which may be thought necessary for the belief to be considered knowledge might have a role
to play in determining epistemic status.
</p>
<p>
By contast, I believe that for the concept of the <i>a priori</i> to work best
it should not be used at all as a qualifier of beliefs, and its use in relation
to knowledge should be to qualify the <i>justification</i> on the basis of which the
knowledge is supposed to have been established.
Finally, we might add, that knowledge is only true knowledge if its supposed justification does in fact justify, and that this will only be the case if the justification offered is appropriate to the subject matter of the proposition in question.
If the proposition makes a substantive claim about the world, then an <i>a
    posteriori</i> justification might be expected, otherwise only an <i>a priori</i>
justification is required if the necessity or analyticity of the claim is to be established (though an a posteriori justification might possibly suffice to demonstrate its truth).
Thus, for a belief to be knowledge, its justification <i>must</i> be
epistemically appropriate, and the kind of justification involved has little to
do with how anyone may have come to believe the proposition.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Necessary">

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="pp48-50: Rigid Designators, Transworld Identity, Stipulation">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="pp53-58: Names, Descriptions and Rigid Designation">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="Comparison of Kripke and Carnap on Specific Examples">
<sbcol title="Page">
<subsec>
54-56
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="Example">
<subsec>
<p>
Meter rod (S at time t<sub>0</sub>) used to define the rigid designation of "Meter".
</p><p>
Status of propositon "S is one meter in length at time t<sub>0</sub>".
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="Kripke">
<subsec>
The proposition is contingent.
Kripke does not say whether it is synthetic, my guess is that he would say it is.
The person who makes the definition knows the propositon <i>a priori</i>.
He doesn't say this but it follows that others know it <i>a posteriori</i>, so it is both an <i>a priori</i> truth and an <i>a posteriori</i> truth.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="Carnap">
<subsec>
On the hypothesis that meter is a rigid designator, the statement is contingent, synthetic and <i>a posteriori</i>.
The rationale for considering it <i>a posteriori</i> is that any justification of the claim depends 
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
28-29, 57-58, 
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
Hesperus = Phosphorous
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
93
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
A man might know Aristotle has some disjuncion of properties <i>a priori</i>
in some sense if he fixes the reference of 'Aristotle` as the man who did one of those things,
even though his posession of the property is not necessary.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
Kripke thinks perhaps the notion of <i>a priori</i> needs to be reformulated to avoid such cases,
but does not offer a reformulation.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
Carnap, I suggest, would not regard a sentence as a priori unless its truth could be justified
without reference to empirical observations, except such observations as may contribute to establishing
the <i>meaning</i> of the sentence.
In this case the meaning would have to be (or include) the constant function delivering the individual
in fact satisfying the disjunction of properties, which does not justify the claim that Aristotle does
satisfy that disjunction, the need for observation makes the result <i>a posteriori</i> whether or not
the person making the definition had prior knowledge of that fact.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

<section title="Lecture II" tag="LII">
<abstract>
pp71-105::
Identities Between Names
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="pp99-105: Identities Between Names">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Lecture III" tag="LIII">
<abstract>
pp106-155::
True Identities Between Names are Necessary
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="pp108-109: True Identities Between Names are Necessary">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
