<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: magee78.xml,v 1.2 2006/04/22 19:26:23 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Notes on - Men of Ideas"
       created="2006/2/20"
       description="Notes on Bryan Magee's dialogues with 15 leading philosophers."
       keywords="philosophy"
       class="bib"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center"><image name="lgnote.gif"/> by <image name="rbjin1.gif"/> on - Men of Ideas</maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
This is freely rewritten transcript of interviews with fifteen philosophers which took place in 1975-7 and were broadcast on BBC television in 1978.
It is a snapshot of the main varieties of western philosophy as they stood in 1975.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Isiah Berlin - Introduction to Philosophy" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Iris Murdoch - Philosophy and Literature" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Isiah Berlin - Introduction to Philosophy" tag="Berlin">
<abstract>
Why should anyone be interested in philosophy at all?
Why is it important?
What is it anyway?
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Iris Murdoch - Philosophy and Literature" tag="Murdoch">
<abstract>
Considering respects in which literature and philosophy may overlap.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
I found Iris to be not very impressive in this interview.
Iris seemed to have decided that literature which aims a delivering philosophy is generally bad literature, decided to avoid this mistake in her own philosophy, and taken limited interest in the efforts of others to make this work.
</p><p>
However, the defects of this lack-lustre interview are not all with Iris.
</p><p>
Though this was not long after the high noon of linguistic philosophy, the empoverished conceptions of both philosophers of the scope and methods of philosphy still seems remarkable to me. 
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Overlap">
I note here some of the more concrete information about which philosophers or novelists were thought to have done something which connected philosophy and literature.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Which Philosophers Wrote Well">
First, here is Magee's idea of which philosophers were good writers (without consideration of their status as philosophers).
First the great:
<ul>
<li>Plato</li>
<li>St. Augustine</li>
<li>Schopenhaeur</li>
<li>Nietzsche</li>
</ul>
Then the "very good":
<ul>
<li>Descartes</li>
<li>Pascal</li>
<li>Berkeley</li>
<li>Hume</li>
<li>Rousseau</li>
</ul>
He also mentions two nobel laureates, Russell and Sartre, without saying whether he thinks them good.
I won't report which he thought bad.
Later he mentions some works of literature which were philosophically motivated
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Attitudes of Philosophers to Literature or Art">
<ul>
<li>Plato - was hostile to artists</li>
<li>Schopenhaeur - regarded art as being central to human life</li>
<li>Marx(ism) - sought to enrol art as an instrument of social revolution</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Novelists with a Mission">
<ul>
<li>Dickens - social commentary promoting social reform</li>
<li>George Elliot - similar to Dickens but not always as "successful"</li>
<li>Tolstoy</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Novelists whose work has philosophical content">
<ul>
<li>Dostoevski - the greatest of all existentialist writers?</li>
<li>Jean Paui Sarte - particularly La Nausee</li>
<li>Proust - the nature of time</li>
<li>Stern - Tristram Shandy influences by Locke's ideas about association of ideas</li> 
<li>Tolstoy - a philosophy of history (inter alia)</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Philosophers who Wrote Novels">
<ul>
<li>Voltaire</li>
<li>Rousseau</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
