<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: sartre46.xml,v 1.1 2006/07/10 19:20:24 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Notes on - Existentialism &amp; Humanism"
       created="2006-06-16"
       description="Notes on Sartre's Existentialism &amp; Humanism."
       keywords="philosophy existentialsm humanism"
       class="bib"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center">Notes by RBJ on<br/>Existentialism &amp; Humanism<br/>by Jean-Paul Sartre</maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
A lecture originally given at the Club Maintenant, which contains a summary of Sartre's Existentialism responding to some common criticisms.
The book also includes a transcript of the discussion following a subsequent private re-run for his opponents.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Reproaches"/>
<subsec title="Two Kinds of Existentialism">
<p>
Viz. the Christians (Jaspers and Gabriel Marcel) and the Atheists (Heidegger, the French existentialists, Sarte).
</p><p>
They have in common, that <i>existence</i> comes before <i>essence</i>.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Definitions"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Reproaches">
<abstract>
Sartre's purpose is "to offer a defence of existentialism against several reproaches". 
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="quietism of despair">
<blockquote>"an invitation to people to live in quiteism of despair"</blockquote>
</subsec>
<subsec title="underlining the ignominious">
<blockquote>"reproached for having underlined all that is ignominious in the human situation"</blockquote>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="denial of reality">
<blockquote>"reproached as people who deny the reality and seriousness of human affaires"</blockquote>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Definitions">
<abstract>
Sartre's definitions of key concepts.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Existentialism">

</subsec>
<subsec title="Anguish">
This is an anguish which results from the profound sense of responsibility caused by his knowledge that when he commits himself he legislates for mankind. 
</subsec>
<subsec title="Abandonment">
<blockquote>
"When we speak of 'abandonment' ... we only mean to say that God does not exist, and it is necessary to draw the consequences of his absence right to the end."
</blockquote>
The consequences seem primarily for Sartre to be that there are no absolute moral values which we might use to guide our conduct.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Despair">
<blockquote>
"... merely means that we limit ourselves to a reliance upon that which is within our wills, or within the sum of the probabilities that render our action feasible."
</blockquote>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
