<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: wiley52.xml,v 1.2 2009/03/01 15:32:40 rbj Exp $"
       title="Notes on: The Subtle Knot"
       created="2007/01/29"
       description="Notes on Wiley's 'The Subtle Knot'."
       keywords="philosophy literature scepticism seventeenth century"
       class="bib"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center">Notes by RBJ on<br/>The Subtle Knot<br/>by Margaret L.Wiley</maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
My impressions of this book, of which I have read only a part, are faint and unreliable.
I will record them here as I disengage without completing the book.
</p><p>
The book presents itself as primarily about scepticism in the seventeenth century as it appears combined with faith in the literature of the period.
As a sceptic and a non-believer, someone lacking and understanding of poetry, I proceded in the hope that there would be something to learn about scepticism, which there is.
</p><p>
Eventually however, I came to the view that this was not a wholehearted scepticism, either in the author or in the subjects of the book, and that there was too little to be learned from it by one inclined in religion to disbelief rather than faith.
</p><p>
I found in these pages little sign of religious doubt, and it seems that this scepticism is the scepticism of men whose inclination to believe runs deep and who find scepticism a useful weapon against considertaions which might otherwise threaten to undermine their belief
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
The central symbol of the book, the subtle knot, symbolises the relationship between flesh and spirit, which the author considers the centre of the scepticial stance.
This however seems to me to have no bearing on scepticism.
Surely this symbolises an attitude toward some aspects of religious belief?
(bearing in mind that the "duality" here, a central theme for the book, is not the less religiously oriented Cartesian duality between mind and body)
</p><p>
Perhaps the author was unwittingly drawn into a conception of scepticism too greatly tainted by its association with faith, for her interest was she says drawn by the coexistence of faith and scepticisim in some of the literary figures of the seventeenth century.
My impression is that she has studied and presented these sceptics too exclusively.
She has presented them, to be sure, in the context of a history of scepticism, but the history is lightly drawn and the subsequent detailed examination of the five chosen "sceptics" compares them among themselves rather than with sceptics who lack their faith.
</p>
<p>
<i>[Since I wrote the above I have read "Fram Savonarola to Bayle" bu Richard
  Popkin and am better acquainted with the revival of Pyrrhonism and its role
  in religious controversy in the seventeenth century.]</i>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Ch.2 An Historical Definition of Scepticism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Ch.3 Seventeenth Century Scepticism: The Knot"/>
<secref title=""/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p> 
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Ch.2 An Historical Definition of Scepticism" tag="2">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol title="Greek Scepticism">
<subsec title="Pyrrho">
</subsec>
<subsec title="The New Academy">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Sextus Empiricus">
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Knot">
<blockquote>
As our blood labours to beget<br/>
Spirits, as like souls it can,<br/>
Because such fingers need to knit<br/>
That subtile knot, which makes us man:<br/>
So must pure lovers souls descend<br/>
T'affections, and to faculties,<br/>
Which sense may reach and apprehend,<br/>
Else a great Prince in prison lies.
</blockquote>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="The Middle Ages">
<subsec title="Augustine">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Arnobius">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Abelard">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Dualism">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Nicholas of Cusa">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol title="The Renaissance">
<subsec title="Phyrrhonism in France">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Deism">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Italian Scepticism">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Erasmus and Galileo">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Raleigh and Montaigne">
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Sceptic Pattern">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="">
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Ch.3 Seventeenth Century Scepticism: The Knot" tag="3">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title=""> 
WHERE, like a pillow on a bed,	 <br/>
  A Pregnant banke swel'd up, to rest	<br/> 
The violets reclining head,	 <br/>
  Sat we two, one anothers best.	<br/> 
Our hands were firmely cimented	         5<br/>
  With a fast balme, which thence did spring,	<br/> 
Our eye-beames twisted, and did thred	 <br/>
  Our eyes, upon one double string;	 <br/>
So to'entergraft our hands, as yet	 <br/>
  Was all the meanes to make us one,	  10<br/>
And pictures in our eyes to get	 <br/>
  Was all our propagation.	 <br/>
As 'twixt two equall Armies, Fate	<br/> 
  Suspends uncertaine victorie,	 <br/>
Our soules, (which to advance their state,	  15<br/>
  Were gone out,) hung 'twixt her, and mee.	 <br/>
And whil'st our soules negotiate there,	 <br/>
  Wee like sepulchrall statues lay;	 <br/>
All day, the same our postures were,	 <br/>
  And wee said nothing, all the day.	  20<br/>
If any, so by love refin'd,	 <br/>
  That he soules language understood,	<br/> 
And by good love were growen all minde,	 <br/>
  Within convenient distance stood,	 <br/>
He (though he knew not which soule spake,	  25<br/>
  Because both meant, both spake the same)	 <br/>
Might thence a new concoction take,	 <br/>
  And part farre purer then he came.	 <br/>
This Extasie doth unperplex	 <br/>
  (We said) and tell us what we love,	  30<br/>
Wee see by this, it was not sexe,	 <br/>
  Wee see, we saw not what did move:	 <br/>
But as all severall soules containe	 <br/>
  Mixture of things, they know not what,	<br/> 
Love, these mixt soules, doth mixe againe,	  35<br/>
  And makes both one, each this and that.	 <br/>
A single violet transplant,	 <br/>
  The strength, the colour, and the size,	<br/> 
(All which before was poore, and scant,)	 <br/>
  Redoubles still, and multiplies.	  40<br/>
When love, with one another so	 <br/>
  Interinanimates two soules,	 <br/>
That abler soule, which thence doth flow,<br/>	 
  Defects of lonelinesse controules.	 <br/>
Wee then, who are this new soule, know,	  45<br/>
  Of what we are compos'd, and made,	 <br/>
For, th'Atomies of which we grow,	 <br/>
  Are soules, whom no change can invade.	<br/> 
But O alas, so long, so farre	 <br/>
  Our bodies why doe wee forbeare?	  50<br/>
They are ours, though they are not wee, Wee are	 <br/>
  The intelligences, they the spheare.	 <br/>
We owe them thankes, because they thus,	 <br/>
  Did us, to us, at first convay,	 <br/>
Yeelded their forces, sense, to us,	  55<br/>
  Nor are drosse to us, but allay.	 <br/>
On man heavens influence workes not so,	 <br/>
  But that it first imprints the ayre,	 <br/>
Soe soule into the soule may flow,	 <br/>
  Though it to body first repaire.	  60<br/>
As our blood labours to beget	 <br/>
  Spirits, as like soules as it can,	<br/> 
Because such fingers need to knit	 <br/>
  That subtile knot, which makes us man:	<br/> 
So must pure lovers soules descend	  65<br/>
  T'affections, and to faculties,	 <br/>
Which sense may reach and apprehend,	 <br/>
  Else a great Prince in prison lies.	 <br/>
To'our bodies turne wee then, that so	 <br/>
  Weake men on love reveal'd may looke;	  70<br/>
Loves mysteries in soules doe grow,	 <br/>
  But yet the body is his booke.	 <br/>
And if some lover, such as wee,	 <br/>
  Have heard this dialogue of one,	<br/> 
Let him still marke us, he shall see	  75<br/>
  Small change, when we'are to bodies gone.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
