<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xart002.xml,v 1.1 2009/05/04 21:22:18 rbj Exp $"
       title="Expressionism"
       description="Ideas about expressionism in the arts broadly conceived."
       keywords="writing music art philosopy expressionism"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
An attempt to tie together conceptions of expressionism in various different
domains.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Art"/>
<secref title="Music"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Literature"/>
<secref title="Philosophy"/>
<secref title="Life"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
Self expression is a basic human need.
We don't all need it in the same way (it is of its nature personal) or to the
same extent but in some way, to some extent it is an essential part of what we
are.
It is my aim in writing this page to think this through, partly by gathering
together its diverse manifestations, and to see whether some insights might
come out of it that may be helpful in doing it better.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Origins">
<p>
There is some point in considering the origins of the need for self expression.
I can only speculate about this, but my speculations influence my perspective
on self-expression and so whether sound or not (you may make your own
judgement) they are a useful bit of context.
</p><p>
I understand the need for self-expression as profoundly ingrained in us all by
the process of evolution.
It is a part of our social being which can be traced back to
the very earliest stages in the evolution of life.
One of the earliest life forms is bacterial, and even these early bacterial are
engineered as social beings.
They live in colonies, and they are engineered for the benefit of the colony.
</p><p>
When such bateria reproduce they produce offspring which differ depending upon
whether food is plentiful or scarce at the time of reproduction.
If food is plentiful the offspring are designed to feed and reproduce rapidly
so that the colony grows.
When food is scarce the offspring are designed for finding new resources.
They explore for food, and they emit chemical messages which signal whether
they are or are not sucessful.
</p><p>
This is a mode of self expression in organisms so primitive (unicellular) that they have no
nervous system. 
</p><p>
From these primitive beginnings, sociality has evolved continuously, exploiting
to the full the development from instinctual to more advanced forms of adaptive
behaviour, has played a role in the evolution of intelligence, and is now
deeply engrained in out being.
Two complementary aspects of our being work together in this.
Self expression is closely coupled with self selection.
Each of us seeks that place in society where we can be of greatest benefit,
selecting for him or herself that place, albeit after an extended and
excruciating search.
Thoughout this process we continuously signal to those around us who we are and
how well we are succeeding in finding that place.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Kinds of Expressionism">
<p>
I'm using this term very loosely and rather personally here.
Loosely because I talk under this heading of <i>Wu Wei</i> a concept from Tao
which is more often described as <i>spontaneity</i> than as self expression,
and of a generalised notion of <i>stream of consciousness</i> a literary style,
of an approach to philosophy for which I am groping, and of a way of life which
is itself a kind of philosophy.
</p><p>
Where the term has been used by others, in art and music for example, I do not
use it in the same sense, for what expressionism involves depends upon what
these others who have chosen the word have inside them to express, and often
these are extreme.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Art">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Music">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Literature">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Philosophy">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Life">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



