<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xart001.xml,v 1.2 2009/05/06 10:02:41 rbj Exp $"
       title="The Art of Hainee-Jo Summers"
       description="A personal appreciation.of the art of Hainee-Jo Summers"
       keywords="art expressionism fauvism Hainee-Jo Summers"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Background"/>
<secref title="Visiting the Studio"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Expressionism"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Background">
<abstract>
How I came to write this page.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
I have never before written about art, not at least, concrete art rather than
art in the abstract.
Nor has it ever occurred to me that I might, that I have anything to say about
the works of particular artists that might conceivably be of interest.
</p><p>
This with good cause, for I have never done art.
Not at least, visual art, as
opposed to works in the various other art forms such as music and literature.
Nor have I studied it, though I have picked up some slight appreciation of some
parts of its history.
</p><p>
That I embark on this improbable enterprise does not mark a change in any of
these disqualications, or even despite it all, that I have something to say
which lovers of art will find to be interesting (though I don't rule that out).
</p><p>
It is more from compulsion that conviction that I now embark on this modest piece
of, what might be called, <i>na&icirc;ve</i> art criticism.
</p><p>
I visited the artists "cottage studio" in the expectation of being at best
pleasantly impressed (as is my usual fate on these occasions), and found myself
thinking as if I were in the face of great art in my backyard.
I don't imagine myself qualified to judge whether art is "great" or not (not
that I am convinved anyone else is), so I am not here to tell you that
Hainee-jo is a new Picasso.
</p><p>
Still, I am going to talk as if she were, for that is how I
found myself thinking, and it is my purpose here not to tell you the truth
about Hainee-Jo's art, but to tell you the truth about how and what it made me feel and think.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
One weekend not so long ago in Lincolnshire, a number of local artists opened
their studios as part of an enterprise entitled "Art on the Map".
Having been out to support our grandson's football team, my wife and I took in
a couple of studios on our way home.
</p><p>
The second was Hainee-Jo's in the small Lincolnshire village of Fulbeck.
Toad Hall is a tiny cottage which makes the traditional "two-up two-down"
terraced house seem palatial.
It is one-and-half up and down, for there are just two rooms at about 9 feet
square, (one up one down) and some more space which might be 9 by 6.
The two larger rooms were galleries, the smaller space on the ground floor was
both lobby and what passed for a kitchen.
upstairs this must have been in two parts, for I recall at the front the room
which was presented as a studio, at about 6 foot square, and I imagine the
remaining space may have been a tiny bathroom.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Visiting the Studio">
<abstract>
My fist acquaintance with Hainee-Jo's art.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Expressionism">
<abstract>
Some reflections.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">

</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



