<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xart001.xml,v 1.4 2009/07/14 14:26:10 rbj Exp $"
       title="The Art of Haidee-Jo Summers"
       description="A personal appreciation.of the art of Haidee-Jo Summers"
       keywords="art expressionism fauvism Haidee-Jo Summers"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Recounting an experience.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Background"/>
<secref title="Visiting the Studio"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Expressionism"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Background">
<abstract>
How I came to write this page.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Naive Art Criticism">
<p>
I have never before written about art.
Not at least "Art" (the visual) rather than other arts or "The Arts".
Nor had it occurred to me that I might; that I have anything to say about
the works of particular artists that might be of interest.
</p><p>
This with good cause, for I have neither done it nor studied it (in any
earnest), so I am well disqualified from speaking.
</p><p>
That I embark on this improbable enterprise does not mark a change in any of
these disqualifications, or even despite it all, that I have something to say
which lovers of art will find to be interesting (though I don't rule that out).
</p>
<p>
It is more from compulsion than conviction that I now embark on this modest piece
of, what might be called, <i>na&icirc;ve</i> art criticism.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Great Art">
<p>
I visited the artists "cottage studio" in the expectation of being at best
pleasantly impressed (as is my usual fate on these occasions), and found myself
thinking as if I were in the face of great art in my backyard.
I don't imagine myself qualified to judge whether art is "great" or not (not
that I am convinced anyone else is), so I am not here to tell you that
Haidee-Jo is a new Picasso.
</p><p>
Still, I'm going to talk as if she were, for that is how I
found myself thinking, and it is my purpose here not to tell you the truth
about Haidee-Jo's art, but to tell you the truth about how and what it made me feel and think.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Expressionism">
<p>
I suppose I should confess that beyond the compulsion, perhaps contributing to
it, I have an interest in something I call (mostly just to myself) "expressionism",
tenuously connected with artistic movements using that word, but spanning all
the arts and philosophy, and life.
Haidee-Jo's art I took to be expressionist in this very general sense, and
talking about it gives another perspective and perhaps another toe hold on
these tenuous ideas.
</p><p>
But there is something else.
The work, the artist, between them, somehow, impressed themselves upon me in
ways which I do not understand.
This is some token of that impression.
An attempt to understand it, and a gesture of appreciation, for what she has
given in her work.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Visiting the Studio">
<abstract>
My first acquaintance with Haidee-Jo's art.
</abstract>
<secbody title="The Cottage">
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
One weekend not so long ago in Lincolnshire, a number of local artists opened
their studios as part of an enterprise entitled "Art on the Map".
Having been out to support our grandson's football team, my wife and I took in
a couple of studios on our way home.
</p><p>
The second was Haidee-Jo's in the small Lincolnshire village of Fulbeck.
Toad Hall is a tiny cottage which makes the traditional "two-up two-down"
terraced house seem palatial.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
It is one-and-half up and down, for there are just two rooms at about 9 feet
square, (one up one down) and some more space which might be 9 by 6.
The two larger rooms were galleries, the smaller space on the ground floor was
both lobby and what passed for a kitchen.
upstairs this must have been in two parts, for I recall at the front the room
which was presented as a studio, at about 6 foot square, and I imagine the
remaining space may have been a tiny bathroom.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="The Art">
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
The exhibition was of course mainly housed in the two largest rooms, one up,
one down.
As a casual observer of art, I usually move through a gallery expeditiously,
and I have no recollection at all of what I felt about the first of the two
"large" rooms, though it must have set my temper for appreciating the works to
follow.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Sunflowers">
<p>
In the upstairs room, my attention was immediately seized by the largest piece
in the exhibition, of a woman standing in front of a field of sunflowers.
The painting, perhaps 3x4 feet, dominates one wall of this tiny gallery (I
think there may have been two doors in the wall).
Sunflowers naturally bring Van Gogh into mind, and the manner of their
presentation was, if not a mimic of Van Gogh, at least in the spirit, speaking
confidently out from the canvas.
</p><p>
My eye was drawn quickly from the sunflowers to the woman, particularly to the
arm. held horizontally across her waist.
It stood out from the canvas.
My eyes are not so good, not dreadful but well below average, and I am looking
at the arm trying to decide if it really is in relief.
I have to move closer to the canvas to settle the matter and establish that the
canvas really is flat.
</p><p>
This too we know from Van Gogh, most conspicuous in the exaggerated perspective
of his wicker chair.
But I never found in Van Gogh the same sense that the objects in the painting
really were jumping out of the page, (perhaps I have seen these paintings to
often in books rather than in the flesh), perhaps Van Gogh's exaggerations
go beyond what the eye can credit, nonetheless to good expressive effect.
<p></p>
In Haidee-Jo's painting of the sunflower field the effect is too local, it
draws the eye too forcibly to the forearm of the woman, a place where it only
belongs because of this impressive technical effect.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Window">
<p>
I am now I think, becoming more seriously engaged, and as I survey the
paintings on the opposite wall of the room I am aware that I am peering closely
(my eyes) and at uncharacteristic length.
</p><p>
The largest and most impressive of these is a view from a house into a garden.
The window through which we see the garden benefits from the same technique,
the window sill standing out from the canvas.
This feature extends across the larger part of the canvas, sloping up and away,
and the effect is better balanced than in the sunflower field.
</p><p>
The other more pervasive effect which suffuses the picture comes from the colours,
with which the picture glows.
If this follows Van Gogh in being a work of expression, it is a far cry from
the turbulence we often find there; it expresses something sublime, glowing
beyond contentment.
</p><p>
Can art be as great when it flows from peace as from torment?
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="......................">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Great Art">
<p>Oh, dear.
That word again.
And who am I?
</p><p>
I am reaching the end of my uncharacteristically intense examination of the
paintings on the wall opposite to the sunflowers.
On the left, high up, a small abstract in which colours must do all the work.
And I realise that I am thinking about these pieces in just the way I would
when passing in a national gallery through the parts which I love the best.
I am feeling, this is as good as it gets, my appreciation in this medium knows
no better.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Portrait">
<p>
Just one more painting to mention.
We are now out of the main rooms in a smaller room at the front which is
presented as the artists studio, with a work table sporting the accoutrements
of an artist, and works in progress.
</p><p>
On the floor, unframed, leaning against the wall is a self-portrait of
Haidee-Jo, which I have subsequently christened to myself "La Demoiselle de
Fulbeck".
It is at once realistic, and surreal.
Words fail me.
I long to have it.
There is no price.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Demoiselle D'Avignon">
<p>
Almost involuntarily I have called Haidee-Jo's self-portrait "La Demoiselle",
though she is not.
</p><p>
It reminds me of, Picasso's seminal work which lead the way into Cubism.
It strikes me in the same way, as leading from an expressionism in which colour
and perspective are the vehicles, into a more integrated expressionistic style.
 </p><p>
Picasso's transition under the influence of Cezanne, and of his then recent
exposure to African art, took art from the expressionism of fauvism into
something more abstract and more intellectual and more?
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Expressionism">
<abstract>
Some reflections.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">

</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
