<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       created="2006-3-13"
       id="$Id: xwri002.xml,v 1.3 2006/05/25 15:43:00 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Stream of Consciousness"
       description="Stream of Consciousness and its interpretation at RBJones.com"
       keywords="writing"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
A discussion of the literary style known as "stream of consciousness" and an elaboration of this which I am aiming to use on this website. 
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
This is a discussion of a way of writing philosophy, not entirely dissimilar to the literary style called "stream of consiousness" adopted by (among others) Virginia Woolf.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
Fiction and philosophy are not similar, so its not obvious that a technique which works for writing novels can be applied to philosophy.
This is nevertheless what I am attempting.
To get these two to fit together, something has to give, and what gives is both. 
</p>
<p>

</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Technique in Literature">
This is what <i>The Penguin Companion to Literature</i> says about <i>Mrs Dalloway</i>:
<blockquote>
Mrs Dalloway is the story of one day in the life of the heroine in which the impingement of past on present consciousness enables her to tell the whole of Mrs Dalloway's past by naturally developing flashbacks within consciousness.
</blockquote>
A special feature of the novel is that this medium permits an author to place his reader inside the mind of its subject's to experience their thoughts and feelings.
In <i>stream of consiousness</i> the entire story is delivered though the consiousness of the subject.
</subsec>

</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Stream of Consciousness" doc="rbj001" suf="htm"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



