<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       created="2006-3-13"
       id="$Id: xwri002.xml,v 1.2 2006/04/09 19:02:04 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Stream of Consciousness"
       description="Stream of Consciousness and its interpretation at RBJones.com"
       keywords="writing"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
A discussion of the literary style known as "stream of consciousness" and an elaboration of this which I am aiming to use on this website. 
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
In 1997 I was working full time for International Computers Limited.
I was 49 years old then, and I had decided to resign my position and launch out on my own on my 50th birthday.
Exactly what I was going to do was unclear, but it was going to be creative, and the main part of that creativity was to be some, or various, kinds of <i>writing</i>.
Among the various things I were software and philosophy.
I might say that writing software for bread and butter to make writing philosophy possible, but my conception of the relationship between the two was much more complex than that.
<p/>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
While I anticipated release from daily drudgery and the freedom to write, my mind went into overdrive on the ideas front, and a continuous stream of new ideas bubbling through my head whenever my attention elsewhere was not essential.
What I wanted most, was not so much to accomplish some grand opus, as to capture this process, this facility which I then felt of coming up with new and interesting perspectives on every problem I considered.
It was natural to consider the literary style of "Stream of Consiousess" and I gave that a bit of thought at the time.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Stream of Consciousness" doc="rbj001" suf="htm"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Structure" doc="rbj007" suf="htm"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



