<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: index.xml,v 1.1 2009/10/05 09:18:19 rbj Exp $"
       title="Books"
       created="1999/8/24"
       description="Some books ideas"
       keywords="writing"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Here are my (not very impressive) attempts at writing books.
Mostly in the form of aborted projects, but also, some ideas in progress. 
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Books in Progress on Metaphysical Positivism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Earlier Ideas"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
A few words on the evolution of my ideas for books.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
This directory contains material written in book format using LaTeX and
converted to PDF (using pdflatex) and/or into HTML (using latex2html).
This includes both "books" written by me and in some cases notes which I have written on books by others.
There really is not much material here at all, these are all pathetic little starts which get nowhere at all!
However, though I once thought of all my false starts as cul-de-sacs in a lengthy search for a viable projects, I can now see that they are all minor variations in the formulation of one project, which I will figure out how to do.
</p><p>
The material on "Philosophical Revolutions" was done in 1999, and my ostensible reason for abandoning this before it got very far was doubt about the historical content.
This was turning out to be a significant proportion of the whole, and I had little confidence in my ability to do this well.
In retrospect it now seems that there was a certain inevitability in my having at this time (though it was not to become conspicuous to me until the next year) a fairly comprehensive collapse in my confidence as a writer of any kind.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
The material on "Rationality and Utopia" was begun in 1999 as "Engineering the Future", (getting nowhere at all), resumed in 2002 under the title "Evolution, Rationality and Utopia" (the "evolution" bit arising from the influence of Howard Bloom's books), with some more work in 2005 dropping the "Evolution".
</p><p>
In 2008 I started the "Anarchy is Order" material, in my conception of which
material on evolution is pretty essential.
There is behind this much more in my utopian conception, but not much sign that
this will ever get onto paper.
Like a cat a played with this idea in my head, for a while convinced that it
would fly, but it did not, though I cherish the hope that something not to far
removed from it can be revived if I can first do some more theoretical work.
</p><p>
In 2009 I came to the opinion that I would have to do the theoretical
philosophy first, and that to do so required confrontation of Quine and Kripke
on the three classic dichotomies, analytic/synthetic, necessary/contingent, a
priori/a posteriori.
This set me out on a project at first entitled "The Fundamental
Triple-Dichotomy", but which quickly mutated into "Metaphysical Positivism" when I
reflected on the point of it all, and sought a purpose with broader appeal.
This is an approach to metaphysics which passes through (and fully embraces)
the positivist rejections to yield a subtler and more modest conception of
metaphysics.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Books in Progress on Metaphysical Positivism" doc="xb001" />

<section title="Earlier Ideas">
<abstract>
These ideas are not entirely dead, though they never got very far as book
projects.
Some of the ideas have evolved into the present projects of Metaphysical
Positivism.
Some of the projects here may yet be revived or merged into future projects going outside the
confines on analytic philosophy.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Anarchy is Order - A Manifesto" doc="aoman/index" suf="htm">
Really a prospectus for a book of similar title, but masquerading as program of
action.
<p/>
(also available as <xlink href="aoman/manpam.pdf">A4 two-column pdf pamphlet</xlink>)
</subsec>
<subsec title="Anarchy is Order" doc="aobook/index" suf="htm">
This is about "practical" philosophy, influenced by Dao and anarchism.
<p/>
(also available as <xlink href="aobook/aopam.pdf">A4 two-column pdf pamphlet</xlink>)
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Philosophical Revolutions" doc="philrev/philrev" suf="htm">
An attempt to tell a story about what analytic philosophy might be, come the next revolution (<xlink href="philrev/philrev.pdf">pdf</xlink>).
</subsec>
<subsec title="Rationality and Utopia" doc="engfut/index" suf="htm">
The beginnings of a "utopian engineering" project (<xlink href="engfut/engfut.pdf">pdf</xlink>).
</subsec>
<subsec title="Wittgenstein's Place in 20th Century Analytic Philosophy"
	doc="wptcap/index" suf="htm">
My own study notes on this book by <bibref name="Hacker">P.M.S.Hacker</bibref>
{This wasn't ever intended as a book, its here just because I used latex2html
to make the HTML].
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



