<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xb001.xml,v 1.1 2009/09/16 09:46:49 rbj Exp $"
       title="Books in progress on Metaphysical Positivism"
       description="Some notes about two books presenting Metaphysical Positivism"
       keywords="writing"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Two books are in progress which together are intended to give an account of
metaphysical positivism and extended examples of the application of its
analytic method to philosophical problems.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Metaphysical Positivism"/>
<secref title="An Analytic History of Philosophical Logic"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
The two books consist of a short informal exposition and a more extended
exposition of the analytic method in application to problems of analytical
exegesis bearing upon the history of concepts and problems which underpin the method.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Presentation of Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
Our account of this philosophy falls into three parts.
</p><p>
The first two parts connect Metaphysical Positivism with its philosophical
roots by explaining how it first into the history of positivism and that of
metaphysics (which despite the recent coinage of "positivism" both extend back
through millenia).
</p><p>
Metaphysical positivism at the same time takes to their logical conclusion
certain idea key to positivism, as well as moderating features of positivism
most antagonistic to metaphysics.
</p><p>
The remaining part of the exposition hangs around a method of logical analysis.
The method itself is intended to enable rigour in the deductive parts of
philosophy, and to make rigourous analytic historical exegesis.
It is not confined to philosophy, but is intended for application wherever
deductive arguments may be thought beneficial.
</p><p>
An extended and comprehensive presentation of this method, embracing its
fundamental philosophical underpinnings and technical and philosophical
accounts of the way in which the method may be applied in metaphysics, analytic
philosophy, logic, mathematics, science and engineering provides the framework
for a broad coverage of the principles of Metaphysical Positivism.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Analytic Method applied to Historical Exegesis">

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<abstract>
I am at present working towards a book intended for publication as a POD
paperback provisionally entitled "Metaphysical Positivism".
<p/>
Though I have definite ideas about what I want to do in the book,
I am hoping to involve others in its creation through philosophical discussion and debate.
<p/>
This section provide access to drafts of the book in various forms and to
other related materials.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Presentations of The Book">
<p>
Several different formats of document are generated from the sources of the
book.
These different forms have the same content so you may read whichever format
you find most convenient.
All except the paperback book format are provided for you to read or download
for reading from this web site at no cost, and you are granted permission only
to read them, not to make any other use of them.
All formats will be available for drafts from the earliest stages of writing
the book, with the sole exception of the paperback format, which will become
available only when the book is deemed complete (-enough for the first edition).
</p><p>
The available formats are:
<ul>
<li><xlink href="ftd/index.htm">HTML</xlink> (produced by LaTeX2HTML)</li>
<li><xlink href="ftd/ftdpam.pdf">A4 PDF</xlink> two-column pamphlet</li>
</ul>
A link for buying the paperback from Amazon will be included when the book has
been published.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Other Materials">
I have a variety of other material on this topic which I am developing
concurrently with the book.
Some of these provide additional detail and discussion or background, others
present the material in different ways.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Scope of The Book">
Though entitled "Metaphysical Positivism", <i>the book</i> as at present conceived, is
not as broad as the conception of metaphysical positivism (incompletely) presented on the
RBJones.com web site.
The book project began as a monograph project specifically on "Hume's Fork" and
it was in trying to provide sufficient context for a proper understanding of
the significance of Hume's fork that I was lead into making "Metaphysical
Positivism" the headline.
Nevertheless, Hume's fork, with its apparent principle function of eliminating
metaphysics, is central to the account, and presented as the central feature of
positivist philosophy, and it is from an examination of what has happened
in the history of controversy over the fork that we come to understand in what
sense metaphysics is thereby eliminated, and in what sense there remains a
place for metaphysics on the high ground of philosophical enquiry.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Discussions">
I had hopes of vigorous discussion of the work in progress and my preferred
venue for this was the hist-analytic mailing list
(see <xlink href="http://rbjones.com/pipermail/hist-analytic_rbjones.com/">archives</xlink>).
I am now rather more pessimistic about the prospects for much worthwhile
discussion, but still happy to engage.
To subscribe to hist-analytic see <xlink href="http://hist-analytic.org/">hist-analytic.org</xlink>.
I am also willing to engage in private discussion, for which purpose I (rbj) may be
emailed at rbjones.com.
If you want to engage in some other forum, post your contribution to the forum and copy me.
I will then respond in the relevant forum, if appropriate.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="An Analytic History of Philosophical Logic" dir="../../philos/logic" doc="xpl001"/>

</xldoc>



