<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xpl003.xml,v 1.1 2009/07/14 14:26:10 rbj Exp $"
       title="History of Philosophical Logic - Part I"
       created="2009/7/13"
       description="A history of logic and of the concept of logical truth"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy analytic semantics meaning necessity logic metaphysics"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
First part of a history of Philosophical Logic reaching Russell's Logical
Atomism and Wittgenstein's Tractatus via Aristotle, Leibniz, Hume, Kant and Frege.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Plato and Aristotle"/>
<subsec title="Leibniz"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Hume and Kant"/>
<subsec title="Frege"/>
<subsec title="Russell and Wittgenstein"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
This presents an informal view of a project consisting of a selective history
of philosophical logic and related areas making use of a method for formal
logical analysis and providing the historical background underpinning and
leading to that method.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Scope and Emphasis">
<p>
The aim of this historical sketch is to examine the history of logic and
certain related areas with particular concern for the evolution of the concept
of logical truth, and related concepts.
These include the notion of empirical fact, the concepts if logical necessity, contingency,
analyticity, the synthetic.
The demarcation of logical truth involves semantics, and metaphysics, and our
story therefore embraces these closely related areas of logic and philosophy.  
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Presentation">
The full material, formal and informal, will be prepared chapter by chapter in
PDF documents which will be available from RBJones.com as they are prepared.
In addition informal accounts will be available here in HTML, often as sketches
before the detailed preparation.
Links on the list of chapters will reach the current PDF of any chapters which
I have made a start on.
Information presented here in HTML will include my ideas about what I should be
doing with a chapter before I actually start.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Chapters">
The full list will not be finalised for a while, but the earlier chapters are
pencilled in as:
<ol>
<li>Introduction</li>
<li><xlink href="../../pp/doc/t028.pdf">Plato and Aristotle</xlink></li>
<li>Leibniz</li>
<li>Hume and Kant</li>
<li>Frege</li>
<li><xlink href="../../pp/doc/t030.pdf">Russell and Wittgenstein</xlink></li>
</ol>
The book will probably come in two volumes, the first containing the main body
of the analysis, the second containing a set of listings of the formal theories
developed in the analysis.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Plato and Aristotle" doc="xpl002" tag="pa"/>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
