<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xpl004.xml,v 1.3 2009/10/12 11:22:44 rbj Exp $"
       title="An analytic History of Philosophical Analysis - Part II"
       created="2009/7/13"
       description="An Analytic history of philosophical analysis covering most of the twentieth century."
       keywords="rbjones philosophy analytic semantics meaning necessity logic
		 metaphysics Plato Aristotle"
       up="xpl001.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
The coverage of the twentieth century emphasises those aspects of the
development of philosophical analysis which have greatest relevance to the
method adopted in this analysis, "The Method of Logical Analysis", and
culminates with a full account of the method and some ideas about its scope of applicability, within analytic philosophy and elsewhere.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction" />
<subsec title="Carnap"/>
<subsec title="Quine"/>
<subsec title="Kripke"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Logicism"/>
<subsec title="Formalism"/>
<subsec title="Constructive Mathematics"/>
<subsec title="Structuralism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Set Theory"/>
<subsec title="Combinatory Logic"/>
<subsec title="Type Theories"/>
<subsec title="The Method"/>
<subsec title="Applications"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Some tentative ideas about what this part of the history might cover.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Main Thrust">
<p>In keeping with the purpose of the work as a whole, this will be a
selective history.
In the second half of the twentieth century an enormous variety of
logical systems were studied by philosophers.
However, the purpose of this history is to explore the ancestry of a point of
view from which this diversity of formal systems is of peripheral interest.
</p><p>
The explosion of interest in so called ``non-standard logics'' coincided with
the demise of any consensus on any systematic and pervasive role for logic in
philosophy of the kind advocated in the first half of the century by
philosophers such as Russell and Carnap.
</p><p>
Metaphysical Positivism revives the idea that the systematic exploitation of
methods based on logic might be a worthwhile feature of analytic philosophy.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Philosophical Thread">
<p>
The proximate ancestor of Metaphysical Positivism is Logical Positivism,
particularly as represented by the philosophy of Rudolf Carnap.
This is seen by many philosophers as having been refuted first by Quine, and
then by Kripke.
</p><p>
It is therefore important to present those aspects of Carnap's philosophy which
are of greatest relevance to this history, which are his concept of logical
truth, his views on semantics, and conception of formal methods for philosophy
and science.
</p><p>
Some presentation of Quine's critique of the analytic/synthetic distinction if
I can find any useful way of applying the method to these ideas.
In this I am handicapped by the low level of credence which I give to his
arguments and his alternative position.
</p><p>
Kripke's re-invention of metaphysics, though not to my taste, is at least more
promising from the point of view of obtaining interesting models. and it will
be of interest to contrast Kripke's conception of metaphysics with the that of
Metaphysical Positivism.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Methodological Thread">
<p>
This thread will be concerned with tracing the roots of our formal method, its
languages logics and supporting software, through the Twentieth Century.
</p><p>
This will involve an account of what we draw from both logicism and formalism,
together with something about why intuitionism is largely ignored.  
</p><p>
The line of descent of the version of Higher Order Logic will be traced, which
goes roughly:
<ul>
<li>Russell's Theory of Types</li>
<li>Ramsey's Simplification</li>
<li>Church's Lambda Calculus</li>
<li>Church's Simple Theory of Types</li>
<li>Milner's Polymorphic Type-System for LCF</li>
<li>Gordon's Polymorphic HOL</li>
<li>Set Theory in HOL</li>
</ul>
</p><p>
The culture of modelling by conservative extension, following Frege's idea
that:
<blockquote>
Mathematics = Logic + Definitions
</blockquote>
</p><p>
The implementation of software support in the form of the HOL proof assistant
and ProofPower
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
