<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xpl001.xml,v 1.2 2009/08/05 06:47:11 rbj Exp $"
       title="An Analytic History of Philosophical Logic"
       created="2009/7/3"
       description="A history of logic and of the concept of logical truth"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy analytic semantics meaning necessity logic metaphysics"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
A history of logic from a philosophical standpoint, with particular emphasis on
the evolution of the concept of logical truth.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Background"/>
<secref title="Part II - The Twentieth Century"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Part I - To The Tractatus"/>
<secref title="Part III - Theory Listings"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Background">
<abstract>
A few words on the purposes and character of the proposed history.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Purpose and Character">
<p>
This is not intended as a comprehensive scholarly history of philosophical
logic.
It is intended to play a role in the development and exposition
of <i>Metphysical Positivism</i> a contemporary positivistic philosophical
system.
</p><p>
A central feature of Metaphysical Positivism is a method of logical analysis,
and the philosophical rationale for its application in philosophy and elsewhere..
The role of this analytic history of philosophical logic is to trace the
history of the key elements of the philosophical and technical basis for this
method, and to do so in a manner consistent with the proposed analytic method,
provided an extended exemplar of the method.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Method of Formal Logical Analysis" doc="fm013" dir="../../methods/fm" suf="htm">
<p>
The backbone of this analytic history will be a series of formal models of
various aspects of the history of philosophical logic, semantics and
metaphysics, all undertaken by a single formal method.
</p><p>
It will therefore begin with an exposition of this method, together with some
material about the significance of semantics, and the application of the method
to metaphysics.
</p><p>
Those aspects of the history which underpin this method will be emphasised,
providing a 2500 year history of the developments which culminated in the adopted method.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism" doc="x010" dir="..">
<p>
This work is being undertaken in tandem with a much smaller informal volume
promulgating a new generation of positivistic phlosophy and entitled
"metaphysical positivism", a key feature of which is the reconciliation of some
of the more benign features of positivist thought with a positive attitude
towards metaphysics.
</p><p>
This explains the particular place in the proposed history of metaphysics, and
the importance attached to the central notion of "logical truth" and its
various correlates such as logical necessity, and the interest in semantics and
analyiticity.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Part I - To The Tractatus" doc="xpl003" tag="PartI"/>

<section title="Part II - The Twentieth Century" doc="xpl004" tag="PartII"/>

<section title="Part III - Theory Listings">
<abstract>
A condensation of the formal backbone to the analytical history, presenting the
naked analytic truths obtained by formal deduction.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Ultimately">
<p>
This will be, in the final work, a separate volume comprising complete listings
of all the formal theories developed in the first two parts, and of any
previoualy developed theories upon which the work depends.
These will be fully indexed to facilitate reference.
</p><p>
It will provide a listing of all the definitively proven results, which will
constitute exclusively analytic propositions for which formal demonstrations
will have been constructed and computer checked.
Each theory listing will include the definitions which establish the
logical context for the derivations.
</p><p>
This part will also provide complete definitions of the logic in which the work
has been done, either explicitly or by reference.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="En Passant">
<p>
Publication, all being well, will be in stages, even though all parts of the
work will be progressed in concert.
</p><p>
The first edition of the first part will include the listing of the theories
belonging to that part, as will the first edition of the second volume.
Once both volumes have been published the theory listings will then be combined
into a third volume and will be removed from the first two parts.
</p><p>
Publication will be as "Print on Demand" through
Amazon's <xlink href="http://createspace.com">CreateSpace</xlink> subsidiary.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
