<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xpl001.xml,v 1.6 2010/03/02 13:35:31 rbj Exp $"
       title="Analyses of Analysis"
       created="2009/7/3"
       description="Explorations in the analysis, partly formal, of varieties of analysis"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy analytic semantics meaning necessity logic metaphysics"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
An analytic examination of varieties of analysis (mostly but not necessarily philosophical) and their philosophical, technical and technological underpinnings, historical and contemporary, formal and informal. 
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Background"/>
<secref title="Part II"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Part I"/>
<secref title="Part III"/>
<secref title="Current Drafts in PDF">
<center>
<xlink href="../../pp/doc/b001.pdf">Part I</xlink>,
<xlink href="../../pp/doc/b003.pdf">Part II</xlink>,
<xlink href="../../pp/doc/b002.pdf">Part III</xlink>.
</center>
</secref>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Background">
<abstract>
A few words on the purposes and character of the work.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
This project began with some work on formal modelling of Aristotle's logic and metaphysics.
I thought it worked out OK and invented a formal book project consisting of lots of such models.
This was way over the top of what I could expect myself to do.
My conception of the work transformed quite rapidly over a period of about six months, but has now transformed itself out of being a book project at all (since I no longer can imagine doing enough formal exegesis to make into a book.
</p><p>
I have also decided that all my formal modelling work (which is in need of rationalisation) should be migrated to open source projects hosted on a publicly accessible repository, and that there will be one project for formal philosophical exegesis.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
I am leaving the material covering the book project, partly as a reminder of ideas for subjects for formal exegesis, partly just in case I should ever decide to revive the book project (though I don't think this likely).
</p><p>
What I expect now is that at some point I will set up a project on sourceforge or google code and put the aristotle up there.
This won't happen until after I have made some headway with the formal side of X-Logic, because there will be some general infrastructure done in that project which will be needed.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Prelude on Changes in Progress">
This work in (intermittent) progress began as a history, which is a silly thing for me to attempt.
I dropped history from the title, even though there will probably still be significant historical content, in search of a title fitting better my as yet sketchy sense of the purpose of the work.
It is intended to incorporate some kind of an account of the general notions of comparative and nomologico-deductive analysis which form the centerpiece of the analytic philosophy which I call "Metaphysical Positivism".
It is intended to fit together with two other works on Positive Philosophy, the whole still evolving in its overall conception.
Expect the available content to be sketchy and inconsistent!
</subsec>
<subsec title="Purpose and Character">
<p>
This document is intended to play a role in the development and exposition of <i>Metphysical Positivism</i> a contemporary positivistic philosophical system, and a part of a broader conception of philosophy which I call <i>Positive Philosophy</i>.
</p><p>
Central features of Metaphysical Positivism are a liberal attitude toward method and a preoccupation with analytic method and its infrastructure.
In this context "infrastructure" should be understood broadly, to include comparative ideology and methodology, philosophical underpinnings, logical and mathematical foundations, and supporting software.
The enterprise is "meta-circular" the underpinnings of analysis encompass a substantial part of its philosophical applications.
</p><p>
The historical aspects of the work are to trace the history of key elements of the philosophical and technical basis for analytic
methods, and to do so by comparative analysis, providing an extended exemplar of the methods.
</p><p>
There will also be forward looking elements, in which ideas for infrastructure are presented and analysed.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Intuitive, Nomologico-Deductive, and Comparative Analysis" doc="fm013" dir="../../methods/fm" suf="htm">
<p>
The backbone of this analytic history will be a series of informal and formal models of
various aspects of the history of philosophical analysis, semantics and
metaphysics.
The analytic methods employed are intended to be diverse, allowing the analysis of any problem domain to progress from intuitive to formal methods as the work progresses. 
</p><p>
Two general features of the analytic methods employed are emphasised.
The first is that conclusions are generally comparative rather than definitive, and there is particular interest in the explorations of different comparative measures.
Second there is a particular interest in a class of methods which we call "nomologico-deductive methods", which are those methods which involve rigorous application of deduction (allowing for various degrees of rigour).
There is a complementary interest in what we might call pre-deductive methods, in understanding the merits of analyses achieved by these means, and in how these can be "progressed" to nomologico-deductive analyses. 
</p><p>
A particular formal nomologico-deductive method as supported by the ProofPower proof development software will be used for formal material.
</p><p>
Those aspects of the history of philosophy and logic which underpin the both general methods employed and the more specific formal techniques will be emphasised, providing a partial 2500 year history of the developments which culminated in these methods.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Positive Philosophy" doc="x010" dir="..">
<p>
This work is being undertaken in tandem with a much smaller informal volume
promulgating a new generation of positivistic phlosophy and entitled
"metaphysical positivism", a key feature of which is the reconciliation of some
of the more benign features of positivist thought with a positive attitude
towards metaphysics.
</p><p>
This explains the particular place in the proposed history of metaphysics, and
the importance attached to the central notion of "logical truth" and its
various correlates such as logical necessity, and the interest in semantics and
analyiticity.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Part I" doc="xpl003" tag="PartI"/>

<section title="Part II" doc="xpl004" tag="PartII"/>

<section title="Part III">
<abstract>
A condensation of the formal backbone to the formal analyses, presenting the naked analytic truths obtained by deduction in the context of the formal models.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Ultimately">
<p>
This will be, in the final work, a separate volume comprising complete listings
of all the formal theories developed in the first two parts, and of any
previoualy developed theories upon which the work depends.
These will be fully indexed to facilitate reference.
</p><p>
It will provide a listing of all the definitively proven results, which will
constitute exclusively analytic propositions for which formal demonstrations
will have been constructed and computer checked.
Each theory listing will include the definitions which establish the
logical context for the derivations.
</p><p>
This part will also provide complete definitions of the logic in which the work
has been done, either explicitly or by reference.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="En Passant">
<p>
Publication, all being well, will be in stages, even though all parts of the
work will be progressed in concert.
</p><p>
The first edition of the first part will include the listing of the theories
belonging to that part, as will the first edition of the second volume.
Once both volumes have been published the theory listings will then be combined
into a third volume and will be removed from the first two parts.
</p><p>
Publication will be as "Print on Demand" through
Amazon's <xlink href="http://createspace.com">CreateSpace</xlink> subsidiary.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Current Drafts in PDF" tag="pdf">
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Part I" doc="b001" dir="../../pp/doc" suf="pdf" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Part II" doc="b003" dir="../../pp/doc" suf="pdf" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Part III" doc="b002" dir="../../pp/doc" suf="pdf" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
