<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: eng010.xml,v 1.1 2006/03/25 22:50:36 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Engineering as Philosophy"
       created="2006-3-9"
       description="Some Engineering Design Problems with high Philosophical Content"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy engineering"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
The problem of engineering machines which reason is philosophically provocative.
The justification of an architecture for such a machine is a kind of constructive philosophy.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Logic for Design">
The design of control logic by formal methods provides a stimulating test case for radical advances in the application of formal logic.
The articulation of principles, rationale, foundations and methods for such an approach to engineering design has substantial philosophical content.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Cognitive Engineering">
The construction of machines which realise signficant elements of the kinds of cognitive capacity hitherto exclusive to the human brain is an engineering problem with a substantial philosophical content.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Social Engineering">
Political philosophy has historically been a significant influence on the evolution of political systems in the real world.
Even the most neutral philosophical analysis of may cast light which changes the world.
Conversely, thinking about how to realise significant improvements to the world we live in leads us into a kind of philosophy.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
Best known as a philosopher and mathematician, Leibniz was also an engineer.
He built calculating machines, and conceived of a universal calculating machine capable of solving any problem which could be formulated in a sufficiently precise way.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
<i>Artificial Intelligence</i> as we now call it, is an engineering problem whose putative solutions raise philosophical problems.
The mere possibility of non-human intelligence, once accepted, may
provoke changes in philosophical attitude to problems which have no
obvious connec
tion with the engineering of artefacts.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Leibniz and the Automation of Reason"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The Automation of Reason"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Leibniz and the Automation of Reason" tag="ARH" dir="../philos/history" doc="xh003" />

<section title="The Automation of Reason" tag="ARH" dir=".." doc="x002" />

</xldoc>