<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: gfq001.xml,v 1.2 2011/11/04 16:38:43 rbj Exp $"
       title="Quotations from the writings of Gottlob Frege"
       created="2010-2-15"
       description="Quotations from Frege"
       keywords="philosophy history"
       up="../index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Contents">

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Die Grundlagen der Arithmetic" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Grundgesetze der Arithmetik" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

<section title="Grundgesetze der Arithmetik">
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Scientific Method in Mathematics">
<blockquote>
<p>
The ideal of strictly scientific method in mathematics which I have tried to realise here, and which perhaps might be named after Euclid I should like to describe in the following way:
</p><p>
It cannot be required that we should prove everything, for that is impossible; but we can demand that all propositions used without proof should be expressly mentioned as such, so that we can see distinctly what the whole construction rests upon.
</p><p>
We should accordingly strive to reduce the number of these fundamental laws as much as possible, by proving everything which can be proved.
</p><p>
Furthermore I demand --- and in this I go beyond Euclid --- that all the methods of inference used should be specified in advance.
Otherwise is it impossible to ensure satisfying the first demand.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
From the preface to <i>Grundgesetze der Arithmetik</i> Volume I <bibref name="frege1893" />.
Translation to English from <bibref name="frege1952" />.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Die Grundlagen der Arithmetik" >
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Three Fundamental Principles" >
<blockquote>
In the enquiry which follows I have kept to three fundamental principles:
<ul>
<li>always to separate sharply the psychological from the logical, the subjective from the objective</li>
<li>never to ask for the meaning of a word in isolation, but only in the context of a proposition</li>
<li>never to lose sight of the distinction between concept and object</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>
From the introduction to <i>The Foundations of Arithmetic</i> <bibref name="frege1884"></bibref>.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="2. Analyticity and A Priority" >
<blockquote>
Now these distinctions between a priori and a posteriori, synthetic and analytic, concern, as I see it, not the content of the judgement but the justification for making the judgement...
When a proposition is called a posteriori or analytic in my sense, this is not a statement about the conditions, psychological, physiological, and physical, which have made it possible to form the content of the proposition in our consciousness; nor is it a judgement about how some other man has come, perhaps erroneously, to believe it true; rather, it is a judgement about the ultimate ground on which rests the justification for holding it to be true.  
</blockquote>
<p>
<i>The Foundations of Arithmetic</i> <bibref name="frege1884" />, &sect;3.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="87. The Analyticity of Arithmetic" >
<blockquote>
I hope I may claim in the present work to have made it probable that the laws of arithmetic are analytic judgements and consequently <i>a priori</i>/.
<p/>
Arithmetic thus becomes simply a development of logic, and every proposition of arithmetic a law of logic, albeit a derivative one.
</blockquote>
<p>
<i>The Foundations of Arithmetic</i> <bibref name="frege1884" />, &sect;87.
</p>
</subsec>

</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" >
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


</xldoc>
