<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xh001.xml,v 1.1 2005/04/09 14:00:53 rbj Exp $"
       name="xh001"
       title="A History of Positivist Philosophy"
       created="2005-2-21"
       description="Notes on the history of positivist philosophy."
       keywords="rbjones philosophy positivism pragmatism utilitarianism"
       class="con"
       root="../../../"
       up="index.htm"
       path="rbjpub/philos/history"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<maintitle>A History of Positivist Philosophy</maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Positivist philosophy in its broadest sense is a general tendency in philosophy which embraces aspects of the thought of many philosophers including Humean scepticism, the work of Comte (who coined the term), elements of utilitarianism and pragmatism, and logical positivism.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction" />
<secref title="Positivism and Scepticism" />
<secref title="Medieval Precursors" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="David Hume" />
<secref title="Auguste Comte" />
<subsec title="Positivist Philosophy - From Hume to the Vienna Circle" href="../bibliog/kolakowski1972.htm">
My notes on the book by Leszek Kolakowski.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Positivism is a kind of philosophy for philosophically minded scientists (who can stomach only so much) or for scientifically or practically oriented philosophers (who are primarily interested in genuinely philosophical problems but want philosophy to be as solid and useful as it may be, and may be rather embarrassed by most of what is offered as philosophy).
Here are outlined some common elements of positivist philosophies.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Empiricism">
Its worth noting that positivism is closely related to empiricism, most positivists are also empiricists.
David Hume is for example, considered an arch positivist, though John Locke is not.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Skepticisims">
Though falling short of pyrrhonean extremes positivists are usually of a sceptical tenor and show moderate to strong scepticism in respect of ontology, meaning and truth.
In respect of ontology positivism therefore tends to be nominalistic.
In respect of meaning positivists are likely to condemn large areas of philosophy and also parts of science as meaningless.
In respect of truth, they will demand new standards of rigour in establishing conjectures.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Positive Method">
The sceptical tenor of positivism is usually countered by positive doctrines on how meaning can be made clear, and conclusions can be firmly established.
Positivist philosophy therefore often includes scientific methodology, and this is usually normative rather than descriptive, i.e. it describes how science and philosophy <i>should</i> be conducted rather than how they <i>are</i> conducted.
Positivists are likely also to advocate the application of scientific method in philosophy, though they may differ on what kind of method is appropriate.
Sometimes, as in the case of Hume they advocate that philosophers adopt the methods of empirical science.
Sometimes, as in the case of logical positivism, they advocate that philosophy adopt the methods of the <i>a priori</i> sciences (mathematics and logic).
</subsec>
<subsec title="Kinds of Knowledge">
It is usual for positivists to distinguish between <i>a priori</i>, <i>analytic</i>, <i>necessary</i> propositions and <i>a posteriori</i> (or <i>empirical</i>), <i>synthetic</i>, and <i>contingent</i> propositions, sometimes holding that these three dichotomies are coextensive.
These may also be said to be exhaustive of the realm of true knowledge and to exclude value judgements, ethics, aesthetics.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Foundationalisms">
Positivists are typically also empiricists, and hold that our knowledge of empirical truths comes (or is founded in) through our senses, and that <i>a priori</i> knowledge is derived from some some kernel of primitive logical truths (e.g. <i>follows from the law of contradiction</i>).
These doctrines may be called foundationalism in respect of factual and logical truth respectively.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Conventionalism">
Conventionalist's doctrines asserting that certain kinds of propositions are true in virtue of conventions are often found in positivist philosophy.
The most common is the view that statements which are logically true are true as a result of the linguistic conventions which determine the meaning of sentences in the language.
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Unity of Science">
Normative scientific methodology is naturally accompanied by conviction of the essential unity of science.
This is present, for example, both in Comte conception of Positive Science and in the Unity of Science movement spawned in the twentieth century by logical positivism.
The unity of science may be considered to consist in its being reducible to physics.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Utility and Pragmatics">
The sceptical element of positivist though concerns not merely meaning and truth but also utility.
The attempt to give criteria for meaning may become connected with questions of utility or pragmatics, and hence utilitarian or pragmatic philosophers may be considered to fall within the broad sweep of positivist thought.
However, the positivist distinction between empirical facts and value statements may be lost in utilitarian or pragmatic theories of meaning or truth.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Positivism and Scepticism" tag="PAS" doc="xh002">
<abstract>
This ancient Greek school of extreme sceptical philosophy provides an important element of positivism.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Intro">
The most extreme and systematic scepticism in the philosophy of the ancient Greeks was that of Pyrrho of Ellis and the school he founded.
Pyrrho added moral and logical scepticism to the scepticism with regard to the senses which had preceded him, and is said to have held that there could never be any rational ground for preferring one course of action over any other.
<p />
The most thorough and consistent sceptic reserves judgement on all matters, save perhaps that "appearances appear", and this attitude is echoed in those positivist philosophers who advocate that science should do no more than record the results of experiments.
Because positivists often have this element of sympathy even for extreme scepticism I propose here to discuss such scepticism in ways which are perhaps better informed by positivist than pyrrhonean philosophy.
<p />
In the parlance of sceptics a dogmatist is anyone who has a definite belief.
There is of course a tendency for sceptics to slip into dogmatic scepticism by asserting that nothing can be known (except perhaps the content of our sensory experience), and this tendency is evident in many positivist philosophers.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Lack of Absolute Certainty">
It may be argued that we lack knowledge of the external world because our conclusions about it are derived from the evidence of our senses, which is unreliable, but more important, which, reliable or not, does not <i>logically entail</i> any conclusion about the external world.
It is <i>logically</i> possible that our senses should yield information which is entirely disconnected with the condition of the world, that they do not, however reliably, is contingent.
In this argument is implicit the presumption that to have knowledge of a proposition we must be posessed of evidence which logically entails the proposition under consideration.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Skepticism with regard to the senses">
This is an important kind of scepticism for positivism, and is prominent in the philsophy of David Hume.
It can be described in foundationalist terms by observing that our knowledge of the external world is derived entirely from the data provided to us by our sense, but even the most simple judgements of perception go beyond what is given to us by our senses.
Some kind of process
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Medieval Precursors">
<abstract>
The views of some late medieval philosophers may be said to have elements of positivism in them, and contributed towards the separation of scientific knowledge from metaphysics and a separation of secular from ecclesiastical matters.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Roger Bacon">
<p>
Roger Bacon is relevant both for his sweeping scepticism about the received wisdom of his day and for his advocacy of experimental method.
</p><p>
He identified four causes of ignorance:
</p>
<ol>
<li>the example of frail and unsuited authority</li>
<li>the influence of custom</li>
<li>the opinion of the unlearned crowd (which appears to have included all his contemporaries)</li>
<li>the concealment of one's ignorance in a display of apparent wisdom</li>
</ol>
<p>
He believed that the only reliable ways of attaining knowledge were through experiment and geometric deduction, and had almost utopian conceptions of what might be achieved if these methods were universally adopted.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="William of Occam">
<p>
Immortalised by the nominalistic principle known as "Occam's razor":
</p>
<i>we are to include in our conception of the world only so much as the irrefutable testimony of experience obliges us to</i>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Paris Nominalists">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="David Hume">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Auguste Comte">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



