<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xh002.xml,v 1.1 2005/04/09 14:00:53 rbj Exp $"
       name="xh002"
       title="Positivism and Scepticism"
       created="2005-2-25"
       description="Some observations about the relationship between Positivism and Scepticism"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy positivism scepticism"
       class="con"
       root="../../../"
       up="xl001.htm"
       path="rbjpub/philos/history"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<maintitle>Positivism and Skepticism</maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Positivism may be thought of as a kind of constructive skepticism.
It is interesting to explore this aspect of the roots of positivism.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Pyrrho of Ellis" />
<secref title="Separation of Science from Religion" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Empiricism as a Skeptical Response to Rationalism" />
<secref title="Positivism as Radical Constructive Empiricism" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Pyrrho of Ellis">
<abstract>
This ancient Greek school of extreme sceptical philosophy provides an important element of positivism.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Intro">
The most extreme and systematic scepticism in the philosophy of the ancient Greeks was that of Pyrrho of Ellis and the school he founded.
Pyrrho added moral and logical scepticism to the scepticism with regard to the senses which had preceded him, and is said to have held that there could never be any rational ground for preferring one course of action over any other.
<p />
The most thorough and consistent sceptic reserves judgement on all matters, save perhaps that "appearances appear", and this attitude is echoed in those positivist philosophers who advocate that science should do no more than record the results of experiments.
Because positivists often have this element of sympathy even for extreme scepticism I propose here to discuss such scepticism in ways which are perhaps better informed by positivist than pyrrhonean philosophy.
<p />
In the parlance of sceptics a dogmatist is anyone who has a definite belief.
There is of course a tendency for sceptics to slip into dogmatic scepticism by asserting that nothing can be known (except perhaps the content of our sensory experience), and this tendency is evident in many positivist philosophers.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Lack of Absolute Certainty">
It may be argued that we lack knowledge of the external world because our conclusions about it are derived from the evidence of our senses, which is unreliable, but more important, which, reliable or not, does not <i>logically entail</i> any conclusion about the external world.
It is <i>logically</i> possible that our senses should yield information which is entirely disconnected with the condition of the world, that they do not, however reliably, is contingent.
In this argument is implicit the presumption that to have knowledge of a proposition we must be posessed of evidence which logically entails the proposition under consideration.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Skepticism with regard to the senses">
This is an important kind of scepticism for positivism, and is prominent in the philsophy of David Hume.
It can be described in foundationalist terms by observing that our knowledge of the external world is derived entirely from the data provided to us by our sense, but even the most simple judgements of perception go beyond what is given to us by our senses.
Some kind of process
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Separation of Science from Religion">
<abstract>
In the middle ages the Church monopolised learning.
The rediscovered philosophy of ancient Greece was put into the service of God, and religious doctrine was supported by both rational and natural theology.
In the thirteen century more independent thinkers were beginning to sew the seeds of separation between regious and secular matters using ideas which took skeptical insights in the direction of positivism.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Roger Bacon">
<p>
Roger Bacon is relevant both for his sweeping scepticism about the received wisdom of his day and for his advocacy of experimental method.
</p><p>
He identified four causes of ignorance:
</p>
<ol>
<li>the example of frail and unsuited authority</li>
<li>the influence of custom</li>
<li>the opinion of the unlearned crowd (which appears to have included all his contemporaries)</li>
<li>the concealment of one's ignorance in a display of apparent wisdom</li>
</ol>
<p>
He believed that the only reliable ways of attaining knowledge were through experiment and geometric deduction, and had almost utopian conceptions of what might be achieved if these methods were universally adopted.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="William of Occam">
<p>
Immortalised by the nominalistic principle known as "Occam's razor":
</p>
<i>we are to include in our conception of the world only so much as the irrefutable testimony of experience obliges us to</i>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Paris Nominalists">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="David Hume">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



