<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xh009.xml,v 1.1 2006/07/10 19:20:24 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Isaiah Berlin on ..."
       created="2006-07-09"
       description="Notes on Berlin's view of various thinkers."
       keywords="philosophy logic history"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Notes on what Isaiah Berlin says about various figures in the history of ideas.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Fichte" />
<secref title="Rousseau" />
<subsec title="" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="" />
<subsec title="" />
<subsec title="" />
<subsec title="" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Fichte">
<abstract>

</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Introduction">
<p>
Berlin tells us that Fichte's thought is transformed so radically through his life that we should think of there being three quite different Fichte's.
They are the Fichte supporting unfetterd individualistic artistic expression, the Fichte advocating Platonic guardians, and the Fichte of the master race.  
</p>
<p>
These are all three aspects at different levels of the idea of Romantic self-assertion.
The self assertion of the individual artists, the guardians of society or of the master race, is not for all but for the select few who have the required abilities (creativity...) and others either have the wisdom to see that they are right and to comply, or lcaking that wisdom, should be compelled to comply for their own good.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Fichte and Kant">
Fichte takes "Kant's central notion" that "that the world as understood by men was as it was because of the forms imposed upon it by the human mind", and turns this into an act of will.
The act of will is necessary to halt the regress of justification, in which the justification of some proposition requires in turn to be justified.
The regress is terminated by act of will, and the will in this way shapes the world perceived.
"The world is that which we will it to be".
</subsec>
<subsec title="Fichte's Notion of Self">
<blockquote>
"The self becomes aware of itself in action, and in the beginning is action, not contemplation." 
</blockquote>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Making Ends">
<p>
This is the feature of Fichte's thought which Berlin considers his most important innovation, and his most direct challenge to the enlightenment, or indeed the whole previous thrust of Western philosophy. 
</p>
<blockquote>
"Fichte is the first thinker who explicitly says that ends are not discoverable but invented; they are not found, they are made.
</blockquote>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Rousseau" doc="xh008" />

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



