<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: privacy.xml,v 1.2 2010/01/25 13:11:02 rbj Exp $"
       title="RBJones.com Privacy Policy"
       created="2010/1/8"
       description="A privacy policy (as required by Google Adsense)"
       keywords="rbjones.com privacy google cookie javascript"
       class="con"
       up="../index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="" tag="tag">
<abstract>
The privacy policy for RBJones.com.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
I have not spent much time on this, and I am not hot on privacy.
</p><p>
The privacy policy of this site is simply to obtain no private information.
No use is made by the site of cookies, or any other means of gathering information about customers.
</p><p>
However, the site does supply search buttons to enable users of the site to conduct searches using Google.
The use of these buttons involves the execution of javascript, so they will not function as intended unless your browser permits execution of javascript.
The results of such searches as delivered by Google may contain advertisments and may make use of cookies.
Third parties may be placing and reading cookies on your browser, or using web beacons to collect information, in the course of ads being served in the results of Google searches on this site.
Full details of the privacy implications of using these search facilities should be sought at google.
</p><p>
User options for cookie management are documented at Google.com.
</p><p>
The user should be aware, that some people more deeply concerned in and competent about privacy have expressed serious reservations about Googles attitude towards privacy, and the user may wish to take this into account in deciding whether to make use of Google search facilities.
You can use Google (or some other search engine) to discover more about these issues!
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
