<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x001.xml,v 1.37 2010/03/02 13:35:31 rbj Exp $"
       title="RBJones.com"
       created="2010-01-02"
       description="Home page for the rbjones.com web site."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics utopia"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="left"><image name="rbjdcoml.gif" align="top" alt="rbjones.com"/></maintitle>
<indextitle>RBJones.com</indextitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
HOT Philosophy.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
This web site is my working space.
Here, for about the last fifteen years, I have been seeking to write philosophy.
My efforts have so far been spectacularly unsuccessful.
I have failed so far to capture in these writings anything at all close to my own evolving point of view.
</p><p>
This continuing failure spawns a succession of conceptions of the nature of my enterprise, which I might now describe as a series of ideas on how I might unify the process of philosophical thinking with that of creative writing.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The HOT Philosophy Project"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="A Conversation between Carnap and Grice" >
<center>(as it might have been)</center>
<p>
Even hotter because Speranza is in there raising the temperature.
</p><p>
A joint enterprise of Jones and Speranza.
</p>
</secref>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="Other Projects">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Some History">
<p>
In 2009 I set out to write a monograph on "The Fundamental Triple-Dichotomy"(!), which project evolved (mostly in its conception rather than by way of execution) throughout the year and spawned a companion.
By the end of the year the idea was for a book "Metaphysical Positivism" with a companion volume "An Analytic History of Philosophical Analysis".
</p><p>
At the very beginning of 2010 I scrapped them both and started afresh with "The HOT Philosophy Project".
A week later I resuscitated the two projects, modified to complement HOT philosophy, and now thought of in a rather more leisurely time-frame.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Principle Changes">
<p>
I mention here the essence of the changes I have in mind.
Most of the material on the web site has not caught up with these ideas.
</p><p>
The volume on Metaphysical Positivism I now think of as a focused and tight presentation of a conception of analytic philosophy, which centres around an exposition of analytic method in which the notion of a nomologico-deductive method is central.
Where as previously I had intended this volume to contain quite a bit of historical background explaining how Metaphysical Positivism fits in to the history of philosophy, all this historical material is now relegated to the companion volume.
</p><p>
The analytic history of philosophical analysis will trace the origins of our methods and their philosophical underpinnings and will exemplify their use.
This is not the kind of task that I would ever expect to complete, so I expect it to look like an incomplete book more or less indefinitely.
With the broadening of my conception of analysis this project which was initially intended to be mostly formal modelling I now expect to be more varied in content.
Particularly because I have in mind that most of the historical material which I had previously intended to put in the book of Metaphysical Positivism will now go here.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Positive Philosophy" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Analyses of Analysis" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Searches" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Projects" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

<section title="A Conversation between Carnap and Grice" tag="cgc" doc="xh012" dir="philos/history"/>

<section title="The HOT Philosophy Project" tag="HOTPP" doc="x032" dir="philos"/>

<section title="Positive Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x018" tag="pp" />

<section title="Analyses of Analysis" dir="philos/logic" doc="xpl001" tag="hpl" />

<section title="Searches" doc="search" />

</xldoc>
