<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x001.xml,v 1.2 2004/03/11 10:44:05 rbj Exp $"
       name="x001"
       title="RBJones.com"
       created="2002-10-15"
       description="Introductory/overview page for the rbjones.com web site."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy utopia"
       class="con"
       root="../"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<maintitle><img name="rbjdcoml.gif" /></maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
The home of <i>analytic positivism</i>.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction to Analytic Positivism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Factasia"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction to Analytic Positivism">
<abstract>
Sets and sugar suffice.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Slogan">
<p>
The slogan of analytic positivism is <i>sets and sugar suffice</i>.
"For what, and how?" you may ask.
But before that, "what on earth does he mean?".
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Meaning?">
What this slogan means it that the ontology of sets, the language of set theory, and the formal deductive system it comes with, made more readable by what computer scientists call <i>syntactic sugar</i>, i.e. just nicer ways of writing down things which could have been said in the primitive language of set theory, suffice for rigorous science and philosophy.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="For What?">
<p>
Well, for the kind of idealised model of how science might be which is typical of a positivistic philosophical system.
Alternatively, for the foundations of abstract semantics, and hence for defining analyticity, the notion of sound deduction, for underpinning the a priori sciences, via the nomologico-deductive model for the deductive aspects of empirical sciences and for the deductively sound aspects of analytic philosophy, including abstract ontology and such metaphysics as a positivist may be prepared to comprehend.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="How?">
<p>
How, is a longer story, but there is a short version.
</p>
<p>
The short version is: "by abstract modelling".
The underlying insight is that, whatever your subject matter, its structure can be replicated in an abstract domain.
You can do this either by chosing an appropriate language for talking about your subject and giving that language an abstract semantics in set theory, or alternatively just using set theory itself (sugared probably) to construct an abstract model.
Set theory then provides a foundation for reasoning rigorously about your subject.
</p>

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Factasia" href="rbj040.htm">
<abstract>
My previous enterprise was "Factasia", which still forms the bulk of this website.
</abstract>
</section>

</xldoc>
