<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x001.xml,v 1.50 2015/07/06 $"
       title="The Philosophy of Roger Bishop Jones"
       created="2010-01-02"
       description="Home page for the rbjones.com web site."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics utopia"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle>The Philosophy of Roger Bishop Jones</maintitle>
<indextitle>RBJ's Philosophy</indextitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Some wishful thinking.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
I am <i>trying to write books</i>.
This seems to involve thinking up a project, thinking about the project, doing some research, doing some writing (not usually a lot), running into sand, doing a lot more thinking, and then eventually coming up with a better project idea, often connected with one I was working on a few years back.
Perhaps this process will eventually converge and one or more books will emerge.
Whether or not, I do now seem to enjoy this process (for a long time I found it frustrating), so I'm not going to stop!
My projects are primarily philosophical, but sometimes involve the investigation of certain technical problems, usually motivated by the philosophy.
</p>
<p>
The best clues to the kind of project which interests me (at least so far as <i>analytic</i> philosophy is concerned) are the examples of Leibniz and Carnap.
Leibniz for his conception of <xlink href="philos/history/xh003.html">a Universal Characteristic with a Calculus Ratiocinator</xlink>, and Carnap for his dedication to pressing forward Russell's conception of a "Scientific Philosophy", based on modern logical methods, into new territory (the formalisation of philosophy and science).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
In keeping with the latter example, I usually think of myself as a kind of positivist, in particular as a <i><xlink href="philos/x010.html">metaphysical positivist</xlink></i>, when I feel the need of a label.
My interests do go beyond purely <i>analytic</i> philosophy.
I call the broader conception <i><xlink href="x003.html">positive philosophy</xlink></i> (alternatively <xlink href="philos/x018.html">here</xlink> ), but it doesn't get a fair share of my brain.
</p>
<p>
On the technical side, I accept a fairly old fashioned conception of Cantorian theory of (well-founded) sets as a near-universal ultimate foundation for abstract semantics, but believe that a non-well-founded ontology might be better as a near-universal logical context in which to formally develop mathematics and its applications (though I don't know of any detailed formulation of such a system which I would advocate).
Note here the talk of set theory as being <i>logical</i>, in keeping with a rather old fashioned (and unqualified) Carnapian logicism.
Obtaining the right kind of non-well-founded foundation system (<xlink href="pp/doc/t041.pdf">a strong illative lambda-calculus</xlink>) and doing the metatheory for it in a well-founded set theory had been an important aim of my technical work, but has not progressed for eons.
</p>
<p>
I also do some formal exegesis of the work of other philosophers, perhaps that should count as "technical" (e.g.: <xlink href="pp/doc/t028.pdf">Aristotle</xlink>), and other things which might count as exemplars of the kinds of formal method I advocate.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="RBJones.com paperbacks" dir="www/books" doc="xb005">
New editions of Aristotle's Organon and Metaphysics in PDF and paperback.
</subsec>
<subsec title="THE SHED at RBJones.com" doc="index" dir="pp/doc">
The technical side of my research in progress can be found in <xlink href="pp/doc/index.html">THE SHED</xlink>.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>



</xldoc>
