<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x001.xml,v 1.30 2009/10/12 11:22:45 rbj Exp $"
       title="RBJones.com"
       created="2006-01-31"
       description="Home page for the rbjones.com web site."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics utopia"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="left"><image name="rbjdcoml.gif" align="top" alt="rbjones.com"/></maintitle>
<indextitle>RBJones.com</indextitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Philosophy on the move.
</abstract>

<secbody title="Some Changes in Progress">
<sbcol></sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
I have recently undertaken some significant changes to the main projects in progress
on this site, which will take some time to effect.
The main thrust of these is:
<ul>
<li> firstly to make "metaphysical positivism" a more
purely analytic philosophical position, which primarily involves the excision
  of prescriptive elements (which are typical of positivistic philosophy).
</li><li>
secondly, the broadening of the accompanying material on the historical origins
from a history of philosophical logic embracing much metaphysics, to a history
of philosophical analysis.
This change will permit a fuller account of the origins of the analytic method at the center
of metaphysical positivism, and make the whole thing into a more interesting story.
</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol></sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="purpose">
<p>
My aim in this site is to give the reader a vivid sense of the dynamics
of my current philosophical projects.
</p><p>
I have two book-writing projects taking off right now, and every step along
these roads of discovery will be presented here on RBJones.com long before the
books ever appear in print.
</p><p>
The site also contains a variety of previous cogitations.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="the books">
<p>
The first of these projects is to be entitled "Metaphysical Positivism" and
will be a new formulation of positivist philosophy.
The book is intended to be a prose volume of similar scale and character to
A.J.Ayer's "Language Truth and Logic".
However, the book is primarily a presentation of an analytic method.
It offers, rather than prescribes, a method, and provides analysis of that method,
rather than polemic in its favour or against other methods. 
</p><p>
The second, which provides both background for the former and an
extended exemplar of the method of analysis informally described in that book, will
be an analytic history of philosophical analysis, tracing the origins of our
method and exemplifying its use.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Metaphysical Positivism" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="An Analytic History of Philosophical Analysis" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<center>If you want to see the rest of the site,<br/>some places to start are:</center>
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Quick Index" href="index.htm" />
<subsec title="RBJones.com Top 100" href="rbj036.htm" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>


<section title="Metaphysical Positivism" dir="philos" doc="x010" tag="mp" />

<section title="An Analytic History of Philosophical Analysis" dir="philos/logic" doc="xpl001" tag="hpl" />

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
