<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x001.xml,v 1.43 2011/01/05 11:02:31 rbj Exp $"
       title="The Philosophy of Roger Bishop Jones"
       created="2010-01-02"
       description="Home page for the rbjones.com web site."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics utopia"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle>The Philosophy of Roger Bishop Jones</maintitle>
<indextitle>RBJ's Philosophy</indextitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<secbody>
<sbcol/>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="THE SHED at RBJones.com" doc="index" dir="pp/doc">
If you want to see what I actually am doing, the best place to look is in <xlink href="pp/doc/index.html">THE SHED</xlink>.
This isn't everything that I am working on, but it is where the greater part of the real action is going on.
This is work in progress, expect it to be indiscipherable and misguided.
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Rest">
<p>
I persist in thinking in terms of books, on a large scale.
So far this has meant setting out on substantial projects which for one reason or another (or for no reason at all) don't happen.
Meanwhile I have smaller projects, some of which do progress.
The formal ones may be found in ``<xlink href="pp/doc/index.html">the shed</xlink>'', but some of my interests demand prose, my attempts at which are more diversely located.
</p><p>
I now think in terms of sewing all these small projects, which do all form a part of a whole in my head, into `books'.
The formal parts I now conceive of as combining to form a three volume tome, <i>Analyses of Analysis</i> of which the first volume is what I call 'exegetical analysis', and the second 'synthetic analysis', which I think of as a contemporary approach to doing philosophy in broadly the manner in which Carnap would have wished to see it done (i.e. formally).
A third volume is devoted to theory listing, concise presentations of the formal theories developed in the preceding two volumes.
</p><p>
My conception of the informal material is less well developed, though of course it is important not least on the grounds that someone might possibly read it!
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol/>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
