<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x001.xml,v 1.49 2012/09/25 15:04:03 rbj Exp $"
       title="The Philosophy of Roger Bishop Jones"
       created="2010-01-02"
       description="Home page for the rbjones.com web site."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics utopia"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle>The Philosophy of Roger Bishop Jones</maintitle>
<indextitle>RBJ's Philosophy</indextitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
There has been a recent shift in my principal philosophical focus.
Before and after sketches are presented here.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Shifting Sands">
<p>
My intellectual preoccupations are primarily philosophical, but also include the investigation of certain technical problems, usually motivated by the philosophy.
My own manner of philosophising involves a great deal of thinking, not a lot of reading, nothing much like scholarship and lamentably little writing.
I don't aim to write papers for philosophical journals.
I would like to write a book, that is what my philosophical thinking is oriented towards, but it seems uncertain that I ever will.
Generally I am working towards one or more books, but never actually get very close.
</p><p>
Earlier this year I was working on a book entitled "Positive Philosophy and The Automation of Reason", which was intended to progress certain of the ideas of Leibniz and Carnap.
In the course of working out some of the historical aspects of that narrative I have been drawn into attempting something of a more theoretical nature loosely in the spirit of his "First Philosophy".
</p><p>
At first I thought of this as a temporary diversion, but it is beginning to feel like a more substantial shift of focus in my philosophical thinking.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="New Focus"/>
<secref title="Previous Focus"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="New Focus" tag="nf">
<abstract>
Organon and Metaphysic.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap and Aristotle">
<p>
For a long time I have been an advocate of a kind of analytic philosophy not far removed from that of Rudolf Carnap.
In that conception the role of the philosopher seems to be primarily methodological, and Carnap's particular interest was in furthering the adoption of formal logical methods in the empirical sciences.
Carnap took Russell to have done this for mathematics, and to have advocated logically rigorous methods in philosophy.
Carnap advocated such methods not only in mathematics and philosophy, but also for empirical sciences.
</p><p>
Of course Carnap is infamous for his attacks on metaphysics, but when on looks into the conception of Metaphysics which Carnap opposed, one finds it narrowly circumscribed.
It was characterised principally as <i>the synthetic a priori</i> which in Carnap usage of these terms was necessarily non-existent, or <i>the meaningless</i> (and his later conceptions of meaning are not closely connected with empirical verifiability).
Its not clear that there might not have been investigations which some people would have regarded as metaphysical and which were nevertheless not covered by Carnap's reservations, not proscribed by him because not seen as metaphysics.
</p><p>
For example, Strawson's descriptive metaphysics might be regarded as an empirical analysis of some of the concepts fundamental to ordinary language, and hence not to constitute metaphysics in Carnap's termimology or to fall under his proscription.
</p><p>
Could Carnap conceivably ever have found merit in Aristotle's "Metaphysics"?
</p><p>
If we consider the procedure advocated by Carnap, for example in his "Empiricism Semantics and Ontology", when establishing some new language for science, and adopt this procedure in a rational reconstruction of Aristotle's metaphysical language, then one could plausibly construct a formal model of Aristolelian metaphysics which complied with Carnap's recommendations.
The question would then arise as to the merits of this language; whether and for what purposes it might actually be adopted.
This question, according to Carnap could be settled on a purely pragmatic basis.
Adopt if found to be useful.
</p><p>
Aristotle himself did not think of metaphysics as constituting a <i>useful</i> system of thought.
In fact his criteria for "first philosophy" (which is what he called the metaphysics) excluded anything done for practical reasons.
Aristotle sought truth, regardless of utility. 
</p><p>
For a long time I have held a position in many ways similar to that of Carnap, while recognising that many possible kinds of "metaphysics" might be consistent with that position.
I went back to Aristotle in the course of tracing the history of concepts which I took to be key to a contemporary articulation of analytic method.
Aristotle's contribution to analytic method is to be found not only in his Organon, but also in his Metaphysics, where he addresses first principles, including those which underpin analytic method.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title=""/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title=""/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Previous Focus" tag="pf">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody title="">
<sbcol/>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
The best clues to the kind of project which interests me (at least so far as <i>analytic</i> philosophy is concerned) are the examples of Leibniz and Carnap.
Leibniz for his conception of <xlink href="philos/history/xh003.html">a Universal Characteristic with a Calculus Ratiocinator</xlink>, and Carnap for his dedication to pressing forward Russell's conception of a "Scientific Philosophy", based on modern logical methods, into new territory (the formalisation of philosophy and science).
In keeping with the latter example, I usually think of myself as a kind of positivist, in particular as a <i><xlink href="philos/x010.html">metaphysical positivist</xlink></i>.
My interests do go beyond purely <i>analytic</i> philosophy.
I call the broader conception <i><xlink href="x003.html">positive philosophy</xlink></i> (alternatively <xlink href="philos/x018.html">here</xlink> ), but it doesn't get a fair share of my brain.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
On the technical side, I accept a fairly old fashioned conception of Cantorian theory of (well-founded) sets as a near-universal ultimate foundation for abstract semantics, but believe that a non-well founded ontology might be better as a near-universal logical context in which to formally develop mathematics and its applications.
Note here the talk of set theory as being logical, in keeping with a rather old fashioned (and unqualified) Carnapian logicism.
Obtaining the right kind of non-well-founded foundation system (<xlink href="pp/doc/t041.pdf">a strong illative lambda-calculus</xlink>) and doing the metatheory for it in a well-founded set theory is the principal present aim of my technical work.
</p>
<p>
I also do some formal exegesis of the work of other philosophers, perhaps that should count as "technical" (e.g.: <xlink href="pp/doc/t028.pdf">Aristotle</xlink>).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol/>
</secbody>
</section>

<section>
<secbody>
<sbcol/>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="THE SHED at RBJones.com" doc="index" dir="pp/doc">
The technical side of my research in progress can be found in <xlink href="pp/doc/index.html">THE SHED</xlink>.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol/>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
