<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x001.xml,v 1.45 2011/03/26 17:30:11 rbj Exp $"
       title="The Philosophy of Roger Bishop Jones"
       created="2010-01-02"
       description="Home page for the rbjones.com web site."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics utopia"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle>The Philosophy of Roger Bishop Jones</maintitle>
<indextitle>RBJ's Philosophy</indextitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<secbody title="What I Mostly Think About">
<sbcol/>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
I suppose I should say that my own conception or style of philosophy involves a great deal of thinking, not a lot of reading, and nothing much like scholarship.
</p><p>
I am a kind of philosophical hacker, I like to try and solve certain kinds of problems, I like to try to progress certain kinds of grand scheme, and I study what others have done only if I think that it might help in my own projects.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
The best clues to the kind of project which interests me (at least so far as <i>analytic</i> philosophy is concerned) are the examples of Leibniz and Carnap.
Leibniz for his conception of <xlink href="philos/history/xh003.html">a Universal Characteristic with a Calculus Ratiocinator</xlink>, and Carnap for his dedication to pressing forward Russell's conception of a "Scientific Philosophy", based on modern logical methods, into new territory (the formalisation of philosophy and science).
In keeping with the latter example, I usually think of myself as a kind of positivist, in particular as a <i><xlink href="philos/x010.html">metaphysical positivist</xlink></i>.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol/>
</secbody>
<secbody title="More About the Action">
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
So what do I actually do to progress these ideas?
</p><p>
One thing I try to do is foundational innovation.
I do quite a bit of formal work, and am constantly aware of the awkwardnesses imposed on this process by the fact that the logical systems I use are based on <i>well-founded</i> ontologies.
</p><p>
Ever since I became aware of what a logical foundation for mathematics is, I have been unhappy with the draconian constraint imposed either by a classical type theory, or by the dominant set theoretic ontology of well-founded sets.
This probably started with the instinctive reaction of a computer hacker against the idea behind Russell's Theory of Types, that circularity is pathological in itself (rather than that most circularity is benign, and only occasionally do we find bad eggs).
Later I acquired more positive motivations for ill-founded ontologies, of which the first came in thinking about logical AI, construing the mind as essentially reflective, and interpreting this as the need for functions which are self-applicable.
The need for functions which are self-applicable is not confined to this tendentious motivation.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
I have now been looking for the right kind of strong non-well-founded logical foundation for mathematics (or more generally, for abstract semantics) for more than a quarter of a century, if somewhat intermittently.
This is my hot button at the moment.
A breakthrough is imminent!
</p><p>
Because my conception of philosophical analysis is rather like Carnap's (though I am more <i>universalistic</i> than Carnap, while at the same time being a logical pluralist as well), a radical change of the kind I seek in the foundations inevitably impacts substantially the way in which all other formal work would be done.
So, if this is in prospect, it does focus attention.
The prospect can demotivate progressing formal applications, because one imagines that they might be done better if the new foundations were first in place.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
My present approach to this "holy grail" is as <xlink href="pp/doc/t041.pdf">a strong illative lambda-calculus</xlink>, with a system of type assignments which would make it look rather like a rich but not well-founded type theory.
My present focus, having formally defined a model for this system, is to secure a non-triviality result in the form of a Church-Rosser theorem for this model.
Since I am doing this all with machine-checked formal proofs, and I am not that hot, it is a slow business.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol/>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="THE SHED at RBJones.com" doc="index" dir="pp/doc">
If you want to see what I actually am doing, the best place to look is in <xlink href="pp/doc/index.html">THE SHED</xlink>.
This isn't everything that I am working on, but it is where the greater part of the real action is going on.
This is work in progress, expect it to be indiscipherable and misguided.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol/>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
