<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x003.xml,v 1.5 2011/11/29 16:45:36 rbj Exp $"
       title="Positive Philosophy"
       created="2006-01-01"
       description="Introduction to a contemporary positivist philosophy."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
It is a site of philosophical sketches.
At their more conservative these describe <i>metaphysical positivism</i> which is concerned centrally with deductive reason, analytic truth and more broadly with such philosophical truths as we may consider objective.
In another vein or plane <i>existential expressionism</i> concerns values which are in their essence subjective and all that depends on such values.
In the middle ground we have a constructive if philosophical interest in the automation of deductive reason.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
The rationale for my current conception of this, my personal website, is to be found in <i>existential positivism</i>.
The proximate provocation for existential positivism lies in the scientific evangelism of Richard Dawkins, who, perceiving an attack on rational science from fundamentalist religion has responded with a critique of faith (in general) and a defence of scientific rationality.
This seems to me too much like a conflict between different systems of institutionalised dogma for me to enrol on either side, but the battle lines drawn up by Dawkins have made me feel the need to state my own counter position to dogma of all kinds.
My position is rooted in a positive scepticism, for which the word <i>positivism</i>, coined by Auguste Comte is apt (even though positivisms have their dogmas).
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
I already was engaged in positivistic analytic philosophy, under the heading <i>metaphysical positivism</i>, which is at best tenuously relevant to present concerns.
I have opened up a second positivist front, more broadly scoped, under the heading <i>existential positivism</i>.
This is really no more than an account of my own personal belief system, extending to matters beyond the scope of analytic philosophy, taking a more definite stance on social, economic, political, moral, and of course existential concerns than could ever be justified analytically, and serving as an exemplar of the kinds of belief system which can sustain a sense of meaning and purpose in life in default of religious or other dogma.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Metaphysical Positivism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The Automation of Reason"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Existential Positivism"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Metaphysical Positivism" dir="philos" tag="MP" doc="x010" />
<section title="The Automation of Reason" tag="AR" doc="x002" />
<section title="Existential Positivism" dir="philos" tag="EE" doc="xp001" />

</xldoc>
