<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xhp003.xml,v 1.2 2010/01/25 13:11:02 rbj Exp $"
       title="RBJones.com"
       created="2006-01-31"
       description="Home page for the rbjones.com web site."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics utopia"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="left"><image name="rbjdcoml.gif" align="top" alt="rbjones.com"/></maintitle>
<indextitle>RBJones.com</indextitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Back in the starting blocks.
</abstract>
<secbody title="Winds of Change">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Socratic Progress">
<p>
I was intent on making this web site a window on the progress in my current philosophical writing projects, and still am.
However, the progress I am making at present is rather Socratic, I am learning that I have not yet reached a sufficiently clear and complete conception of the projects to consider myself properly engaged in their implementation.
I do believe that I am close, but I know that such beliefs are often ill-founded.
</p><p>
So at present this site may be thought of as providing a glimpse of my thinking on a pair of closely coupled book writing projects on which I will properly launch just as soon as the ideas become sufficiently settled.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Revolution?">
<p>
It feels like a revolution at present, that I am going through in my conception of the project, and a little too new to articulate very clearly what is involved.
There follows a little sketch of how my recent ideas have evolved, from some modest if central adjustments as I and then a step further in II, to something which seems like it may be a big change which I try to sketch in III.
</p><p>
Whereas the original idea was for a monograph on "The Fundamental Triple-Dichotomy", which broadened into a book on "Metaphysical Positivism" which would hang around a story about the triple-dichotomy, my conception of Metaphysical Positivism is now so substantially changed that a complete re-think of the structure of the exposition may be necessary.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Evolution of Metaphysical Positivism" dir="www/column" doc="s0911" />

<section title="The Status Quo">
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="purpose">
<p>
My aim in this site is to give the reader a vivid sense of the dynamics
of my current philosophical projects.
</p><p>
I have two book-writing projects taking off right now, and every step along
these roads of discovery will be presented here on RBJones.com long before the
books ever appear in print.
</p><p>
The site also contains a variety of previous cogitations.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="the books">
<p>
The first of these projects is to be entitled "Metaphysical Positivism" and
will be a new formulation of positivist philosophy.
The book is intended to be a prose volume of similar scale and character to
A.J.Ayer's "Language Truth and Logic".
However, the book is primarily a presentation of an analytic method.
It offers, rather than prescribes, a method, and provides analysis of that method,
rather than polemic in its favour or against other methods. 
</p><p>
The second, which provides both background for the former and an
extended exemplar of the method of analysis informally described in that book, will
be an analytic history of philosophical analysis, tracing the origins of our
method and exemplifying its use.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Metaphysical Positivism" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="An Analytic History of Philosophical Analysis" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<center>If you want to see the rest of the site,<br/>some places to start are:</center>
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Quick Index" href="index.htm" />
<subsec title="RBJones.com Top 100" href="rbj036.htm" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Metaphysical Positivism" dir="philos" doc="x010" tag="mp" />

<section title="An Analytic History of Philosophical Analysis" dir="philos/logic" doc="xpl001" tag="hpl" />

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
