<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xt002.xml,v 1.10 2007/02/20 22:14:05 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="The Stack of Change"
       created="2006-05-29"
       description="A stack shaped catalogue of areas of RBJones.com which are under development"
       keywords="rbjones.com stack log changes"
       up="x001.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
This is a "stack" of work in progress on this website.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
This is an experiment to help me keep track of what I am working on (or perhaps more the ones I'm not actually working on but have left in mid flow to follow some other hare).
</p>
<p>
I expect it to be a stack only in the loosest sense.
Which is, that the stuff at the top is what I'm working on.
The stuff later I was working on before that, and the further down you go the more distant the prospect that I will ever get back to it.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
I generally have so many pages in an incomplete state (most of them!) that I loose track of pages before I ever finish them.
Maybe this page will help me to get things nearer to completion. 
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Reflexive Foundations"/>
<secref title="Metaphysics"/>
<secref title="Rationality and Romanticism"/>
<secref title="Naive Philosophy"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="About Writing"/>
<secref title="Scepticism and Positivism"/>
<secref title="Logic and Mathematics"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Reflexive Foundations">
<abstract>
The search for a non-well-founded foundation system suited to the formal development of mathematics.
</abstract>
<secbody title="Introduction">
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
In September 2006 Thomas Forster announced that he would be holding meeting in 2007 for an anniversary connected with Quine's set theory NF.
I decided that I would do something with NF to get myself to a level of knowledge at which it would be worth my while to go to the meeting (thinking that in my then state of ignorance too little of the proceedings would be intelligible),
</p><p>
I began with some attempts to formalise NF and NFU in ProofPower, and one thing lead to another.
I was looking to use the formalisation of NF as a semantic domain for other (non set-theoretic) foundation systems, but as I spent time getting to understand NF better I gradually became convinced that NF was not the right starting point and decided that a non-well-founded set theory devised with my purposes in mind would be better.
</p><p>
That lead to the PolySets, which I made several starts at formalising some in ProofPower some in Isabelle.
The formal construction was completed in Isabelle, but proof work was rather slow (I am not fluent in Isabelle proofs).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
I liked the PolySets, and they seemed to do the main thing which inspired them, i.e., add to a full well-founded set ontology the graphs of (a transfinite extrapolation of) the kinds of polymorphic function definable in the programming language ML.
BUT, there was something more important, which I thought might come with that but which I came to suspect would not.
That is, the kind of context management similar in character to the ML let clause (which the PolySets probably are good for) but which is applied to the management of the more diverse kind of content which is needed in context for the formal development of mathematics.
I here refer to the sort of thing which "Locales" are aimed at in Isabelle. 
</p><p>
I use the category of categories as the test for this kind of context management (I know, the connection may not be obvious), and I came to feel it unlikely that the PolySets would do the trick,
So I have begun to think about stretching the PolySets further, and have several ideas I am progressing.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol title="Using ProofPower HOL">
<subsec title="NFU and NF in ProofPower HOL" dir="pp/doc" doc="t019" suf="pdf">
Several approaches to the formalisation of these theories are tried out here.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Category Theoretic Foundation Systems with Universal Categories" dir="pp/doc" doc="t018" suf="pdf">
This was the application I started to try the best advanced formalisation of NFU.
</subsec>
<subsec title="PolySet Theory" dir="pp/doc" doc="t020" suf="pdf">
This is an early approach to the construction of PolySets based on the non-axiomatic approach to set theory in "Membership Structures".
I very quickly came to feel this not a practical way of proceeding.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Interpretations of Set Theory" dir="pp/doc" doc="t021" suf="pdf">
This is my latest approach to the problem in which I begin with an axiomatic well-founded set theory, then construct the PolySets, as a preliminary to investigating the broadening of the ontology by adding complements.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="Using Isabelle HOL">
<subsec title="Membership" dir="isar/HOL" doc="Membership" suf="pdf">
This was my first attempt at the PolySets in Isabelle, using a set theory introduced with locales.
(more or less hypothesising the set theory rather than axiomatising it).
The locales weren't as helpful as I had hoped and I abandoned this approach in favour of building on an axiomatic set theory.
</subsec>
<subsec title="PolySets" dir="isar/HOL" doc="PolySets" suf="pdf">
This is the most substantial formal treatment, which gets as far as defining the representation type and the membership relationship and introducing a new type of PolySets, but not as far as proving anything useful about them.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="Plain(ish) English">
<subsec title="PolySets" dir="www/papers" doc="p011" suf="pdf">
This is my best effort at an informal description of the PolySets.
Some material on the "why"s and "wherefore"s, and some speculation about their properties,
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Metaphysics">
<abstract>
Groping for a grip on metaphysics.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysics" dir="philos" doc="x009" />
<subsec title="First Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x007" />
<subsec title="Metaphysical Problems" dir="philos" doc="x006" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
There are two main objectives here.
The first is to articulate a positivistic conception of metaphysics.
The second is to progress certain aspects of that.
The three specific aspects to progress are abstract ontology, space-time and concrete ontology.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Rationality and Romanticism" doc="xtc001" tag="rr"/>

<section title="Naive Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x020" tag="np"/>

<section title="About Writing" doc="xtc002" tag="aw"/>

<section title="Scepticism and Positivism" tag="sap">
<abstract>
The fundamental ethos of this web site is sceptical and scepticism is the main content of the "naive philosophy" which underpins all my other philosophy.
At a "higher" level my "positive" philosophy is in large part <i>metaphysicsl positivism</i>.
The articulation both of the sceptical and the positivistic aspects of my philosophy are skeletal, and this topic concerns fleshing them out a bit.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Naive Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x020" />
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism" dir="philos" doc="x010" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Logic and Mathematics" tag="lm">
<abstract>
At the extreme rationalist end of my philosophy formal methods loom large and in these logic and mathematics are crucial.
This is infrastructure for formal philosophy.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="X-Logic" dir="philos" doc="x005"/>
<subsec title="Automation of Reason, Some History" dir="philos" doc="x004"/>
<subsec title="Exact Real Computation" dir="cs" doc="xreal001"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
