<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xt001.xml,v 1.6 2010/01/10 21:30:11 rbj Exp $"
       title="Home Page History"
       created="2006-05-29"
       description="A graveyard for retired RBJones.com home pages"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy home page"
       up="x001.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Index">
<abstract>
Links to previous versions of the RBJones.com home page, together with some notes on the history of my web presence.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
The links here are to pages in the present web site which were at some stage in the past the home page that you get if you come into the site using only the domain name.
When modest changes take place the home page is updated in situ, but if something more radical happens a new page is started.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
They don't necessarily look like the did at the time, some material may be automatically incorporated from other pages which have changed, the things referred to may change, and in some cases the topic the page addresses may still be developing and the old home page is updated as my thinking about that topic develops..
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="December 2009" doc="xhp003">
At this point I decided to start with a "blank sheet" on the book/books.
So I archived the home page and started again with a blank home page.
</subsec>
<subsec title="August 2007" doc="xhp002" />
<subsec title="June 2005" doc="xhp001" />
<secref title="Positive Philosophy (April 2005)">
<abstract>
Here I focused on the structure of my ideas for achieving a better integrated synthesis between the rational and romantic sides of my philosophy.
</abstract>
</secref>
<subsec title="The Dark Ages (2001-2005)">
I don't have a version of the home page dating between 2001 and 2005.
After my burst of ideas at the beginning of 2000 I quickly went into creative meltdown, and though I continued to do some fragmentary work which appeared buried in the web site, I did was not working on the web site <i>as such</i>.
</subsec>
<subsec title="RBJones.com (2000)" doc="rbj054" suf="htm">
Two new domain names are introduced, x-logic.org and openbrand.org (which have since been abandoned).
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Factasia (1998-9)" doc="rbj040" suf="htm">
The last view of RBJones.com as Factasia.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Factasia (1996-7)" doc="rbj043" suf="htm">
This is the earliest home page in which RBJones.com has been styled as "Factasia".
The rationale for the transition to this conception of the web site is discussed in <a href="www/column/c0020.htm">premonitions of Factasia</a> 
</subsec>
<subsec title="Philosophical Classics in HTML" dir="philos/classics" doc="index" suf="htm">
The website was begun as soon as I first had access to a web server, which was in 1994, though at that time the service was internal to ICL (International Computers Limited as was, now absorbed into Fujitsu).
The site became visible globally probably in 1995.
I don't have a copy of the home pages of these early sites, but an idea of the content of the sites can be obtained by searching the present website for "created 1994" using Google.
The first things I did were HTML conversions of some philosophical classics, various pages of links and the beginnings of the bibliography and glossary.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Positive Philosophy (April 2005)" tag="001" dir="philos" doc="x018" />

</xldoc>
