<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xt002.xml,v 1.8 2006/09/11 10:11:46 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="The Stack of Change"
       created="2006-05-29"
       description="A stack shaped catalogue of areas of RBJones.com which are under development"
       keywords="rbjones.com stack log changes"
       up="x001.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
This is a "stack" of work in progress on this website.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
This is an experiment to help me keep track of what I am working on (or perhaps more the ones I'm not actually working on but have left in mid flow to follow some other hare).
</p>
<p>
I expect it to be a stack only in the loosest sense.
Which is, that the stuff at the top is what I'm working on.
The stuff later I was working on before that, and the further down you go the more distant the prospect that I will ever get back to it.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
I generally have so many pages in an incomplete state (most of them!) that I loose track of pages before I ever finish them.
Maybe this page will help me to get things nearer to completion. 
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Metaphysics"/>
<secref title="Rationality and Romanticism"/>
<secref title="Naive Philosophy"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="About Writing"/>
<secref title="Scepticism and Positivism"/>
<secref title="Logic and Mathematics"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Rationality and Metaphysics">
<abstract>
Firstly this move was provoked by my being referred to Algebraic Geometry by Rob Arthan as a better way of approaching differential geometry and more generally the matheamtics of physics.
(my main problem with the kind of metaphysics I am interested is in the mathematica; prerequisites for a formal analysis of the issues).
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysics" dir="philos" doc="x009" />
<subsec title="First Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x007" />
<subsec title="Metaphysical Problems" dir="philos" doc="x006" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
There are two main objectives here.
The first is to articulate a positivistic conception of metaphysics.
The second is to progress certain aspects of that.
The three specific aspects to progress are abstract ontology, space-time and concrete ontology.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Rationality and Romanticism" doc="xtc001" tag="rr"/>

<section title="Naive Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x020" tag="np"/>

<section title="About Writing" doc="xtc002" tag="aw"/>

<section title="Scepticism and Positivism" tag="sap">
<abstract>
The fundamental ethos of this web site is sceptical and scepticism is the main content of the "naive philosophy" which underpins all my other philosophy.
At a "higher" level my "positive" philosophy is in large part <i>metaphysicsl positivism</i>.
The articulation both of the sceptical and the positivistic aspects of my philosophy are skeletal, and this topic concerns fleshing them out a bit.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Naive Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x020" />
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism" dir="philos" doc="x010" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Logic and Mathematics" tag="lm">
<abstract>
At the extreme rationalist end of my philosophy formal methods loom large and in these logic and mathematics are crucial.
This is infrastructure for formal philosophy.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="X-Logic" dir="philos" doc="x005"/>
<subsec title="Automation of Reason, Some History" dir="philos" doc="x004"/>
<subsec title="Exact Real Computation" dir="cs" doc="xreal001"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
