<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xtc001.xml,v 1.3 2006/09/11 10:11:46 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Rationality and Romanticism"
       created="2006-06-04"
       description="Work on a synthesis of elements of rationality and romanticism, with the help of readings from Isaiah Berlin"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy rationality reason romanticism politics liberty Berlin"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Work on a synthesis of elements of rationality and romanticism, with the help of readings from Isaiah Berlin
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Introduction">
<p>
This "topic cluster" gathers together links to pages concerned with a direction of development in my philosophy the purpose of which is to integrate more fully into that philosophy ideas connected with the "Romantic" tradition in philosophy.
</p><p>
To further this I first sketched a new philosophical posture called <i>positive philosophy</i> in which <i>metaphysical positivism</i> is counterbalanced by something of a more Romantic character provisionally named <i>existential positivism</i>, accompanied by some discussion of the relationship between the rationalism of the enlightenment and the Romantic reaction against it.
</p><p>
I quickly came to the view that I really didn't know enough about Romanticism to be able to say anything meaningful about it, decided to do a bit of background reading, and somehow concluded that reading Isaiah Berlin might help.
I found Berlin readable and read several of his books.
In the course of this I came up with some ideas on how to take notes (which I do very badly), and how to bridge the gap between reading, taking notes, and various degrees of more tenuously connected writing about related ideas.
</p><p>
None of this has worked well.
My reading of Berlin is probably largely complete, at least for the time being, and my present preoccupation is with rethinking my philosophy with the "Romantic" elements having their proper influence.
I am now doing this along two parallel tracks of which the original synthesis in <i>positive philosophy</i> is one, and the second is a completely new approach based around some new epistemological ideas and called <i>synthetic philosophy</i>. 
</p><p>
The links provided are in order of decreasing distance from the reading material.
</p><p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Synthetic Philosophy" />
<secref title="Positive Philosophy" />
<secref title="Rationality and Romanticism" />
<secref title="Ideas on Political Philosophy" />
<secref title="Notes on Isaiah Berlin" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Synthetic Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x021" tag="sp"/>
<section title="Positive Philosophy" dir="philos" doc="x018" tag="pp"/>
<section title="Rationality and Romanticism" dir="philos" doc="x017" tag="rr"/>
<section title="Ideas on Political Philosophy" dir="philos/politics" doc="xpt001" tag="ipp"/>
<section title="Notes on Isaiah Berlin" dir="philos/history" doc="xh007" tag="nib"/>

</xldoc>
