<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xtc001.xml,v 1.1 2006/06/16 17:40:38 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Rationality and Romanticism"
       created="2006-06-04"
       description="Work on a synthesis of elements of rationality and romanticism, with the help of readings from Isaiah Berlin"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy rationality reason romanticism politics liberty Berlin"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Work on a synthesis of elements of rationality and romanticism, with the help of readings from Isaiah Berlin
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Introduction">
<p>
This is the first "topic cluster" testing out an idea of how to read a book and make the most of the ideas which arise during the reading.
The idea is to have a page linking together a cluster of pages in which I am working out some "topic" during the course of reading and making notes on the book.
The book in question right now is Isaiag Berlin's <i>Political Ideas in the Romantic Age [<bibref name="Berlin2006" />]</i> but I think it makes sense to use this "topic cluster" to cover any of Berlin's books which I may read or re-read in the future.
</p>
<p>
This cluster refers directly only to three pages.
The main purpose is to rewrite the page on Rationality and Romanticism.
Then I have a page for ideas on poliical philosophy which are not discussions of Berlin's writings or views, but which arise in the reading and don't belong in "Rationality and Romanticism".
The second is a page about Berlin's ideas, which in turn refers to a page collecting together my notes specific to each of the books by Berlin which I have read.
</p>
<p>
At the same time I am making notes on one of his books, adding to notes on his ideas, and collecting together any ideas of my own and sorting out my page on Rationality and Romanticism.
</p>
<p>
Topic clusters in progress are held in <i>The Stack of Change</i> and when work is completed, suspended or abandoned the topic is moved to a change log.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Rationality and Romanticism" />
<secref title="Ideas on Political Philosophy" />
<secref title="Notes on Isaiah Berlin" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Rationality and Romanticism" dir="philos" doc="x017" />
<section title="Ideas on Political Philosophy" dir="philos/politics" doc="xpt001" />
<section title="Notes on Isaiah Berlin" dir="philos/history" doc="xh007" />



</xldoc>
