<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: CQ90LOC.xml,v 1.1 2009/12/16 21:55:38 rbj Exp $"
       title="Notes on: Dear Carnap, Dear Van - Lectures on Carnap"
       created="2009/11/28"
       description="Notes on the published volume of correspondence between Carnap and Quine, covering Quine's 1934 lectures on Carnap's Philosophy of Logical Syntax"
       keywords="philosophy logic history semantics empiricism positivism Carnap Quine syntax"
       class="bib"
       up="carnapquine90.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle align="center"><image name="lgnote.gif"/> by
  <image name="rbjin1.gif"/> on<br/>Quine's lectures on Carnap's Philosophy of Logical Syntax</maintitle>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Quine gave three lectures on Carnap's Philosophy of Logical Syntax at Harvard in 1934.
The first of these lectures provided the basis for the paper <i>Truth by Convention [<bibref name="Quine36"/></i>].
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Background"/>
<secref title="Lecture I: The A Priori"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Lecture II: Syntax"/>
<subsec title="Lecture III: Philosophy as Syntax"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Background">
<abstract>
A few words placing the lectures in historical context.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol><subsec title="">
<p>
On completing his doctoral dissertation (in just two years) Quine obtained a Sheldon Travelling Fellowship (for one year) and went to Vienna in the fall of 1932.
Carnap had then taken up a position in Prague, so after attending lectures by Schlick in Vienna Quine went on to Prague in the spring, meeting Carnap in March 1933.
Carnap was then writing <i>Logische Syntax Der Sprache [<bibref name="Carnap34"/>]</i>, and Quine had the opportunity to read the book as it was typed up by Ina Carnap.
</p>
</subsec></sbcol>
<sbcol><subsec>
<p>
Quine's reservations about the analytic/synthetic distinction date from this first acquaintance with Carnap's work. 
</p>
</subsec></sbcol>
<sbcol><subsec>
<p>
Quine was elected a junior fellow of Harvard while in Europe.
His doctoral dissertation was being prepared for publication, but Quine's European travels resulted in his wishing to make substantial changes, the completion of which occupied the greater part of his time during the first year of his three year fellowship.
He was also asked to prepare three lectures on the philosophy of Carnap, which were delivered in November 1934.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Lecture I: The A Priori" tag="I">
<abstract>
Quine's first lecture addresses primarily the concept of analyticity and also the a priori, not professing to be an account of Carnap's philosophy, but rather as providing introductory background prior to an account of Carnap's philosophy of logical syntax in the second and third lectures.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Definitions of Analyticity and the A Priori">
<p>
This lecture is devoted to a discussion of "the analytic character of the a priori".
Quine begins by reference to Kant, citing first Kants view that analytic judgements are a proper subset of the a priori, and quoting the definition of a priori as having "the character of inward necessity".
"and holds independently of any possible experience".
</p><p>
He provides multiple characterisations of (or claims about) analyticity as follows:
<ol>
<li>a judgement the truth of which can be established directly by analysis of the concepts involved</li>
<li>an analytic judgement can do no more than call our attention to something already contained in the definitions of our terms</li>
<li>consequences of definitions, conventions as to the uses of words</li>
<li>consequences of linguistic fiat</li>
</ol>
and observes that among them "are to be reckoned" logic and "the bulk, at least" of mathematics.
</p><p>
Quine then notes Kant's view that there are judgements which are synthetic but a priori (e.g. those of geometry), and the more recent grounds for rejecting this claim (by showing that the whole of mathematics, including geometry, is analytic), and the doctrine that all a priori judgements are analytic.
To examine this claim Quine proposes to examine in detail "the nature of the analytic".
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Commentary">
<p>
On the face of it the first item is offered as a definition and subsequent items are clarifications, but these by no means follow.
Possibly his intention is that we should read them conjointly as defining the concept.
</p><p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Definitions">
<p>
Quine begins by distinguishing two kinds of definition, <i>explicit</i> definitions, which are "merely a convention of abbreviation", and <i>implicit</i> definitions, which are sets of rules specifying that certain sentences in which the word (say 'K') being defined occur and which are to be accepted by convention as true, "their truth constitutes the meaning of 'K'".
Quine observes that definitions have often been construed as exclusively of the kind he calls "explicit", but that it is convenient in the present context to adopt the broader usage (noting that there is precedent for it).
</p><p>
Quine then tells us that analyticity depends on (nothing more than) definitions.
This leads to an extended expansion of his explanation of analyticity based around examples of how this process of defining a language might proceed.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Commentary">
<p>
Note first that Quine's canonical notion of definition, his "explicit" definitions, are syntactic in character, they are syntactic abbreviations, and Quine does not appear here to have a notion of definition as assigning meaning to or denotation for a new name.
</p><p>
Note also that Quine does not mention here that his explicit definitions are eliminable, whereas his implicit definitions may not be.
</p><p>
It may be helpful to consider to what extent Quine's arguments depend upon his particular conception of definition and to what extent the arguments remain sound if we adopt, for example, a conception of definition as introducing a new name (constant) by conservative extension to an existing language or theory.
</p><p>
Quine's conception of analyticity makes it dependent not on meanings, but on definitions.
This conception he applies to natural languages not merely to formally defined languages, so one might get the impression that analyticity only arises in natural languages once the language has been partly or wholly augmented by definitions of the words of the language.
</p><p>
This makes Quine's conception of analyticity dependent on a process of formalisation which is potentially more problematic than the identification of analytic sentences in natural languages on unmediated operation of our intuitions about their meaning, without the need to deliver definitions of all the terms involved.
</p><p>
The cases in which the concept is most readily applicable are those in which a sentence in a natural language is considered in which there is no significant difficulty of comprehension, or a sentence in a formal language whose subject matter is straightforward and whose semantics can be presented unambiguously (for example the first order language of arithmetic).
Quine's subsequent explication of the idea of analyticity through a process of providing definitions for terms originating in a natural language is the least plausible context for a successful outcome.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Lecture II: Syntax" tag="II">
<abstract>
On Carnap's syntactic methods and the method of arithmetisation.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Semantics and Syntax">
<p>
Quine begins with a discussion of the meaning of the word "semantic", which apparently was then in use not only by Pierce to talk about menaing, but aslo by Chistwick in a sense which embraced syntax.
Quine presents Carnap's use of the term "syntax" as a means of avoiding this ambiguity in the term "semantic".
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Kinds od Rules">
<p>
We next hear that Carnap divides his rules of syntax into two kinds rules of <i>formation</i> and of <i>transformation</i>.
The formation rules are concerned with grammar and tell us what are the meaningful sentences.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Formation Rules">
<p>
Quine notes the complexity of a full account of the formation rules for natural languages and cites this as the reason why Carnap choses an artificial language as object for syntactic study.
He then goes on to describe the formation rules for an artificial language somewhat, but not entirely like one used by Carnap.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Transformation Rules">
<p>
The transformation rules "specify the conditions under which a sentence may be <i>inferred</i>".
They "answer to" what Quine described in his first lecture as <i>implicit definitions</i>.
Quine replays the formal system from the first lecture, which covers the propositional calculus and unspecified other areas, offering these as examples of transformation rules (among which he appears to include axiom schemata).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



