<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: fut007.xml$"
       title="The Future of Humanity"
       description="Reasoning about the Future of Humanity"
       keywords=""
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
There are many ways in which we might think about the future of humanity.
Here I sketch one approach.
</abstract>

<secbody title="Introduction">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Reasoning about The Future">
<p>
Is is possible to reason about the (distant) future?
</p><p>
Much of what is written about the medium-to-long-term future is speculative and unconvincing.
Is this the best that can be done, or are there methods which provide
more soundly based projections into the future?
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Methods">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="">
<sbcol>
<secref title="Values"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Purposes"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Methods"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="Forecasts to Build Around">
<sbcol title="Short Term Projections">
<subsec title="Personal Assistants">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Self-Driving Cars">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="Long Term Projections">
<subsec title="Machine Intelligence">
</subsec>
<subsec title="Human Evolution by Genome Design">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

<section title="Purposes">
<abstract>
Its a good idea to think a little first about what you are trying to achieve.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="In General">
<p>
In general my thinking about the future (at the levels currently under consideration, by constrast with my wondering what the weather might be like tomorrow) is intended to contribute to a contemporary discussion which shapes our conception of what the future might be and what we can do today to steer the ship towards those kinds of future which we consider most desirable.
</p><p>
The ways in which such discussions can shape the future might influence what kinds of thinking it is worth undertaking, so it might be worth thinking this through in greater detail, but in the first instance I will pass over this matter.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="More Specifically">
<p>
I'm going to consider what aspect of the future of humanity will most effectively contribute to the kind of future society I would wish to see.
</p><p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Methods">
<abstract>
Let's call a method for achieving some purpose rational if it is a good way of going about that end.
I am here concerned to distinguish between rational and irrational ways of enquiring into the future.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>

</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p><p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>



