<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: index.xml,v 1.1.1.1 2006-04-19 20:44:51 rbj01 Exp $"
       name="index"
	   title="X-Logic"
	   description="Overview of the X-Logic site"
	   keywords="x-logic xml logic philosophy"
	   class="con"
       root="../"
       path="arch/"
       up="../index.html"
	   rbjhome="http://www.rbjones.com/rbjpub/rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
The X-Logic project aims to build generic (i.e. not specific to particular languages or logics) support for deductive inference, with an emphasis on integration with the XML standards.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Philosophy"/>
<secref title="Prospectus"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="WorkPlan"/>
<secref title="Releases"/>
<subsec title="Directories" href="../directories.html">
The directory tree of X-Logic.org giving full access to work in progress.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
The ultimate content of X-Logic remains at this stage quite open.
Nevertheless we have available a prospectus, some preliminary work on philosophical principles, a crude workplan and a first (pre-design!) alpha release.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Philosophy">
The term "philosophy" here covers a broad span.
This is a sufficiently important part of the grounding for X-Logic that X-Logic.org hosts the OpenMind formal philosophy site, a major part of which is concerned with foundations for X-Logic.
A crucial output from the philosophical analysis is high level formal models which contribute to the architectural design of X-Logic.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Prospectus">
In a less formal sense the X-Logic Prospectus is also
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="WorkPlan">
A crude workplan for near term work is now available.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Releases">
The first alpha release concerns the technologies used to build the X-Logic.org website, which includes literate scripts for formal models and listings of the theories created under ProofPower from these scripts, all created from XML sources.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Philosophy" doc="index" dir="../OpenMind">
<abstract>
The OpenMind web site is a testbed for X-Logic technologies and the source of philosophical foundations and high-level formal models for X-Logic.
</abstract>
</section>

<section title="Prospectus" doc="prosp01"/>

<section title="WorkPlan" doc="workplan"/>

<section title="Releases" doc="releases"/>

</xldoc>

