<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: releases.xml,v 1.1.1.1 2006-04-19 20:44:51 rbj01 Exp $"
       name="releases"
	   title="X-Logic Release information"
	   description="File releases of X-Logic available for download"
	   keywords="x-logic xml logic philosophy"
	   class="con"
       root="../"
       path="arch/"
       up="index.html"
	   rbjhome="http://www.rbjones.com/rbjpub/rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
This is just a few notes to explain what the currently available releases of X-Logic are.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
X-Logic is made available as two modules for download.
These modules are not very likely to be actually <i>useful</i> to anyone at this stage, but might possibly help to give some idea of what the project is about.
</p>
<p>
My synchronisation is a bit off as yet, so this page which tells you about the downloads is not actually in the site whose downloads are now available.
Next time I make a release I'll do the documentation before the release not after.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The X-Logic.org Web Site"/>
<secref title="The X-Logic Sources"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The X-Logic.org Web Site">
<abstract>
The X-Logic.org web site, including the OpenMind philosophy site, is available for local browsing as a gzipped tar file.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="name and version">
This is called "x-logic-www.1.0.tar.gz".
It may be helpful to anyone who prefers to read its content offline, or anyone who wants to see the delivered HTML files (though its probably better to look at the XML which does not come in this module).
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Instructions for Use">
This is a self contained relocatable web site.
If you gunzip and untar the file and then open for the top level "index.html" file with your browser you should find the site is browsable offline.
This should work on Windows as well as UNIX, provided you have the wherewithall to unpack the file.
Not sure about other operating systems but I don't know any reason why not.
There are no cgi-bins, you don't need to be running an http server.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The X-Logic Sources" doc="sources"/>

</xldoc>









