<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xep002.xml,v 1.1 2009/03/31 17:52:58 rbj Exp $"
       title="Defining Analyticity"
       created="2009-01-30"
       description=""
       keywords="rbjones philosophy epistemology analyticity necessity Quine Kripke"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
A definition of analyticity is offered and its merits discussed.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Background"/>
<secref title="The Definition"/>
<secref title="Clarification of the Definition"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Relation to Previous Definitions"/>
<secref title="The Merits"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Background" tag="bg">
<abstract>
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="A Formal Model">
This discussion may be viewed as a sequel to a formal model which I knocked up
some years ago <xlink href="rbj014.htm">Modelling the Triple-Dichotomy</xlink> and
the discussion there may be worth reading to provide further background.
The idea of the formal model was to show the analyticity of the identification
of analyticity and necessity by actually proving it.
However, once the definitions are framed the identity is too obvious to warrant
proof of any kind.

The informal definition given here is essentially the same as that in the
formal model, the main difference being that here analyticity is explicitly
defined in terms of necessity, and reasons are given why that is a good idea.
In the consequences connections with some of Kripke's ideas are discussed,
which provide additional reasons (which I did not appreciate when I wrote the
formal model) for defining analyticity in this way.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Quine and Kripke">
<p>
This is part of a philosophical position in which the analytic/synthetic distinction assumes the central role which it had in Hume's philosophy (and later in Logical Positivism).
In the present historical context, such a position requires repudiation of
incompatible views promulgated by Quine and Kripke, and inevitably it is in that light which this must be viewed.
</p><p>
Quine sometimes backed off outright rejection of the analytic/synthetic dichotomy, claiming instead that the distinction could serve no philosophical purpose.
The definition given here is intended to give a concept of analyticity which does plainly serve two purpose.
These are not novel, they are two purposes which have been prominent in
positivist thought since Hume.
<ul>
<li>
Firstly, to make intelligible the epistemological distinction between the <i>a
priori</i> and the <i>a posteriori</i>.
</li>
<li>
Secondly, to secure an analytic connection between analyticity and necessity,
resulting in the elimination of necessity <i>de re</i> (i.e. of a certain kind
of metaphysics, encompassing the kind made fashionable by Kripke).
</li></ul>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>


<section title="The Definition" tag="def">
<abstract>
A sentence is analytic iff it expresses a necessary proposition.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Proposition, Necessity">
<p>
The kind of necessity at stake here is of course that which philosophers term
"logical" necessity, which unlike general usage of the term "necessary" is a
term-of-art in analytic philosophy.
More specifically this is to be understood here as paraphrased "true in all
possible worlds", but not necessarily involving a metaphysical commitment to
the existence of possible worlds.
</p><p>
The definition relates to truths, defining analytic truth in terms of necessary
truth, which could of course be done without mentioning propositions.
However the mention of propositions is in fact useful.
The word proposition stands here for the meaning of a sentence in context sufficient for its disambiguation.
Exactly what that might be, and whether this is conceived as some abstract or
metaphysical entity or as a manner of speaking which can be interpreted without
ontic commitment is left as dependent on the particular language in question
(and on the manner in which the semantics of the language is understood).
The implicit constraint however is that the meanings of sentences must be the
kind of thing which can be said to be necessary, and hence which incorporate in some
way the truth conditions determining the truth value of the proposition in
every possible world.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Generalisation to Other Truth Values">
<p>
It does not help for present purposes to generalise this definition to all
truth values, and for that reason I have put forward the simpler rendition.
The generalisation might go along the lines "a sentence has analytically the truth
value t iff it expresses a proposition which is necessarily t", however I would
be tempted myself if entering into such detail to render it formally, which I
would do along the lines of
<xlink doc="rbj014">Modelling the Triple-Dichotomy</xlink>
modifying that formal model by making the
definitions of analyticity and necessity less independent (i.e. defining the
former in terms of the latter).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


<section title="Clarification of the Definition" tag="cd">
<abstract>
Some clarification of the scope of the definition and of the terms used in the definition.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Terms of Art">
<i>analytic</i>, <i>necessary</i>, <i>proposition</i> are all intended here
with meanings particular to their application in philosophy.
About which I make some preliminary remarks:
</subsec>
<subsec title="analytic">
<i>analytic</i> is being defined, and therefore should be understood as
  here defined. It is nevertheless intended that this be broadly in line with
  at least some of its previous usage, and in particular, broadly in line with
  the idea of expressing a 'relation between ideas' occuring in David Hume.
</subsec>
<subsec title="necessary">
<i>necessary</i> should be understood as <i>logically</i> necessary, which
  in turn is to be understood as 'true in every possible world' (without
  neccessarily involving commitment to the existence of 'possible worlds' as
  metaphysical entities)
  The nominalist may wish to construe a logically necessary truth as one whose
  truth may be established without knowledge of the particular world in the
  context of which it is to be evaluated (except possible of the meaning of the
  language in which it is expressed and any context necessary for
disambiguation).
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="proposition">
<p>
a <i>proposition</i> is to be understood as the meaning of a
  sentence in sufficient context for disambiguation. Since this is an aspect of
  the semantics of a language, we allow that the notion of proposition be
  language relative.
</p><p>
The notion of analyticity is not applicable to all
  languages, it is applicable only to indicative sentences in descriptive or
  abstract languages.
  By descriptive is here meant a language intended for saying something about the
  material world, whereas an abstract language may refer only to abstract
  entities and not to the material world.
  The character of such languages, and the constraint on the applicability of
  the concept of analyticity may be seen in the nature of the propositions
  which are their meanings.
</p><p>
  The essence of a proposition is to convey information about what the world is
  like by excluding certain possibilities, i.e. by identifying a collection of
  possibilities among which the actual world may be found, and a complementary
  collection amoung which the actual world may not be found.
  It is not intended that the trivial cases be excluded (necessary and
  contradictory propositions).
  Nor is it intended that the truth value of a proposition be known in every
  possible world, it may be that in some possible worlds it has no truth value
  (whether this is possible depends on the language in question).
</p><p>
  It is required however, that the semantics of a language is couched in terms
  of a notion of proposition adequate to encompass all that is determinate in
  the language about the truth value of the proposition in the various possible
  worlds envisaged in the semantics.
  The is essential for logical necessity to be an operator on propositions, and
  ensures that insofar as a proposition is necessary, this information is
  embodies in the semantics of the language so that a sentence expressing that
  proposition will be analytic.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>


<section title="Relation to Previous Definitions" tag="rpd">
<abstract>
The main point here is to argue that the given definition says almost exactly
the same as "true in virtue of meaning".
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="True in Virtue of Meaning">
<p>
In the twentieth century the idea that analyticity should best be defined
as <i>truth in virtue of meaning</i> was put forward by various positivist
thinkers.
In Quine's "Two Dogmas of Empiricism" there is an excellent informal explanation of this
concept of analyticity.
It is not my present purpose to defend Quine's definition (I think
it needs no defence), but rather to explain how the definition above can be understood as a minor refinement of it.
</p><p>
A proposition is the meaning of a sentence (given sufficient context to
disambiguate the sentence). 
To say that a sentence expresses a proposition in some given context is simply
to say that in that context the meaning of the sentence is that proposition.
</p><p>
When a proposition is asserted the truth of the assertion depends in general upon which
possible world is actual, this is just a way of saying that its truth value
depends upon what is the case, in particular on whether the condition it
embodies is the case.
When the necessity of a proposition is asserted, this assertion does not depend
upon what is the case, for it is asserted that the proposition will be true in
every case.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Extra Bit">
<p>
Couching the definition of analyticity explicitly in terms of necessity forces
the notion of meaning relative to which analyticity is considered to be the
same as the notion of meaning embodied in the propositions which are the
subjects of modal operators.
</p><p>
It would of course be the case that if analyticity were to be judged by an
incomplete semantics, then in some cases sentences would fail to be analytic
simply because there was not sufficient information in the semantics to
establish truth.
This would be the case even if the truth values of the proposition expressed by
the sentence were completely determinate so as to make the proposition
necessary.
</p><p>
Insofar as defined in terms of "truth in virtue of meaning" the concept of
analyticity should therefore be defined as truth in virtue of the <i>full</i>
meaning incorporating all that is determinate about the truth conditions of the
sentence.
If the sentence is necessary, this is a fact about its truth conditions which
must be incorporated in the meaning relative to which analyticity is to be understood.
This falls out naturally, if analyticity is defined in terms of necessity, and
subject to the caveat on the meaning of meaning these two definitions say the
same thing.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>


<section title="The Merits" tag="merits">
<abstract>
Why its a good idea to define analyticity in terms of necessity.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="1. Defining Analyticity and Necessity Independently">
<p>
If we attempt a formal analysis in which analyticity and necessity are
independently defined, the definitions turn out to be the substantively
identical.
</p><p>
The most signficant difference is if analyticity is taken to be a property of
statements and necessity of propositions, but as soon as the derivative
application to the other category is included this difference melts away.
</p><p>
It therefore seems more sensible to make a merit of their interdefinability,
and to define the property of statements in terms of the property of propositions.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="3. Forcing a Single Conception of Semantics">
The primary merit of defining analyticity in terms of necessity is that it
forces the same conception of semantics to be used in both of these terms.
It ensures that the information available to determine questions of necessity
is also available for deciding analyticity.
This prevents the separation of analyticity from necessity by hypothesing
features of language which influence necessity but do not influence analyticity.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="2. Semantics Versus Metaphysics">
<p>
It is often said that analyticity is a semantic concept but that necessity is a
metaphysical concept (and/or a modal concept), and that on that basis they must
be distinct concepts and if coextensive this requires some demonstration.
</p><p>
This position to some extent begs the question against the nominalist, but ours
may be said to beg the question against the essentialist..
</p><p>
Against this I argue:
<ol>
<li>that as an operator on propositions (which are the meanings of
sentences) necessity is clearly a semantic characteristic</li>
<li>that an element of ``metaphysics'' may be seen in semantics, insofar as
  the formulation of a truth conditional semantics involves identification of
  the domain of discourse, the notion of possible world</li>
</ol>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>


<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>


<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

</xldoc>
