<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xep006.xml,v 1.2 2011/12/04 19:50:45 rbj Exp $"
       title="The Dichotomies Before Hume"
       created="2009-03-11"
       description="First part of a story about the origins and debate over the analytic-synthetic dichotomy"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy epistemology analytic synthetic"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Early Greek Philosophy"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Scepticism and Dogmatism"/>
<secref title="Rationalism and Empiricism"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Early Greek Philosophy" tag="egp">
<abstract>
An early approximation to Hume's fork may be found in Plato, and Aristotle's metaphysics may be seen as responding to some of the weaknesses in Plato's system which are relevant to Hume's fork.
</abstract>
<secbody title="Pre-Socratic Philosophy">
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
The Greek's may be thought of as having invented, or at least as having been the first to make much of, deductive reasoning.
Very early a disparity could be observed in the success with which deduction operated in different domains of discourse.
The contrast is seen most clearly between mathematics, in which a growing body of accepted theory was developed, ultimately gathered together in Euclid's elements, by contrast with which, metaphysicians constantly contradicted each others conclusions.
The unreliability of deduction was copiously illustrated by the paradoxes of Zeno, and by the time of Socrates the sophist Protagoras asserted that "Man is the measure of all things", thus denying that there are objective truths.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
An important example of contrasting dogmas from pre-socratic philosophers were those of Heraclitus and Parmenides, of whom the first asserted that everything changes, and the second that nothing changes.
The reconciliation of these two opposing points of view was one objective of Plato's philosophy, and leads him into our first approsimation to Hume's fork.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Plato">
<p>
Plato's philosophy reconciles the contradictory perspectives of Heraclitus and Parmenides by having two "worlds", one of timeless ideals or forms, and one of shifting ephemeral appearances.
In the former we have a domain in which the philosopher might reason with the same reliability as the mathematician, and which Plato regards as the true reality, in the other we have unreliable sensory evidence about real objects which fail to to match the ideal characteristics of the forms in which they participate.
</p><p>
We can see this as a precursor of the distinction between logical and empirical truth which is based on distinction of subject matter.
In this picture we see the distinction in reliability between logical and empirical truth.
It does not however allow that there are any <i>essential</i> truths about the world of appearances, does not allow that we can reason logically about the world of appearances.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Aristotle">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Scepticism and Dogmatism" tag="sd">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Rationalism and Empiricism" tag="re">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
