<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xep005.xml,v 1.2 2009/04/07 14:53:40 rbj Exp $"
       title="Restating the Dichotomies"
       created="2009-02-04"
       description="A concise description of the necessary-analytic-a priori/contingent-synthetic-a posteriori distinction"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy epistemology necessary contingent analytic synthetic priori posteriori"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
A concise description of the necessary-analytic-a priori/contingent-synthetic-a posteriori distinction.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Preliminaries"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Necessary"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Defining Analyticity"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="A Priori"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Afterthoughts"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Preliminaries">
<abstract>
Context setting descriptions of the kind of language and semantics to which
these concepts are applicable.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Descriptive Language, Indicative Sentences">
<p>
The principle concepts defined are intended to mark a fundamental and objective
division into two kinds of certain kinds of sentence in certain kinds of language. 
</p><p>
These are <i>indicative</i> sentences in <i>descriptive</i> languages.
</p><p>
Language is descriptive if it may be used to convey information about "the
world" in a particular way.
This is done using <i>indicative sentences</i> each of which says something
about how the world might be by describing some condition which might or might
not obtain.
A full understanding of such a sentence consists in knowing in principle how to
determine whether the condition described holds in any particular situation, or
state of affairs.
"In principle" here is intended to steer the reader away from expecting too
much from such an understanding.
It is not required, for example, that given any description of some state of
affairs one can easily determine whether the condition is satisfied.
The difference is similar to that between being <i>well-defined</i> and
being <i>decidable</i>.
The former suffices.
</p><p>
What is involved in <i>an understanding</i> is however not here at stake.
What concerns is rather the information content in the meaning of indicative
sentences (in context), which we
require to encompass <i>truth conditions</i> determining its truth value in
each possible circumstance. .
</p><p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Possible Worlds">
Possible worlds are often said to be <i>metaphysical</i>, but they are an
essential feature of the semantics of descriptive languages..
The semantics of such languages encompasses truth conditions for statements
made in the languages.
These truth conditions assign truth values to the statements in every possible
circumstance.
The range of circumstances for which the truth values of a descriptive language
are determined are the "possible worlds".
</subsec>
<subsec title="Meaning, Propositions">
<p>
In an abstract sense, the semantics of a language assigns meaning to
statements in the language, and this meaning may be thought of as that which
synonymous statements have in common.
We use the name "proposition" for the meaning of statements.
Among the features shared by synonymous statements is the truth conditions of
the statements, which are therefore part of the information content of the
proposition expressed by a statement. 
</p><p>
Exactly what a proposition is, we need not know, but an attempt to formalise
the semantics of a language may involve a choice of representative for
propositions (though some suitable meta-languages may permit propositions to be
specified abstractly, without any nomination of any particular
representatives).
</p><p>
Similar considerations apply to the notion of "possible world".
The possible worlds are the domain of the truth conditions, they are the range
of circumstance in which the truth values of statements are determined by the
truth conditions.
An abstract characterisation of the notion of possible world is a part of the
semantics of a descriptive language, if the semantics of the language is
codified this may involve choice of representatives for the possible worlds.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Necessary">
<abstract>
A proposition is necessary if it is true in every possible world.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="logical">
The definition is of the notion of <i>logical</i> necessity, which is a
term-of-art in philosophy rather than a notion in general currency.
The definition should be taken as a <i>proposal</i> for usage, it is not
claimed that it is equivalent to any previous usage.
Of course the wording of the definition is not novel, but the intended
interpretation of the concepts in terms in the definiens must of course be taken into
account in any comparison.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="proposition">
The term <i>proposition</i> is used to refer to some statement as a
mathematician might say "up to equivalence of meaning".
Those without nominalistic qualms on the score of propositions may take it to
be "the meaning" of some sentence given sufficient context for disambiguation.
Those with greater qualms may consider it to be an equivalence class of
sentences in context (again with sameness of meaning determining the class).
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Defining Analyticity" doc="xep002" tag="analytic" />

<section title="A Priori">
<abstract>
We should expect an <i>a priori</i> justification for a necessary proposition
and an <i>a posteriori</i> justification for a contingent proposition.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="1. Introduction">
<p>
The distinction between analytic and synthetic statements is a distinction of
subject matter.
A synthetic statement tells us something about the world, an analytic statement
does not.
It is natural connect this semantic difference with an epistemic one.
The manner in which we establish the truth of a statement should be connected
with its content.
If a statement has empirical content, then it will be true in some possible
worlds and false in others, and to establish whether it is true we need to know
something about which possible world corresponds to reality.
By contrast, one cannot establish that a statement is necessary using a case
which involves facts from any particular universe, one can at best thereby
establish its truth in that particular world.
</p><p>
To make this point we use the concepts <i>a priori</i> and <i>a posteriori</i>
which must be defined with care if they are to capture precisely the epistemic
difference between analytic and synthetic statements.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="2. Defining The A Priori">
<p>
We define the concept of the <i>a priori</i> as a property
of <i>justifications</i>, a justification being a case for belief in some
proposition.
</p>
<p>
A justification is <i>a priori</i> if it makes no use of any information about
the actual state of the universe (and hence we may say is equally relevant to
every possible state of the universe).
Information about the actual state of the universe may be thought of as
contingent propositions, so an alternative formulation is that a justification
is <i>a priori</i> if it makes no epistemic use of contingent propositions.
</p>
<p>
Any other justification is <i>a posteriori</i>.
</p>
<p>
Some statements may be considered self evident, standing as their own
justification.
In that case they will be <i>a priori</i> if necessary and otherwise <i>a posteriori</i>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="3. Knowledge">
<p>
We are not here concerned with knowledge, and take no position on the meaning
of that term, but, if knowledge is supposed to be
justified, then it may be said to be <i>a priori</i> if it has a
justification <i>a priori</i> and otherwise <i>a posteriori</i>.
</p><p>
Note that in this conception of <i>a priori</i> knowledge, the manner in which
we discover the proposition is immaterial, only the manner of justification is
relevant.
</p><p>
Note also that we are concerned with the justification of the proposition, not
of any statement expressing the proposition.
We may say that a statement expressing the proposition is justified <i>a
    priori</i> if the proposition is justified <i>a
    priori</i>, but note that the establishment of the connection between a
statement and the proposition it expresses is irrelevant to the epistemic status
of either.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="4. Facts Excluded from Consideration">
In considering the epistemic status of a statement, the following two kinds of
factual information should be disregarded (i.e. should not render the
statement <i>a posteriori</i>).
<ol>
<li>information needed to establish which proposition is expressed by the statement</li>
<li>information which played some role in the discovery of the proposition,
  but which does not feature in its justification</li>
</ol>

The first category is of particular relevance to the use of rigid designators,
since in these cases knowledge of the thing designated is essential to the
identification of the proposition expressed, and the manner of discovery (of
the thing designated) is therefore immaterial to the epistemic status on this conception of <i>a priority</i>.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Afterthoughts">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
