<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: ctf.xml,v 1.1 2005/04/09 14:00:53 rbj Exp $"
       name="ctf"
       title="Category Theoretic Foundation Systems"
       description="Various forays in categorical foundations for mathematics."
       keywords="logic proofpower gst hol set theory functor category pure"
       class="con"
       root="../../../"
       path="rbjpub/pp/gst/"
       up="index.html"
       rbjhome="../../rbj.htm"
       maintitle="mnt">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
This document creates a theory of pure concrete categories and functors.
The theory contains a set of theorems which might serve as an independent axiomatisation of the theory.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction" />
<secref title="Definitions of Pure Categories and Functors" />
<secref title="Axioms for Pure Categories and Functors" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Definitions of Pure Abstract Categories and Functors" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Work on foundation systems for mathematics which are <i>ontologically</i> category theoretic, i.e. in which the things in the domain of discourse are the stuff of category theory, categories, arrows, functors.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title='What is a "Foundation System"'>
In this context this term refers to a <i>logical</i> foundation <i>for mathematics</i>.
This means, a formal deductive system sufficiently strong (in an appropriate sense) that in it the concepts of mathematics can be introduced <i>by definition</i> and the theorems of mathematics expressed in terms of these concepts can be formally demonstrated.
No such systems were known prior to the twentieth century.
The most widely accepted system in the twentieth century has been the first order formalisation of set theory known as Zermelo-Fraenkel set theory (ZFC).
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title='What is a "Category Theoretic" Foundation System'>
Not an easy question to answer.
Category theorists and others have made certain complaints about set theory as a foundation for mathematics, and have made some suggestions about alternative foundations.
I have not myself found it easy see the connection between the complaints and the remedies, but I will mention some of each before saying something more about the kinds of "category theoretic" foundation systems which interest me personally.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody title="Some Complaints">
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<ul>
<li>well-foundedness
<p>
Sauders Mac Lane in his classic texbook "Categories for the Working Mathematician" has an eary section on "Foundations".
It is the purpose of this section to clarify the foundational context in which the rest of the book is to be understood, and the terminology of "small" (which actually means though he doesn't put it this way, "of accessible rank") and "large" categories (which have the smallest inaccessible rank) categories which is adopted.
 in which he first remarks on the problems arising from the fact that many collections of interest to category theorists (for example, the collection of all groups) are not sets in ZFC.
This problem is a consequence of the well-foundedness of the ontology of ZFC.
</p>
</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<ul>
<li>lack of abstraction</li>
<p>
Category theory is arguably, in a certain sense of the word, the most abstract kind of  mathematics.
Some category theorist, believing that the mathematics should be as it is seen through category theory, find fault with the method used in the derivation of mathematics in set theory, of coding up the various mathematical structures as sets.
The study of mathematical structures should be done without reference to particular exemplars of the structure, the structure should be studied in abstraction from its instances.
</p>
<li>ontological extravagence</li>
<p>
Some category theorists regard category theory as being <i>constructive</i>, think that appropriate foundations for mathematics should also be constructive, and are hostile particularly to the outer reaches of set theoretic ontology as being the antithesis of constructive mathematics.
</p>
</ul>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Some Remedies">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Method">
This stuff is all done in the context of a strong higher order set theory, i.e. <a href="index.html" target="_top">gst</a> in ProofPower HOL.
The method is to construct a set theoretic semantic model of the proposed category theoretic foundation system, to make new types and define the primitive relations and operators by this means and then formulate and prove a set of theorems which would serve as an indepedent axiomatisation of the proposed foundation systems.
Generally they are intended to be equivalent in strength to gst, and so in principle the gst could be reconstructed.
In some cases some steps toward this have been taken.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Three Variants">
I have at present in mind three categorical foundation system along the lines discussed.
The first, and the only one on which I have done any work on is that in which the ontology consists of heriditarily pure concrete categories and functors, all arrows being in fact functors.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Definitions of Pure Categories and Functors" tag="pcf-defns" doc="pcf-defns" />

<section title="Axioms for Pure Categories and Functors"
tag="pcf-axioms" doc="pcf-axioms" />

<section title="Definitions of Pure Abstract Categories and Functors" tag="pcf2-defns" doc="pcf-defns" />

</xldoc>
