<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: index.xml,v 1.1.1.1 2006-04-19 20:44:52 rbj01 Exp $"
       name="index"
	   title="OpenMind"
	   description="A formal analytic philosophy project underpinning and exploiting X-Logic."
	   keywords="x-logic xml logic philosophy analytic formal"
	   class="con"
       root="../"
       path="OpenMind/"
       up="../index.html"
	   rbjhome="http://www.rbjones.com/rbjpub/rbj.htm"
	   maintitle="mnt">

<maintitle><image name="om.gif" xtra="1234"/></maintitle>
<indextitle><image name="om.gif"/></indextitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Formal analytic philosophy using X-Logic, rationality and deduction, X-Logic foundations.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The Theory of Knowledge"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Foundations of Analytics"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
OpenMind applies formal methods and tools to analytic philosophical problems, explores the relationship between logic and rationality, and provides both applications of and foundations for X-Logic.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Formal Analytics">
Bertrand Russell, after his mammoth essay in the formalisation of mathematics, thought that the methods of logic could enable analytic philosophy to move on from indecisive sophistry to solid scientific (but not empirical) results.
It hasn't happened.
Here at OpenMind, that's what I intend to do.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Rationality">
David Hume appears in some of his writings to have supposed that beliefs are rational only when supported by demonstrative proof.
That this excludes all beliefs about the external world suggests that a better account of the relationship between rationality and deduction is desirable.
A more liberal account might suggest that a collection of belief's can rationally be held provided only that they are logically coherent (which is not a coherence theory of truth).
The concept of rationality is of central importance to The Open Society, and for that reason, eventually I hope to address this at OpenMind.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="X-Logic">
The X-Logic project may be thought of as a project to develop technological support for rationality.
Be that as it may, it certainly is intended to provide support for (inter alia) formal analytic philosophy, and <i>OpenMind</i> is intended to become a showcase for philosophical applications of X-Logic technologies.
However, the relationship between X-Logic and OpenMind is closer than that, for OpenMind is to provide philosophical and logical foundations for X-Logic.
This is an exercise in "analytic philosophy as design", in which the same work can be viewed either as the formalisation of philosophical theories about language and logic, or as an architectural design for the semantic web, eventually to be realised in software.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Theory of Knowledge" tag="ToK" doc="TheoryOfKnowledge"/>

<section title="Foundations of Analytics" tag="FoundAnaly" doc="foundAnaly"/>

</xldoc>

