<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x-logic.xml,v 1.1.1.1 2006-04-19 20:44:52 rbj01 Exp $"
       name="x-logic"
	   title="Philosophical Modelling for X-Logic"
	   description="An overview of philosophical work at OpenMind which contributes to the development of X-Logic"
	   keywords="philosophy analytic formal knowledge rationality x-logic foundations"
	   class="con"
       root="../"
       path="OpenMind/"
       up="TheoryOfKnowledge.html"
	   rbjhome="http://www.rbjones.com/rbjpub/rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Sound reasoning in the context of a "semantic web" problems must be solved which are essentially philosophical in character.
OpenMind here seeks to develop formal philosophical theories which will underpin the detailed design of X-Logic.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Metatheory for X-Logic"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Foundations for X-Logic"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Metatheory for X-Logic">
<abstract>
In order to be able to reason soundly in a multi-lingual environment we propose to develop formal models of language.
These models will then provide the semantic domains in terms of which we define the metanotation which we call XL-glue.
The purpose of XL-glue is to permit sound integrated multi-lingual solutions to problems, in which an overall result is synthesised from the results of a multiplicity of language or domain specific problem solvers.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Two Aspects of X-Logic">
There are two aspects of the X-Logic which get you into philosophy.
The basic idea is that you can work coherently in a multi-lingual environment if you know the meaning of all the languages which you are working with.
A formalist position doesn't really work, if you know the proof rules for each language that doesn't allow you to integrate them, but if you know the semantics of the languages, that does.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metatheory">
<p>
The first fundamental concern is with a metatheory which <i>justifies</i> this claim (that semantics does the trick), and which tells us how to integrate reasoning in different languages.
This is our present concern, with the use of formal modelling to provide such a metatheory.
It is also intended that this formal metatheory will lead us directly to a language which we can use to glue together solutions (or conclusions) from problems where subproblems (or lemmas) have been solved (or proven) in different languages (or logics).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Semantic Foundations for X-Logic">
<abstract>
Foundation systems are the semantic bedrock of X-Logic.
Though X-Logic is pluralistic even in foundation systems, OpenMind contributes a classical higher order set theory which is expected to be an adequate foundation for most work in X-Logic.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Initial Position">
OpenMind will initially do all X-Logic work in Galactic Set Theory.
This has been developed as an axiomatic set theory in ProofPower HOL, and is for present purposes well enough defined.
OpenMind is also engaged in broader foundational investigations which, were they to be fruitful might yield more radical foundational proposals for X-Logic.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Default Semantics">
A generic default semantics for XML documents in GST is anticipated in due course (though this might fall under X-Logic rather than OpenMind).
This would permit reasoning about XML documents used to represent data structures, and would permit semantics for more complex XML applications such as OpenMath to be rendered in set theory via the default semantics (which in these cases acts like an abstract syntax).
</subsec>
<subsec title="Later Work">
A story about infinite regress in formal semantics would be nice.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>

