<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: fm012.xml,v 1.2 2009/10/05 09:18:19 rbj Exp $"
       title="Carnap's Syntactical Method"
       created="1997/10/5"
       description="A description of Carnap's method of logical syntax."
       keywords="rbjones methods formal logic mathematics analytic philosophy"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="../../rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<xlink href="../../philos/bibliog/c.htm#Carnap">Rudolf Carnap</xlink>, a leading figure in the Vienna Circle, visited London in 1934 and gave three lectures at the University of London.
These lectures have since been published, most recently as a book
entitled "Philosophy and Logical Syntax" <i>[<bibref name="Carnap34"/>]</i>.
This book provides a concise overview of the methods being advocated by the Vienna Circle at that time.
I have made some <xref href="../../philos/bibliog/carnap34.htm">notes from the
  book</xref>, which provide an even more compact, if personal, rendition of
its content and I present here a distillation of the method, hyperlinked into
slightly more detailed notes.
Neither of these documents is intended to provide a critique, which I hope will eventually emerge in the course of relating more modern formal methods to some of their historical predecessors.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The Origins of The Syntactic Method"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title='Notes on The Method'/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Origins of The Syntactic Method">
<abstract>
Probably the three most important influences on the syntactic phase of Carnap's
analytic methodology were Russell, Hilbert and G&ouml;del.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Russell">
It was Russell's conception of philosophy as logic which seems to have been the
most significant influence on Carnap in developing his syntactic methods.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Hilbert">
It was probably the influence of Hilbert's formalism which accounts for this
method being specifically and exclusively syntactic.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Goedel">
The proximate inspiration, according to Carnap, for the syntactic method, was
the papers in which G&ouml;del presented his famous incompleteness results.
This was not in fact because of the results themselves, which can been seen as
proofs that a syntactic method could not suffice.
Carnap was inspired by the technique of arithmetisation of syntax employed in the proofs.
This demonstrated that it was possible to reason about languages without having
to adopt a metalanaguage distinct from the object language.
Admittedly the distinction related only to the syntax, but then Hilbert's
influence lead Carnap to believe that semantic concepts could be reduced to syntax.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title='Notes on The Method'>
<abstract>
The method is decribed in formal detail in "The Logical Syntax of Language"
[<bibref name="Carnap37" />], and less formally in "Philosophy and Logical
Syntax" [<bibref name="Carnap35" />]
</abstract>
<secbody title="Philosophy and Logical Syntax">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Rejection of Metaphysics" href="../../philos/bibliog/carnap34.htm#LecI">
The starting position for this method is the rejection of metaphysics (quoting <xlink href="../../philos/classics/hume/index.htm">Hume's <i>Enquiry</i></xlink> <xlink href="../../philos/classics/hume/echu123.htm">Section XIII part 3</xlink> <xlink href="../../philos/classics/hume/echu123.htm#para4">para 4</xlink>), assigning all matters of fact to empirical science and confining philosophy to logical analysis.
The <i>principle of verification</i>, that propositions with no verifiable consequences lack sense, is used against metaphysics, but this plays no major role in the syntactical method which follows, this being more concerned with establishing the status and logical structure of analytic and synthetic propositions.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Logical Syntax of Language" href="../../philos/bibliog/carnap34.htm#LecII">
In this lecture are defined those concepts in terms of which logical analysis is to be conducted.
These concepts are exclusively of a syntactic nature.
A language is defined by a set of <i><xlink href="../../philos/bibliog/carnap34.htm#SecII2">formation rules</xlink></i>, which define <i>sentences</i>, and <i><xlink href="../../philos/bibliog/carnap34.htm#SecII3">transformation rules</xlink></i>, which define <i>direct consequence</i>.
Properly philosophical (i.e. analytic) statements in "the material mode" have a misleading appearance of not being about syntax, and should be translated into "the formal mode" to reveal their true nature.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Syntax as The Method of Philosophy" href="../../philos/bibliog/carnap34.htm#LecIII">
Logical analysis first involves the translation of philosophical sentences expressed in the material mode into the formal mode.
Failing this the sentence must either be synthetic or metaphysical (and hence not properly a part of philosophy).
Translation accomplished, further syntactic analysis will tell us whether the sentence is analytic, contradictory or indeterminate.
By this means philosophy is rendered scientific in the sense intended by Russell.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="The Logical Syntax of Language">
<subsec>
<xlink href="../../philos/bibliog/carnap37.htm">contents list</xlink>.
</subsec>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
