<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: fm013.xml,v 1.1 2009/07/14 14:26:10 rbj Exp $"
       title="The Method of Formal Logical Analysis"
       created="1997/10/29"
       description="A description of a method of analysis employing formal logic."
       keywords="rbjones methods algebraic fm formal logic analysis"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="../../rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Deduction"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Abstract Models"/>
<secref title="Concepts"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Key features of the method, including:
<ul>
<li>applicable to any deductive reasoning</li>
<li>use of abstract models</li>
<li>use of formal notations and appropriate software</li>
</ul>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
The method is applicable whenever it is thought useful and possible to reason
deductively about some subject matter.
It offers ways in which this can be done more precisely and reliably than might
otherwise be possible.
This increase in precision and rigour often brings with it a clearer insight
into the subject matter, and enables results to be obtained which might
otherwise have proved illusive.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
The key elements of the method are:
<ul>
<li>Some ideas about when deductive reasoning is likely to be feasible.</li>
<li>An account of the conditions necessary for sound deductive reasoning.</li>
<li>The use of abstract models to make concepts precise.</li>
<li>The use of intuitions about abstract models to achieve greater
  understanding of the subject matter, and to discover specific results about them.</li>
<li>The use of formal notations and supporting computer software in the
  definition of abstract models and in proving results about those models.</li>
<li>Information about what the formal abstract models cannot deliver.</li>
<li>Ideas about how the formal methods fit in with informal methods.</li>
<li>An abstract conceptual framework in terms of which the method can be
  understood.</li>
<li>Some philosphy and some formal analysis underpinning the method, based on
  the abstract models associated with the conceptual framework.</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Deduction">
<abstract>
When deduction is possible, conditions for soundness.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
The method of formal logical analysis is intended for application wherever arguments are under consideration which are though to be, in part or in whole, deductive.
<p/>
A deductive argument is an <gloss name="APriori">a priori</gloss> argument in which some conclusion is shown to follow, as a matter of necessity, from some declared set of premises. That the conclusion follows from the premises will, in a sound deductive argument, be a consequence of the meanings of the premises and conclusions of the argument.
<p/>
A deductive argument may also be <gloss name="Formal">formal</gloss>, in which case formal rules will have been established for constructing arguments in the relevant notations.
<p/>
Once these rules have been shown to be sound with respect to the semantics of
the notations, checking the correctness of arguments is reduced to a mechanical
process.
</subsec>
<secref title=""/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
The premises from which the conclusions have been deduced represent our knowledge of the subject matter under consideration, and should be examined carefully to secure a proper understanding of the scope of applicability of the conclusions.
<p/>
Usually informal arguments fail to make clear what their premises are. This makes it difficult to check the soundness of the argument, and makes it difficult to determine in any particular circumstance whether the argument is applicable and its conclusion true.
<p/>
Formal analysis involves exposure of the premises of the argument so that their consistency can be established, so that the soundness of the argument can be checked and so that the scope of the conclusions is made clear.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Abstract Models">
<abstract>
The universality of abstract models.
Their advantages.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
The process of establishing the premises for a deductive argument can be beneficially thought of as defining or constructing an abstract model of the intended subject matter.
<p/>
This process, which may be thought of either as creative abstract modelling, or
as conceptual analysis, and which may extend to the development of new
notations, is the most creative and beneficial aspect of logical analysis. It
is the failure to give proper attention to this activity which is the most
damaging defect of wholly informal methods.
</subsec>
<secref title=""/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
Any deductive argument will proceed from some finite set of premises about its subject matter. These will normally be only a partial characterisation of the subject matter and will then be true of a wider range of systems. These system will be the models of an abstract theory which treats the essence of the concepts whose logic is exploited in the argument.
<p/>
In all areas of knowledge, advances are dependent on the development of new terminology, concepts, or notations. These permit expression of those finer distinctions upon which the advance of knowledge so often depends.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Concepts">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
The use of formality in logical analysis, which may be thought of primarily as permitting the detailed mechanical checking of deductive arguments, is in fact much more significant in enabling the meaning of new concepts and notations to be located more precisely than they can be by informal means.
<p/>
In the development of modern mathematics, Frege first devised notations
suitable for formal development of mathematics. The greater precision of these
notation made it possible for Russell to locate a defect in the reasoning which
they supported (now known as Russell's paradox). This in turn prompted further
developments in our understanding of the formal theory. In particular, they
resulted in the axiomatisation of well-founded set theories backed by the
semantic intuitions constituting <xlink href="../../logic/log014.htm">the iterative conception of set</xlink>
</subsec>
<secref title=""/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
Without the formal activities it is doubtful that we could have arrived at that clearer appreciation of the universe of well-founded sets which has been the basis for the development of mathematics in the 20th century. However, once the notion of set has been pinned down in this way (notwithstanding that there remains some looseness), the precision can be imported back into the less formal notations employed by working mathematicians.
<p/>
The central plank of the method of formal logical analysis is the use of
mathematical models to pin down the meaning of the concepts under
consideration. This brings semantics into the foreground and encourages
recognition that when we wish to use language precisely we must chose the
precise meanings of concepts rather suppose that precise meanings can be
distilled from precedent or can be done without.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
