<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id"
       title="Background for Metaphysical Positivism"
       created="2009-09-14"
       description="Many history of relevance to Logical Positivism"
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics history background"
       class="con"
       root="../../"
       up="../x001.html"
       path="rbjpub/philos"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Materials on the history of philosophy which provide context for an
understanding of Metaphysical Positivism.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Historical Introduction"/>
<secref title="Scepticism"/>
<secref title="Positivism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Three Dialectics"/>
<secref title="The Fundamental Triple-Dichotomy"/>
<subsec title="Philosophical Logicism" dir="logic" doc="003" suf="htm">
"Philosophical Logicism" is my conception of analytic philosophy before I
incorporated an element of positivism, and is largely incorporated in
Metaphysical Positivism.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Historical Introduction" tag="hi">
<abstract>
The proximate predecessor of metaphysical positivism is logical positivism.
Metaphysical positivism descends in direct line from Russell's embryonic conception of Logical Analysis, and the philosophy of Rudolf Carnap inspired by and intended to realise that conception.
</abstract>
<secbody title="Ancient Precursors">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Plato">
Plato's admiration for mathematics and his concept of Platonic forms as the
proper subject matter for philosophy and of all true knowledge, makes him a
distinguished advocate of deduction in philosophical analysis.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Aristotle">
A major part of Aristotle philosophy forms the collection of works known as
"The Organon", the function of which is to provide the basis for the
application of logic to the deductive sciences.
The Organon is therefore a first model for the kind of analytic method
articulated at the core of Metaphysical Positivism. 
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="Modern Predecessors">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="David Hume">
Though Hume predates the coining of the term, he is nevertheless often considered a positivist.
This is perhaps largely due to his skepticism, his conviction that philosophy should emulate the methods of empirical science which he admired in the work of Isaac Newton, and his robust condemnation of metaphysics.
Key elements of Hume's philosophy find their way down to metaphysical positivism.
Most notably the central position in Hume's philosophy of what we now call the analytic/synthetic dichotomy, and the further logical distinction between matters of logic or of fact and evaluative or ethical discourse.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Comte and Positive Science">
The term <i>positivism</i> derives from Comte's idea of <i>positive science</i>, science shorn of speculation and confined to what could be known.
Scientific theories for Comte should be no more than summaries or systematisations of the data of experience.
This phenomenalistic tendency is present in many positivist philosophies, right down to logical positivism, but is supplanted in <i>metaphysical positivism</i> with a more liberal pragmatism.
Closely associated is the rejection of metaphysics.
In metaphysical positivism there remains a skepticism about metaphysical problems but there is no outright rejection of metaphysics, and metaphysics is considered an important domain of investigation. 
<p />
Despite Comte's insistence on scientific rigour, his interests were not narrow.
He is better known as the founder of sociology than for his philosophy, and his vision was utopian.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Pragmatism">
Pragmatism is related to positivism, and there is an element of pragmatism in metaphysical positivism (falling short of a pragmatic definitions of meaning or truth).
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Russell and Logical Analysis">
<p>
Russell considered Frege's work and then his own work with A.N.Whitehead leading to Principia Mathematica, as the first examples of a new method of logical analysis whose scope extended beyond mathematics into the empirical sciences and which was also the correct method for philosophy.
Though an empiricist Russell is not himself usually considered a positivist, but his enthusiasm for logical analysis was taken up by Carnap and became the most distinctive new feature in the positivism of the Vienna Circle.
Methods for formal logical analysis, in any domain in which deductive reason is applicable, are at the core of metaphysical analysis.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Carnap's Logical Positivism">
<p>
Russell's vision of philosophy made scientific by the adoption of the method of logical analysis was the principle philosophical inspiration for the philosophical programme undertaken by Rudolf Carnap.
Carnap worked extensively on the development formal logical methods and their application to philosophy and science in the context of a positivistic philosophical culture. 
</p><p>
Carnap's philosophy may be thought of as a starting point for metaphysical positivism.
In fact Ayer's <a target="_top" href="bibliog/a.htm#Ayer36">Language Truth and Logic</a> was probably more influential (on metaphysical positivism), though Ayer was less concerned with the detail of formal methods and so a comparison with Carnap is more informative (for which, <a target="MainFrame" href="#AVLP">see below</a>).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Scepticism" tag="S" doc="x002" />
<section title="Positivism" tag="P" doc="x028" />
<section title="Three Dialectics" tag="TD" doc="x030" />
<section title="The Fundamental Triple-Dichotomy" tag="FTD" dir="epistem" doc="xep003" />

</xldoc>
