<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: s0912.xml,v 1.1 2009/12/16 21:55:38 rbj Exp $"
       created="2009/12/07"
       title="RBJones.com Monthly: December 2009"
       description="Discussion of changes in progress in my conception of Metaphysical Positivism"
       keywords="RbJ ChangeS WorK ProgresS Evolution Metaphysics Positivism Metaphysical"
       class="con"
       root="../../"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section>
<abstract>
My conception of Metaphysical Positivism has been developing continuously over the last few months culminating in a major transformation of its core, which was an account of a method of logical analyis, but is now intended to be more broadly and less dogmatically an analysis of methods of nomologico-deductive analysis.
Last month I attempted a description of the changes which were still in progress, and failed for that reason.
The aborted document was saved and this is a second attempt, at the same peril.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Latest Ideas for the Philosophy and the Books" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Latest Ideas for the Philosophy and the Books">
<abstract>
I have decided to soften the stance on the analytic method and on the underlying conceptual framework, from one of proposing a specific method and providing the necessary underlying metaphysics.
The prescriptive aspect of this is to be eliminated by the adoption of a comparative methodology.
Rather than proposing the method and it philosophical underpinnings, the idea is to provide a variety of objective comparisons of methods.
</abstract>

<secbody title="">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="An Issue Leading from and to Dogmatism">
<p>
First note that <i>Metaphysical Positivism</i> is supposed to be a sceptical philosophy, against dogma.
</p><p>
Second that it involves articulation of a method of analysis involving deduction, and depending on an ontological conceptual framework, a minimal metaphysic, the rationale for which has been undermined by philosophers since Carnap, notably by Quine and Kripke.
By Quine because his denial of the analytic/synthetic distinction is a denial of the objectivity of the distinction between deductive and other (less rigorous) kinds of reason.
By Kripke because his arguments reflect a redrawing of conceptual boundaries fundamental to metaphysical positivism.
</p><p>
The natural response to these difficulties from some of like mind with Carnap would be, in the first instance to clarify the relevant conception of analyticity in a manner which resists any sound criticism of Quine (which I am tempted to say was done by Carnap in the Schilpp volume), and to show how, once the analytic/synthetic, necessary/contingent and <i>a priori</i>/<i>a posteriori</i> distinctions are drawn appropriately that the conclusions of Kripke can be resisted.
</p><p>
Such an answer leads not to a refutation but to a proposal, linguistic (incorporating a minimal metaphysic) and methodological, which if adopted would re-instate the conceptual boundaries more or less as they were in Carnap, and which would be argued for on pragmatic grounds.
If the pragmatic arguments were accepted, this would probably lead to a re-construal of Kripkean metaphysics.
</p><p>
In looking at the details of the critique of Quine and Kripke which would have an important place in such a position, I found myself constantly at risk of slipping into derision, constantly reacting adversely to perceived dogmatic elements in their philosophy.
The idea of construing the response as a conceptual and methodological proposal is not shared by the positions to which this is presented as an alternative.
For it to be tenable, one must at least deny their claim to objectivity.
</p>

</subsec>
<subsec title="I">
<p>
I have recently decided on some significant changes to the main projects in progress on this site, which will take some time to effect.
The main thrust of these is:
<ul>
<li> firstly to make "metaphysical positivism" a more
purely analytic philosophical position.
This primarily involves the excision of prescriptive elements (which are typical of positivistic philosophy).
</li><li>
secondly, the broadening of the accompanying material on the historical origins from a history of philosophical logic embracing much metaphysics, to a history of philosophical analysis.
This change will permit a fuller account of the origins of the analytic method at the centre of metaphysical positivism, and make the whole thing into a more interesting story.
</li>
</ul>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="II">
<p>
I have now a broader conception of method, which will permit the analytic method to more fully describe both its application in the writing of these two books and its application in diverse other fields.
</p><p>
The "broader conception" involves the separation of the analysis more
thoroughly into two components, one concerned exclusively with
deduction and the construction of the contexts in which deduction can
rigorously be conducted (which we often call "models"), the other
with all other aspects of the analysis.
These are concerned with the relationship between the model and the
problem domain in which the model is intended to be applicable.
</p></subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="III">
<p>
This one is hot off the press, and I hope will prove the last change in my core conception of the "Metaphysical Positivism" project.
</p>
<p>
It is just a step further in the direction I was heading, a clearer and richer conception of how to go about the excision of dogma.
The idea is to make everything comparative.
Instead of a single proposed neutral metaphysic, for which a case is given, we consider many metaphysics and ways in which they can be compared.
Though the neutral metaphysic remains a preference, I seek the objective comparisons with other metaphysics which bring out the grounds for that preference.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="IV">
<p>
The next step is to go epistemological, thus changing the principle thrust of the work from methodology (meta-philosophy) to theoretical philosophy.
This involves incorporating some ideas which I have previously called "X-Logic" and broadening them into a fuller epistemological stance.
This is intended to provide a framework in which a whole variety of comparative assesments can be fitted, which will support a sharper understanding of some fundamental issues.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
