<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xmp001.xml,v 1.1 2009/08/05 06:47:11 rbj Exp $"
       title="Positive Metaphysics (II)"
       created="2005-11-30"
       description="A positivist tract on Metaphysics"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy metaphysics scepticism positivism"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
[This is a earlier version of ../x006.xml, saved pro-tem while radical changes
are under way to x006]
<p/>
An attempt to identify certain kinds of problem which might, even for a
positivist, be thought both metaphysical and worthwhile.
Primarily meta-philosophical, even meta-metaphysical.
</abstract>

<secbody title="">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Retrospective">
I begin with a historical sketch, describing first the dogmatic opposition to
metaphysics of the most extreme positivists, and then the evolution of Carnap's
thought from his phenomenalistic beginings to his liberal conclusion.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Prospective">
The I take one step forward beyond the liberal Carnap, and give an analysis of
positivistically acceptable varieties of metaphysics, and touch more generally
on aspects of Aristotle's "first philosophy" which might not now be called
metaphysics.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol title="Retrospective">
<secref title="Positivist Critiques of Metaphysics" />
<secref title="The Evolution of Carnap's Positivism" />
<secref title="Moderating Conventionalism" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol title="Prospective">
<subsec title="Kinds of Metaphysics" />
<secref title="Philosophical Language" />
<secref title="Analytic Metaphysics" />
<secref title="First Philosophy" />
<secref title="More Specific Notes" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


<section title="Positivist Critiques of Metaphysics" tag="PCM">
<abstract>
Hume's fork supports a rejection of metaphysics, and reappears with similar
effect in the philosophy of Rudolf Carnap.
A critique of the resulting conventionalist position makes a space for a
kind of metaphysics.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Introduction">
The approach adopted here is to start from the positivist rejection of
metaphysics through Hume's fork and its later presentation in the philosophy of
Carnap.
This leads to a conventionalist position, in which apparently metaphysical
claims are presented as logical consequences of choices about language.
A critique of radical conventionalism then make space in the positivist
framework for a new kind of metaphysics.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Hume's Fork" dir="../epistem" doc="xep004">
<p>
Hume's fork divides matters of objective truth into truths of reason and
matters of fact.
Hume says that only truths of reason are intuitively or demonstratively
certain, and that our conclusions about matters of fact are obtained by
non-rational and less reliable means.
Hume condemns metaphysics, by which he means any claim to objective truths
which do not comply with this classification both in the character of the
allegation and the method by which it is to be established.
</p><p>
Hume was inspired by Newton, and placed philosophy as concerned with matters of
fact, as an empirical (though not experimental) science of Human nature.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Metaphysics as Synthetic/A Priori">
The characterisation of metaphysics in terms of the analytic/synthetic
distinction is initiated by Kant in response to Hume, and becomes the dominant
simplistic conception of the issue between the Positivists and the Metaphysicians.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Hume's Phenomenalism">
<p>
Hume not only condemned those matters which might normally have been regarded
as metaphysical, but took a Platonic line on what we can know of the world of
the senses.
His conception of necessity was clearly one of logical necessity, and he first
argues that causal connections are not necessary.
On the further presumption that all our supposed knowledge of the external
world is based on the evidence of our senses, which is at best causally related
to the available (sensory) evidence, and the implicit demand that true
knowledge can only be had of things which follow necessarily from the evidence
he concludes that our knowledge of the external world is illusory, and our
tendency to belief is rooted in habitual disposition.
</p><p>
By systematic application of the demand, in effect for demonstrative proof,
Hume casts doubt on all knowledge except that of relations between ideas and of
sensory impressions.
Though he explains our beliefs as rooted in habit, he also effectively
re-interprets these beliefs by attempting to construe them in terms which do
not go beyond the available evidence.
</p><p>
This sets the pattern for a radical positivist conception of metaphysics as any
conclusion about the external world which goes beyond conclusions logically
entailed by the available evidence.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Going Beyond the Evidence">
<p>
Hume's phenomenalism presents his philosophy as a mitigated scepticism.
Hume grants a disposition to demonstrative knowledge, allowing by contrast with
previous empiricists that this category of <i>a priori</i> knowledge is
non-trivial and crucially includes mathematics.
</p><p>
However, the mitigation is confined to the <i>a priori</i>, in respect of
empirical knowledge a full-blooded pyrrhonism is applied, denying that we have
even probable knowledge of the external world.
</p><p>
This is characteristic of extreme positivism, in which scientists are expected
go further than the evidence strictly warrants, and in terms of which any such
speculation is regarded as metaphysical.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Metaphysics as Meaningless">
<p>
As positivists become more concerned with meaning, this provides an alternative
motivator for the identification and exclusion of metaphysics.
At first positivist conceptions of meaning are so closely coupled with the
relationship between a proposition and the evidence which would suffice to
verify it, that exclusion as meaningless is not clearly distinct from exclusion
as going beyond any possible evidence.
</p><p>
Later the coupling is weakened, and the requirement for claims or questions to
be meaningful becomes a more moderate demand than that of empirical verifiability.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Evolution of Carnap's Positivism" tag="CT">
<abstract>
Carnap's logical positivism matured into a position a hairs breath from
embracing metaphysics.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap's fork">
On the division of propositions Carnap's view is similar to Hume's though the
terminology has changed, there is considerably greater detail.
The characterisation of a the a priori as concerned with relations between
ideas (in Hume) becomes in the early Carnap, via ``semantic ascent'', their
characterisation as {\it about syntax} and in the later Carnap as tautological.  
<p>
In Carnap the notion of analyticity is made precise by a model of language
semantics as truth conditions and matches precisely the concept of logical
necessity understood as truth in all possible worlds.
</p><p>
Carnap was inspired by Russell, (and influenced by Frege and Wittgenstein), and
held that philosophy was analytic.
His attitude towards metaphysics was affected by his internal/external
distinction.
In these terms, the "fork" is a statement about "internal" questions,
i.e. questions put in some language with a well defined semantics.
Analyticity in such a language is determined by the semantics.
Questions about the legitimacy of the semantics are external questions, which Carnap
considered meaningless and believed should be settled pragmatically.
</p><p>
For some reason he does not seem to consider the external questions as having
meaning determined by the semantics of some meta-language.
</p><p>
Carnap's position is {\it conventionalist} then in this respect.
Insofar as true supposedly metaphysical propositions are necessary they must in
his conceptual scheme also be analytic.
Their truth therefore derives from the conventions which were adopted in
defining the semantics of the language, and these are not themselves
propositions but definitions.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Phenomenalism and Reductionism">
This aspect of anti-metaphysical positivism is stronger in the early than in
the later Carnap, where it is virtually extinguished by the ``principle of
tolerance''.
Carnap's was concerned with formalisation of the language of science, and he
began by attempting a phenomenalistic reduction consistent with a radical
nominalism.
However, he went on to consider {\it physicalistic} language and {\it
theoretical} language.
His principle of tolerance effectively admits any metaphysic to be incorporated
into the semantics of a language.
Once incorporated into a language in this way, the ``internal'' metaphysical
questions become analytic, and the ``external'' questions (which relate to the
legitimacy of such a semantics) can be dealt with on a purely pragmatic basis.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol><subsec title=""></subsec></sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Moderating Conventionalism" tag="SIC">
<abstract>
Why choices about language should not be completely arbitrary.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol><subsec title=""></subsec></sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Philosophical Language" tag="RL" doc="x008" dir=".."/>
<section title="Analytic Metaphysics" tag="M" doc="x009" dir=".."/>
<section title="First Philosophy" tag="FP" doc="x007" dir=".."/>

<section title="More Specific Notes" tag="MSN">
<abstract>
Some temporary notes about particular metaphysical problems of personal interest.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="abstract ontology">
<p>
Let us define for present purposes an abstract entity as one which is causally isolated from the material or sensory universe, our knowledge of which arises entirely by inference from the definitions of the entities. 
What can be said in this context about what abstract entities exist?
Well, working with Carnap's distinction between internal and external questions, there are very many internal questions which can be settled, and a lot of this is done in set theory.
On the "external" questions, e.g. granted that in the context of set theory we can prove the existence of various sets, but are the axioms of set theory correct descriptions of any part of reality, or is set theory entirely hypothetical?
</p><p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec></subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
