<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xps007.xml,v 1.1 2009/05/26 18:46:37 rbj Exp $"
       title="Carnap and Aristotle"
       created="2009/05/19"
       description="Why Carnap might take and interest in Aristotle's metaphysics"
       keywords="Carnap Aristotle metaphysics"
       up="xps000.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
A presentation of a conception of metaphysics written as if to explain to
Carnap why some useful purpose might be served by looking at Aristotle's Metaphysics.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
How to persuade Rudolf Carnap that Aristotle's metaphysics might be worth a look.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Background">
<p>
I am myself a positivist with a desire to make sense of metaphysics.
I think I am beginning to get some ideas together, but expressing these ideas
to a general (philosophical) audience is made more difficult because of the
prevalent antipathy to positivism, in consequence of which the aspects of
positivism which feature in my conception of metaphysics are likely to stop
people from ever coming to understand what I have to say about metaphysics.
</p><p>
It occurred to me that to explain my ideas to Carnap, in his terms, would be
easier, and would be a worthwhile place to start.
Here I attempt that task.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Plan of Action">
<ol>
<li>
First it is necessary to say something about the central features of positivism,
in Hume and in Carnap (inter alia), which are antagonistic to metaphysics.
This is basically Hume's fork.
</li>
<li>
Next we interpret this not as anihilating metaphysics, but as moving it, in
Carnap's terminology, from <i>internal</i> to <i>external</i> questions.
I will explain that.
</li>
<li>
Then we look closer at these external suggestions and suggest, intead of a
blanket prescription that they be dealt with pragmatically, suggest a
classification of manners of resolution, at one end of which is a class called
"objective metaphysics".
</li>
<li>
Then we consider the merits of these various ways of resolving external
questions, suggesting that there is some merit in addressing the metaphysics.
</li>
<li>
Finally, for the contemporary audience, there is some discussion of how this
stands up when some of Carnap's ideas (e.g. the internal/external distinction)
are questioned.
</li>
</ol>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Elimination of Metaphysics" tag="EM">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
