<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: inter016.xml,v 1.1 2009/09/03 15:04:02 rbj Exp $"
       title="Analytic Philosophy"
       created="1995/1/18"
       description="An account of Analytic Philosophy"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy analysis"
       class="con"
       up="index.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Origins"/>
<secref title="Historical Notes on Analyticity"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Varieties of Philosophical Analysis" doc="his003" dir="history" suf="htm">
Varieties of Philosophical Analysis in recent history are examined and
contrasted with the formal analysis framework.
</subsec>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Origins">
<abstract>
A few words about tbe origins of analytic philosophy.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
The term "Analytic Philosophy" was applied during the twentieth century to the dominant philosophical tradition in English speaking academia, and has been applied retrospectively to the philosophical tradition stretching back through millenia before it.
<p/>
There is more than one story about its origins.
Frege, Russell and Moore are often credited, one recent account centering around Russell may be found in <xlink href="bibliog/h.htm#Hylton92"><i>[Hylton92]</i></xlink>.
Dummet gives a completely different story, not claiming to be exhaustive, in his book on origins of analytic philosophy.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Developments Affecting Philosophy">
I have the impression that two quite different kinds of development in philosophy occurred at the beginning of this century.
<p/>
The first was a considerable advance in our understanding of logic, which makes it possible to settle conclusively most disputes about the validity of deductive arguments.
This coincides with the introduction of formal notations into logic, and therefore with a partial separation of logic from the language of ordinary discourse.
<p/>
The second was an important change of attitude toward language.
The hitherto widespread (if covert) practice of inferring prescriptions about usage in the course of philosophical deliberation was deprecated.
It was displaced by the view that language is a settled institution, facts about which are part of the tools of a philosopher, and which can and should be used to refute any philosophical theory which cannot be adequately expressed without some nicer distinction than can be put without linguistic innovation.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Their Effects">
The opportunities presented by developments in our understanding of logic contributed to logical atomism and were consistent with logical positivism, but have been largely cast aside by the wave of philosophy which has remained firmly embedded in natural languages, largely untouched by formal technique, and oblivious to fatal defects in its methods.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Historical Notes on Analyticity" doc="rbj010" dir="epistem" suf="htm"/>

</xldoc>
