<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x001.xml,v 1.16 2009/09/16 09:46:50 rbj Exp $"
       title="More on Metaphysical Positivism"
       created="2004/3/10"
       description="Supplementary page for metaphysical positivism."
       keywords="rbjones philosophy metaphysics positivism"
       up="../x001.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Metaphysical Positivism is a positivistic philosophical system formulated for the twenty first century, building on a heritage going back at least as far as David Hume; cognisant of developments in logic and computer science which have taken place in the 20th Century, but turning away from some of the recent tendencies in analytic philosophy.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Pictures of Reality"/>
<secref title="Positive Science"/>
<secref title="Logical Analysis"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Abstract Semantics"/>
<secref title="Reasoning about Society"/>
<secref title="Metaphysical and Logical Positivism Compared"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Pictures of Reality" tag="PR">
<abstract>
In his "picture theory" Wittgenstein suggested that the relation between language and fact was similar to that between a picture and the thing portrayed.
In metaphysical positivism language is construed as providing models of the world, the "true structure" of which is inaccessible to scientific method.
Insofar as it is possible to go beyond the exhibition and evaluation of (mathematical) models with enquiries into the true structure of the universe this is the domain of metaphysics.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Logical Analysis" tag="LA">
<abstract>
Logical analysis is the analytic part of positive science and scientific philosophy.
It consists of methods for maximising the rigour of reasoning using abstract models of the domain of discourse.
The logical aspects are thereby rendered as rigorous and reliable as mathematics, and other aspects are exposed for other kinds of scrutiny.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Slogan">
<p>
The slogan of logical analysis is <i>sets and sugar suffice</i>.
"For what, and how?" you may ask.
But before that, "what on earth does he mean?".
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Meaning?">
What this slogan means it that the ontology of sets, the language of set theory, and the formal deductive system it comes with, made more readable by what computer scientists call <i>syntactic sugar</i>, i.e. just nicer ways of writing down things which could have been said in the primitive language of set theory, suffice for rigorous science and philosophy.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="For What?">
<p>
Well, for the kind of idealised model of how science might be which is typical of a positivistic philosophical system.
Alternatively, for the foundations of abstract semantics, and hence for defining analyticity, the notion of sound deduction, for underpinning the a priori sciences, via the nomologico-deductive model for the deductive aspects of empirical sciences and for the deductively sound aspects of analytic philosophy, including abstract ontology and such metaphysics as a positivist may be prepared to comprehend.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="How?">
<p>
How, is a longer story, but there is a short version.
</p>
<p>
The short version is: "by abstract modelling".
The underlying insight is that, whatever your subject matter, its structure can be replicated in an abstract domain.
You can do this either by choosing an appropriate language for talking about your subject and giving that language an abstract semantics in set theory, or alternatively just using set theory itself (sugared probably) to construct an abstract model.
Set theory then provides a foundation for reasoning rigorously about your subject.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Abstract Semantics" tag="AS">
<abstract>
An <i>abstract semantics</i> is a (not necessarily complete) account of the meaning of some language in terms of abstract entities.
If the intended subject matter of a language is concrete, its semantics can be factored into abstract and concrete parts.
The abstract part suffices to determine the relation of semantic entailment, which in turn settles the question of which inferences are deductively sound.
Abstract semantics can be defined with much greater precision than concrete semantics, but cannot be made absolutely unambiguous.
When we strive for limits in semantic precision, foundational problems come to the fore.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Positive Science" tag="PS">
<abstract>
Positive science, a term coined by Auguste Comte which gave rise to the notion of positivism, is revived in metaphysical positivism as an idealised model of scientific method, broad enough to encompass what Russell talked of as "scientific philosophy".
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Reasoning about Society" tag="RAS">
<abstract>
The reducibility of rationality to abstract analysis receives its greatest test when the domain of discourse moves from the hard to the social sciences, from descriptive to evaluative, when economic, political and ethical considerations are at stake.
Can we then expect rigour?
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Metaphysical and Logical Positivism Compared" tag="AVLP" doc="x003" />

</xldoc>



