<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x003.xml,v 1.2 2004/04/26 15:38:04 rbj Exp $"
       name="x003"
       title="Analytic and Logical Positivism Compared"
       created="2004-3-15"
       description="A desciption of how analytic positivism differs from logical positivism"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy analytic logical positivism"
       class="con"
       root="../../"
       up="x001.html"
       path="rbjpub/philos"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Analytic Positivism is described by comparison with Logical Positivism, with particular reference to the philosophy of Rudolf Carnap.
In this we follow Carnap's own account of his philosophy as given in the Carnap volume of the library of living philosophers, using his own headings.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Pseudo Problems in Philosophy"/>
<secref title="The Foundations of Mathematics"/>
<secref title="Physicalism and the Unity of Science"/>
<secref title="The Logical Syntax of Language"/>
<secref title="Liberalisation of Empiricism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Semantics"/>
<secref title="Language Planning"/>
<secref title="Probablility and Inductive Logic"/>
<secref title="The Theoretical Language"/>
<secref title="Values and Practical Decisions"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Pseudo Problems in Philosophy">
<abstract>
Though the verification principle is not adopted by analytic positivism, the avoidance of nonsense of various kinds remains a central concern, and the methods of analytic positivism are intended to permit rigorous analysis and to avoid nonsense and sophistry (witting or not).
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Logical Positivism">
<p>
Logical positivism divides indicative sentences into three kinds.
Analytic sentences, which are supposed to be demonstrable, empirical facts, which must be verifiable, and the rest, which are nonsense.
Metaphysics is singled out for obloquy, where metaphysics is construed as a priori claims about the nature of reality (or the synthetic a priori), or as statements which are neither analytic nor verifiable (and hence meaningless).
</p><p>
In Carnap's philosophy through its various stages there are several different attitudes toward metaphysics.
In his earlier years he simply regarded metaphysics as <i>useless</i>, in the early years of logical positivism he regarded metaphysics as <i>meaningless</i>, adopting the verificationist view that the meaning of a proposition is its method of verification.
Later he adopted a more liberal view on meaning, and expressed the status of metaphysics as <i>lacking cognitive content</i>.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Analytic Positivism">
<p>
While recognising the same three categories of indicative sentence, the distinction between sense and nonsense is made by different means.
Sufficient meaning to support reasoning in a language may be provided by an <i>abstract semantics</i> (for the language under consideration), which will support the demonstration of analytic truths (though formal derivability is likely to be incomplete).
Concrete semantics presents greater difficulties, and for science a (nomologico-deductive) <i>modelling</i> methodology is advocated, in which considerations of <i>truth</i> are supplanted by those of utility.
</p>
<p>
Metaphysics has no special status in this scheme, though in the terminology of analytic positivism there are no synthetic a priori truths, and contratry to modern metaphysicians there is no necessity <i>de re</i>.
Necessity <i>de re</i> is a product of equivocation about semantics.
A statement is necessary <i>de re</i> if it is necessary by not analytic.
However, this cannot be the case, since a correct semantics for a language must fully capture the truth conditions for the sentences of the language, and if a sentence is true in any possible world then this <i>must</i> be entailed by a full semantics.
Of course, it need not be entailed by an incomplete semantics.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Foundations of Mathematics">
<abstract>
Analytic positivism has nothing very specific to the foundations of mathematics to add to the broad outlines of Carnap's philosophy in this matter.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap's Views">
<p>
Carnap's logicism derived initially and primarily from Frege, though he also studied Principia Mathematica, preferring its notation and building on its theory of relations. He accepted Frege's view that mathematics is analytic (and also the mathematical study of geometry), and seemed to regard this as providing an important new way for empiricists to give a satisfactory account of mathematics (pace Hume). Carnap recognised the difficulty in showing that the axioms of Principia were logical. He preferred to argue that the axiom of infinity is indeed analytic (via a suitable interpretation) but if that failed he would regard mathematical truths as conditional (and hence still analytic) rather than synthetic (and hence empirical, in default of pure intuition).</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Analytic Positivism">
<p>
Though holding that mathematical truths are analytic, in analytic positivism <i>analytic</i> means something like "true in virtue of meaning" (though a more detailed analysis of this is sought), whereas Frege's conception of analyticity seemed more to do with derivability than semantics.
(this is perhaps more like Ayer's than Carnap's account of analyticity)
This lessens the difficulties arising from ontological axioms, but nevertheless abstract ontology is an important topic for further investigation. 
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Physicalism and the Unity of Science">
<abstract>
Little of these aspects of logical positivism survives in analytic positivism.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap's Positions">
<p>
Carnap (at various times) advocated and worked on the presentation of science in both physical and phenomenalostic terms (the latter primarily for philosophical purposes, i.e. as a exercise in epistemology) and believed that "the total language covering all science can be constructed on a physicalistic basis".
This extended to there being some kind of reducibility of psychological language into "physicalistic" language.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Analytic Positivism">
<p>
It is for analytic positivism an interesting question in what sense if any a physicists "theory of everything" provides a basis to which all of science can be reduced.
However, analytic positivism advocates a pragmatic attitude to the adoption and application of scientific theories, and expects that reductionism will remain of limited pragmatic value.
Analytic positivism has no problem with theories modelling aspects of reality using non-physical entities, and is skeptical about the pragmatic value of attempts at physicalistic reduction of mental concepts or events.
</p>
<p>
For analytic positivism the best level at which to seek a sense of the unity of science is at the logical level.
All scientific theories which can be used deductively (as in the deductive-nomological model) can be formulated as abstract models in set theory, or in many other formal or mathematical languages of similar strength.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Logical Syntax of Language">
<abstract>
This early cental feature of Carnap's philosophy was later significantly changed by Carnap's shift to semantics.
The emphasis on semantics is retained in analytic positivism and much detail is changed.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Syntax Suffices">
<p>
Like Hilbert, Carnap in his early years thought formal syntax could completely replace informal semantic notions.
Goedel's incompleteness results show that this is not the case and Carnap later gave considerable attention to semantics.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Liberalisation of Empiricism">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Semantics">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Language Planning">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Probablility and Inductive Logic">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Theoretical Language">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Values and Practical Decisions">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
