<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x003.xml,v 1.5 2006/03/25 22:50:36 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Metaphysical and Logical Positivism Compared"
       created="2004-3-15"
       description="A desciption of how metaphysical positivism differs from logical positivism"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy analysis metaphysics logic positivism"
       up="x001.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Metaphysical Positivism is described by comparison with Logical Positivism, with particular reference to the philosophy of Rudolf Carnap.
In this we follow Carnap's own account of his philosophy as given in the Carnap volume of the library of living philosophers, using his own headings.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The philosophy of Rudolf Carnap" href="../philos/history/rcp000.htm">
You may find it helpful to refer to my other account of Carnap's philosophy which this comparison parallels.
</subsec>
<secref title="Pseudo Problems in Philosophy"/>
<secref title="The Foundations of Mathematics"/>
<secref title="Physicalism and the Unity of Science"/>
<secref title="The Logical Syntax of Language"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Semantics"/>
<secref title="Language Planning"/>
<secref title="Probability and Inductive Logic"/>
<secref title="The Theoretical Language"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Pseudo Problems in Philosophy">
<abstract>
Though the verification principle is not adopted by metaphysical positivism, the avoidance of nonsense of various kinds remains a central concern, and the methods of metaphysical positivism are intended to permit rigorous analysis and to avoid nonsense and sophistry (witting or not).
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Logical Positivism">
<p>
Logical positivism divides indicative sentences into three kinds.
Analytic sentences, which are supposed to be demonstrable, empirical facts, which must be verifiable, and the rest, which are nonsense.
Metaphysics is singled out for obloquy, where metaphysics is construed as a priori claims about the nature of reality (or the synthetic a priori), or as statements which are neither analytic nor verifiable (and hence meaningless).
</p><p>
In Carnap's philosophy through its various stages there are several different attitudes toward metaphysics.
In his earlier years he simply regarded metaphysics as <i>useless</i>, in the early years of logical positivism he regarded metaphysics as <i>meaningless</i>, adopting the verificationist view that the meaning of a proposition is its method of verification.
Later he adopted a more liberal view on meaning, and expressed the status of metaphysics as <i>lacking cognitive content</i>.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
While recognising the same three categories of indicative sentence, the distinction between sense and nonsense is made by different means.
Sufficient meaning to support reasoning in a language may be provided by an <i>abstract semantics</i> (for the language under consideration), which will support the demonstration of analytic truths (though formal derivability is likely to be incomplete).
Concrete semantics presents greater difficulties, and for science a (nomologico-deductive) <i>modelling</i> methodology is advocated, in which considerations of <i>truth</i> are supplanted by those of utility.
</p>
<p>
Metaphysics has no special status in this scheme, though in the terminology of metaphysical positivism there are no synthetic a priori truths, and contratry to modern metaphysicians there is no necessity <i>de re</i>.
Necessity <i>de re</i> is a product of equivocation about semantics.
A statement is necessary <i>de re</i> if it is necessary but not analytic.
However, this cannot be the case, since a correct semantics for a language must fully capture the truth conditions for the sentences of the language, and if a sentence is true in any possible world then this <i>must</i> be entailed by a full semantics.
Of course, it need not be entailed by an incomplete semantics.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Foundations of Mathematics">
<abstract>
Metaphysical positivism has nothing very specific to the foundations of mathematics to add to the broad outlines of Carnap's philosophy in this matter.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap's Views">
<p>
Carnap's logicism derived initially and primarily from Frege, though he also studied Principia Mathematica, preferring its notation and building on its theory of relations. He accepted Frege's view that mathematics is analytic (and also the mathematical study of geometry), and seemed to regard this as providing an important new way for empiricists to give a satisfactory account of mathematics (pace Hume). Carnap recognised the difficulty in showing that the axioms of Principia were logical. He preferred to argue that the axiom of infinity is indeed analytic (via a suitable interpretation) but if that failed he would regard mathematical truths as conditional (and hence still analytic) rather than synthetic (and hence empirical, in default of pure intuition).</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
Though holding that mathematical truths are analytic, in metaphysical positivism <i>analytic</i> means something like "true in virtue of meaning" (though a more detailed analysis of this is sought), whereas Frege's conception of analyticity seemed more to do with derivability than semantics.
(this is perhaps more like Ayer's than Carnap's account of analyticity)
This lessens the difficulties arising from ontological axioms, but nevertheless abstract ontology is an important topic for further investigation. 
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Physicalism and the Unity of Science">
<abstract>
Metaphysical positivism sits on a fence here, recognising that there is something interesting to be said in this area, but not going as far as Carnap appears to do.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap's Positions">
<p>
Carnap (at various times) advocated and worked on the formal presentation of science in three different ways.
They were (I think in the order he considered them):
<ul>
<li>pheomenalistic</li>
<li>physicalistic</li>
<li>theoretical</li>
</ul>
</p><p>
The first was for purely philosophical purposes and was associated with the foundationalist principle that all our knowledge of the world is derived from sense data.
The second served a different philosophical purpose, and is the language which is relevant to Carnap's view on the unity of science.
The third is the least philosophical and the closest to a formalisation for purely scientific purposes using the concepts of the scientist.
</p><p>
The unity of science principle was a reaction against a view popular in Germany at that time that sciences consisted of two kinds, the natural sciences and the spiritual sciences (covering the social sciences and the humanities).
The unity of science movement was connected with physicalism through the thesis that "the total language covering all science can be constructed on a physicalistic basis".
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
It is for me an interesting question in what sense if any a physicists "theory of everything" provides a basis to which all of science can be reduced.
I am sympathetic to the idea that there could be a <i>complete</i> abstract model of the universe broadly along the lines sought by fundamental physics.
</p><p>
However, I advocate a pragmatic attitude to the adoption and application of scientific concepts and theories, and expect that reductionism will remain of limited pragmatic value in many domains.
I have no problem with theories modelling aspects of reality using non-physical entities, and am skeptical about the pragmatic value of attempts at physicalistic reduction of mental concepts or events.
</p>
<p>
I believe that the best level at which to seek a sense of the unity of science is at the logical level.
All scientific theories which can be used deductively (as in the "nomologico-deductive" method) can be formulated as abstract models in set theory, or in many other formal or mathematical languages of similar strength.
It might be better to talk of "the language of mathematics" as the base for science rather than "set theory", though set theory might be said to admit models which are not actually mathematical (whatever that means).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Logical Syntax of Language">
<abstract>
This early central feature of Carnap's philosophy was later significantly changed by Carnap's shift to semantics.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap">
<p>
Possibly following Hilbert, Carnap in his early years thought formal syntax could completely replace informal semantic notions.
Goedel's incompleteness results show that this is not the case and Carnap later gave considerable attention to semantics.
</p>
<p>
What Carnap spoke of under the heading "Philosophy and Logical Syntax" was however much broader in its scope than Hilbert's idea that formal axioms suffice for semantics.
Carnap sought to adapt Russell's analytic method, applied by Russell to the derivation of mathematics, for use in the empirical sciences, but he also added, following Hilbert, a metatheoretic dimension which is absent from Russell's work.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
Metaphysical positivism starts rather than ends with a concern for semantics.
The hinterland of logical truth beyond the limits of accepted axiom systems is of particular interest, and as a study in abstract ontology is one of the elements of "metaphysics" of interest to metaphysical positivism.
Metaphysical positivism continues the concern with methods for application of formal logical analysis wherever deductive conclusions are sought.
</p>
<p>
Metaphysical positivism is conceived in a world of digital electronics.
Digital information processing has a radical effect upon methods of formal analysis.
It takes away an increasing part of the drudgery of detailed formal derivation, and in that way makes the application of formal techniques (rather than their metatheory) more tractable.
At the same time these technologies continually transform the ways in which those we now call "knowledge workers" work, and promise that hitherto exclusively human activities (knowing and reasoning) may in the future be done by wholly inhuman entities using radically novel methods.
</p>
<p>
To be relevant to the future, analytic method must now anticipate advances in software capabilities the nature of which is itself a matter of speculation.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Semantics">
<abstract>
Metaphysical positivism is inclined to regard Carnap's semantic methods as of purely historical interest.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap">
<p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
A separation is argued between <i>abstract semantics</i> and <i>concrete semantics</i>.
The former can be realised formally in set theory or some comparable foundation system, and suffices the establish the relation of entailment and the property of analyticity or logical truth.
The latter concerns the connection between the abstract entities in the abstract semantics and any concrete entities in the real world with which they may be intended to correspond.
It is neither so easy, nor so important, from the point of view of formal analysis, to get the concrete semantics done with formal precision.
The concrete semantics has no impact on the conclusions which can be drawn from the formal analysis, but does determine whether and how the analysis is relevant to any real world problem.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Language Planning">
<abstract>
Carnap was a linguistic pluralist, advocating not a single language for science but the use of languages appropriate to the domain under consideration.
This gives rise to particular difficulties when one has an application involving several branches of science formaulated in different languages.
This was the problem which he addressed in "Language Planning".
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap">
<p>
I don't know anything about Carnap's work in this area.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
Metaphysical Positivism is also pluralistic (as well as foundationalist).
The simplest solution to the language planning problem is to adopt a semantic foundation system and develop suitable tools which support reasoning in the language of that system or in other languages via sematnic embedding into the foundational language.
</p>
<p>
The other solution comes with a complex of ideas connected with XML called <i>X-Logic</i>.
This is along the same lines but oriented to fit with the standards for multilingual markup on the internet.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Probability and Inductive Logic">
<abstract>
There's a pretty large gulf here.
Metaphysical positivism gives no credit to the idea of inductive inference, and is skeptical about the value of confirmation theory. 
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap">
<p>
I'll have to pass on describing Carnap's position here.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
Doubts the utility of "inductive logic" or confirmation theory.
Instead it considers scientific theories as providing models of aspects of the world which need not be considered "true" or "false".
Even models which are known to be imperfect (and hence presumably if true or false must be false) can be very useful, and probably most accepted scientific theories are known to be only approximations.
</p>
<p>
It therefore seems to me more rational to compile useful data about the scope of applicability, and the reliability and precision in its various applications of a scientific theory or model, rather than attempting to quantify confidence in its truth.
What confidence can we have in the truth of Newton's laws of motion or Boyle's law?
We know presumably that they and many other useful scientific laws are in fact false.
If we are to give a useful comment about these theories it must surely be to provide some inforamtion which will help to determine when they are adequate approximations for some practical application.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Theoretical Language">
<abstract>
This approach of Carnap's to the formalisation of science is the one with which metaphysical positivism has greatest sympathy.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap">
<p>
If I recall correctly the theoretical language, by contrast with phenomenal or physicalistic language is the one which is closest to dealing with science through the concepts used by physicists.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metphysical Positivism">
Insofar as we speak of the use of formal methods for scientific rather than philsoophical purposes then the starting point should be the formalisation of the theoretical language used by science.
Formalisation would expose scientific theory to a microscope and would demand greater care for consistency (e.g. it would be a bit picky about how to handle theories like relativity which break down under certain circumstances).
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
