<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x006.xml,v 1.5 2009/05/26 18:46:37 rbj Exp $"
       title="Positive Metaphysics"
       created="2005-11-30"
       description="A positivist tract on Metaphysics"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy metaphysics scepticism positivism"
       up="../x001.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
An attempt to identify certain kinds of problem which might, even for a
positivist, be thought both metaphysical and worthwhile.
Primarily meta-philosophical, even meta-metaphysical.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction" />
<secref title="First Philosophy" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Philosophical Language" />
<secref title="Analytic Metaphysics" />
<secref title="More Specific Notes" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Hume's fork supports a rejection of metaphysics, and reappears with similar
effect in the philosophy of Rudolf Carnap.
A critique of the resulting conventionalist position makes a new place for a
kind of metaphysics.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Introduction">
The approach adopted here is to start from the positivist rejection of
metaphysics through Hume's fork and its later presentation in the philosophy of
Carnap.
This leads to a conventionalist position, in which apparently metaphysical
claims are presented as logical consequences of choices about language.
A critique of radical conventionalism then make space in the positivist
framework for a new kind of metaphysics.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Hume's Fork" dir="epistem" doc="xep004">
<p>
Hume's fork divides matters of objective truth into truths of reason and
matters of fact.
Hume says that only truths of reason are intuitively or demonstratively
certain, and that our conclusions about matters of fact are obtained by
non-rational and less reliable means.
Hume condemns metaphysics, by which he means any claim to objective truths
which do not comply with this classification both in the character of the
allegation and the method by which it is to be established.
</p><p>
Hume was inspired by Newton, and placed philosophy as concerned with matters of
fact, as an empirical (though not experimental) science of Human nature.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Carnap's fork">
Carnaps view is similar.
<p>
It benefits from new terminology arising first with Kant, then with the advent
of modern logic and the development of formal semantics.
In Carnap the notion of analyticity is made precise by a model of language
semantics as truth conditions and matches precisely the concept of logical
necessity understood as truth in all possible worlds.
</p><p>
Carnap was inspired by Russell, (and influenced by Frege and Wittgenstein), and
held that philosophy was analtyic.
His attitude towards metaphysics was affected by his internal/external
distinction.
In these terms, the "fork" is a statement about "internal" questions,
i.e. questions put in some language with a well defined semantics.
Analyticity in such a language is determined by the semantics, and questions
about the legitimacy of the semantics were external questions, which Carnap
considered meaningless and believed should be settled pragmatically.
</p><p>
For some reason he does not seem to consider the external questions as having
meaning determined by the semantics of some meta-language.
</p><p>
Carnap's position is conventionalist then in this important respect.
Insofar as true supposedly metaphysical propositions are necessary they must in
his conceptual scheme also be analytic.
Their truth therefore derives from the conventions which were adopted in
defining the semantics of the language, and these are not themselves
propositions but definitions. 
</p>
</subsec>

</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="First Philosophy" tag="FP" doc="x007" />
<section title="Philosophical Language" tag="RL" doc="x008" />
<section title="Analytic Metaphysics" tag="M" doc="x009" />

<section title="More Specific Notes" tag="MSN">
<abstract>
Some temporary notes about particular metaphysical problems of personal interest.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="abstract ontology">
<p>
Let us define for present purposes an abstract entity as one which is causally isolated from the material or sensory universe, our knowledge of which arises entirely by inference from the definitions of the entities. 
What can be said in this context about what abstract entities exist?
Well, working with Carnap's distinction between internal and external questions, there are very many internal questions which can be settled, and a lot of this is done in set theory.
On the "external" questions, e.g. granted that in the context of set theory we can prove the existence of various sets, but are the axioms of set theory correct descriptions of any part of reality, or is set theory entirely hypothetical?
</p><p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec></subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
