<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x006.xml,v 1.2 2006/09/11 10:11:46 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Positive Metaphysics"
       created="2005-11-30"
       description="A positivist tract on Metaphysics"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy metaphysics scepticism positivism"
       up="../x001.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
A philosophical tract arising from the retrenchement of <i>Metaphysical Positivism</i> from a philosophical <i>position</i> aspiring to be a <i>system</i> and a <i>programmme</i> to being, more modestly, the description of certain philosophical problems.
This kind of regression is of course, for a sceptical philosophy, its best approximation to triumphal progress.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction" />
<secref title="First Philosophy" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Philosophical Language" />
<secref title="Metaphysics" />
<secref title="More Specific Notes" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
In which is explained the purpose and structure of this work.
This consists in taking a philosophical <i>position</i> and some <i>problems</i> which flow from it and then recasting these problems.
The aim is to do this as clearly possible while replacing, wherever possible, philosophical presumptions with choice of appropriate language for the formulation of the problems.
The role of the position then becomes motivational rather than substantive.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Purpose">
It is my purpose here simply to identify some problems which seem to me to be of philosophical interest
That I can now exalt in such a purpose is symptomatic of the advance of my own personal scepticism.
Previously I have sought to articulate some elementary philosophical principles as a prelude to the articulation of ideas which belong properly to <i>engineering</i> rather than philosophy.
The perceived need for such an articulation lead swifly to an acute and debilitating awareness that these principles which seemed to me elementary, were regarded by many or most contemporary philosophers as false.
<p />
A significant element of the position here considered is Popper stance in the poker debate.
By this I mean the philosophical issue at stake between Popper and Wittgenstein on the occasion of Popper's speaking at the Moral Sciences Club in Cambridge.
The invitation to Popper invited him to speak upon some "Philosophical Riddle" and Popper chose to attach the presumption apparent in this form of invitation that philosophy is not concerned with substantive problems.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Structure">
The <i>philosophical position</i> which I occupy, seems to me, rather than a collection of substantive disagreements on matters of (philosophical) fact, is accounted for primarily by a divergent philosophical interests and related idiomatic preferences.
My disagreement with other philosophers on the truth of various statements is often the child of conflicting usage.
<p />
Because of this a bald statement of position has sometimes seemed to me more appropriate than a confrontation on points of controversy.
<p />
As I have become more aware of my own limitations in progressing the kinds of philosophical problem which I find most interesting, the mere formulation of problems has come to seem by itself worthwhile and interesting.
The focus simply on the statement of problems reinforces my perception that my position consists in large parts of interests, languages and methods rather than of doctrine.
The structure of this work is therefore oriented toward making explicit the extent to which my philosophical world view consists in choice of language and methods appropriate for certain problems of interest.
<p />
The first part of the work is simply a position statement, but its role is auxiliary.
The next part attempts to recast as much as possible of that position as mere choice of language, appropriate for the formulation of the oroblems which appears in the final part.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="First Philosophy" tag="FP" doc="x007" />
<section title="Philosophical Language" tag="RL" doc="x008" />
<section title="Metaphysics" tag="M" doc="x009" />

<section title="More Specific Notes" tag="MSN">
<abstract>
Some temporary notes about particular metaphysical problems of personal interest.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<subsec title="abstract ontology">
<p>
Let us define for present purposes an abstract entity as one which is causally isolated from the material or sensory universe, our knowledge of which arises entirely by inference from the definitions of the entities. 
What can be said in this context about what abstract entities exist?
Well, working with Carnap's distinction between internal and external questions, there are very many internal questions which can be settled, and a lot of this is done in set theory.
On the "external" questions, e.g. granted that in the context of set theory we can prove the existence of various sets, but are the axioms of set theory correct descriptions of any part of reality, or is set theory entirely hypothetical?
</p><p>
</p>
</subsec>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
