<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x008.xml,v 1.2 2008/04/05 08:25:14 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Philosophical Language"
       created="2005-11-30"
       description="Metaphysical positivism as idiom."
       keywords="rbjones philosophy metaphysics language"
       class="con"
       up="x006.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
The re-presentation of metaphyisical positivism, insofar as this can be done, as a choice of idiom rather than as a body of doctrine, preliminary to the use of that language for the statement of various problems.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec></subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
The description of language suitable for definite statement of certain metaphysical problems, transforming relevant aspects of <i>metaphysical positivism</i> from a <i>position statement</i> to a <i>choice of language</i>.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="A Problem of Regress">
There is of course a problem in the idea of clearly defining a language in which problems of metaphysics can be stated.
An attempt to give meaning to such language must surely involve metaphysical presumptions, and the intent to to proceed to problem statement without prejudice must fail.
This accepted the question becomes how small a core of <i>position</i> will suffice to render the rest of metaphysics objective and definite.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Response to the Problem">
The method proposed is therefore to begin with a <i>position</i> on how the semantics of a language may be defined.
The metaphysical content in this position can later be examined to consider whether it can be eliminated in favour of some weaker metaphysical core, or whether variation in this core might expose interesting metaphysical problems not obtainable from the original.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
