<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x012.xml,v 1.4 2007/02/20 22:14:05 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Open Scepticism"
       created="2006-03-04"
       description="A discussion of the theoretical side of scepticism."
       keywords="philosophy scepticism speculation"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
<i>Open scepticism</i> is a kind of <i>theoretical</i> scepticism, an <i>anti-dogmatic</i> philosophy in respect of knowledge, which enjoins suspension of judgement in all matters, accepting only that things <i>appear to be</i> as they do.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Historical Notes on Scepticism" >
</secref>
<secref title="Some Kinds of Scepticism and Speculation" />
<secref title="Elements of Open Scepticism" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Benefits of Scepticism and Dogmatism" />
<secref title="Provocation to Doubt" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Historical Notes on Scepticism" doc="xh002" dir="history" />

<section title="Some Kinds of Scepticism and Speculation">
<abstract>
An analysis tailored to explication of our preferred varieties.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="scepticism">
The kind of scepticism adopted is distinguished by the absence of certain defects and is therefore described via a description of the defects.
Since the defects are all varieties of dogmatic pollution, the preferred variety of scepticism is called <i>open scepticism</i> and the undesirable varieties are kinds of <i>dogmatic scepticism</i>.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="speculation">
The kind of speculation which we favour is consistent with and complementary to the preferred scepticism.
It differs from the most common kind of speculative philosophy and is defined both in relation to scepticism and also by contrast with the more common variety.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="sceptical defects">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="scepticism as an end">
</subsec>
<subsec title="dogmatic scepticism">
First we must distance ourselves from dogmatic scepticism, which in a blatantly incoherent presentation claims to know that no knowledge is possible.
A consistent scepticism merely doubts.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="open scepticism">
A pure scepticism is the reluctant (if pervasive) doubt of one who has genuinely sought and continues to seek knowledge and understanding.
This scepticism is an open-mindedness which need not, however extreme, fall into incoherence.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="speculation">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="dogmatic speculation">
Complementary to dogmatic scepticism is dogmatic speculation, in which on the basis of tenuous evidence claims knowledge of implausible truths.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Speculative Metaphysics">
The term speculative is used in philosophy to refer to metaphysics.
In Kant's philosophy metaphysics is concerned primarily with truths which are <i>synthetic a priori</i>.
This kind of speculative philosophy therefore results in purported conclusive demonstration of synthetic truths.
This is therefore a form of dogmatism and incompatible with open scepticism.
<p/>
Though the establishment of synthetic necessities is not admitted, synthetic possibilities are another matter.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="open speculation">
An open speculation involves the exploration of possibilities.
Rather than being an opposite of scepticism it is another aspect of the same attitude.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Open Speculation">
A synthetic possibility is the negation of a synthetic necessity, and is therefore in a sceptical spirit.
To avoid incoherence (falling into dogmatism)  scepticism must neither assert nor deny, there is a symmetry to be respected.
However, the terminology is derived by contrast with the prevalent dogmatism.
Thus we take what is commonly accepted without question and raise doubts about it, and by a kind of contrapositive allow speculative possibilities which would commonly have been rejected as incompatible with some restrictive dogmatic conception debarring such possibilities.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Elements of Open Scepticism" tag="eoos">
<abstract>
Open scepticism is extreme in its avoidance of dogma, but prefers the ongoing search for (tentative) knowledge rather than collapsing into an exercise in refutation of dogma.
It rejects the demonstration of equipollence as itself dogmatic and emphasises the usefulness of refined elaborations of appearances.
The combined effect of these features is to make open scepticism appear moderate, perhaps even vacuous.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="What is Knowledge?">
<p>
A sceptic is someone who seeks for but fails to find knowledge.
What this means is sensitive of course to the meaning of the word "knowledge".
In ordinary language, in appropriate contexts, we will say that someone knows something even if his evidence for it is very weak, but nevertheless such as might be expected to suffice for belief.
(e.g. having been told something, even if the source was not authoritative, or having seen it, even if there was a possibility of having been mistaken)
In special contexts however, especially if they word "know" has been intoned with emphasis, the standard is raised very considerably.
In such a context having evidence for a proposition which is less than conclusive suffices for a denial of knowledge.
The standard of conclusiveness at stake is itself context sensitive.
In the context of philosophical discussion it may be as strong as <i>logically</i> conclusive (i.e. it may be expected that the evidence logically entail the supposed knowledge) <i>or even stronger</i> (e.g. that the evidence <i>be known conclusively</i> to entail the supposed knowledge).
In particular, in the context of Pyrrhonean scepticism the standard is that of being beyond doubt.
Something is known only if it can be shown to be beyond doubt, or absolutely certain.
</p><p>

</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Search for Knowledge">
<p>
Though a sceptic is nominally one who seeks knowledge, it is evident from the literature that predominantly phyrrhonean sceptics have replaced the search for knowledge by a preoccupation with the systematic refutation of all claims to knowledge.
</p><p>
In open scepticism the availability of general arguments against the possibility of absolutely certain knowledge makes it unnecessary to engage in systematic detailed refutations, which in any case is a highly undesirable perversion of the search for knowledge.
</p><p>
Sceptics accept that though we can know nothing, some things appear to be true.
</p>

</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Avoidance of Dogma">
<p>
The word "open" here emphasises the sceptical repudiation of dogma.
Particular emphasis is placed on the avoidance of various dogmas which are peculiar to scepticism.
</p><p>
The most trivial example of a dogma of scepticism is that of claiming to know that knowledge is impossible.
The incoherence of this was observed by the very earliest sceptics, and so few sceptics have fallen into this error, though some have adopted the most simplistic resolution of the obvious contradiction by claiming to know that nothing can be known except this sceptical conclusion.
Even if this version is carefully formulated so as to avoid incoherence, it remains a dogma and one can conceive a more extreme scepticism in which not even this is affirmed.
</p><p>
A more substantive example of sceptical dogmatism is in the method of demonstrating "equipollence".
This is more substantive, since it seems to have been an important method, and considerable space is given to such demonstrations in Sextus Empiricus.
</p><p>
I am in some doubt as to the true meaning of "equipollence", which might possibly be because there were different conceptions of it in the Greek sceptics.
There are two possible interpretations:
<ol>
<li>A proposition is equipollent if it and its converse are equi-probable</li>
<li>A proposition is equipollent if neither it nor its converse is known</li>
</ol>
The first is of course much stronger than the second, and its possibility and desirability is doubted in <i>open scepticism</i>.
Rather than demonstrating equipollence, open scepticism seeks the refinement of appearances, which is a more plausible fallback from the search for knowledge in the face of doubt.
The refinement of appearances involves the gathering and assessment of evidence in a manner similar to that in normal (non-sceptical) research, differing primarily from normal research in being less dogmatic.
This means that the presentation of results avoids definite conclusions, but presents information about the extent of experimental confirmation for various theories.
More practically oriented research may present information about the applicability of various models under investigation.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


<section title="Provocation to Doubt">
<abstract>
Doubt occurs at many levels and in many domains.
The most fundamental and general doubt flows from the  argument from regress of justification, which suggests that absolutely certain knowledge is not to be had.
The doubt thus established is general but academic, and of little practical significance.
Doubts of greater practical impact are obtained by more special arguments at higher levels.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Regress of Justification">
<p>
We cannot be said to know a proposition without some grounds or justification.
A justification consists in offering some kind of evidence supposed to establish the proposition under contention.
However, this evidence must itself be known, and there is therefore a problem of regress, we cannot get off the ground.
</p><p>
The supposition that we might have knowledge without justification depends on there being some state of mind which we recognise as infallible indication of truth.
This idea is familiar to us from Descartes.
Even if there were such a state of mind, however, we might be mistaken about which state of mind it is, we might suppose that we were experiencing this special state when we were in fact experiencing a state which almost never marks a falsehood.
</p><p>
The strength of this general sceptical doubt is not important, because any doubt which is completely general must be considered an <i>academic doubt</i>.
It applies to all conjectures, and therefore does gives no information about truth, and has no practical consequences.
</p><p>
Signficant doubts are those which are less general, and which therefore contribute materially to an assessment of what appears to be the case by suggesting that some propositions are more doubtful than others.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="" />
<subsec title="" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="" />
<subsec title="" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
