<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x012.xml,v 1.2 2006/06/16 17:40:39 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Theoretical Scepticism"
       created="2006-03-04"
       description="A discussion of the theoretical side of scepticism."
       keywords="philosophy scepticism speculation"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
<i>Theoretical scepticism</i> is an <i>anti-dogmatic</i> philosophy in respect of knowledge, which enjoins suspension of judgement in all matters, accepting only that things <i>appear to be</i> as they do.
Sceptical philosophy continually risks falling into negative dogma.
<i>open scepticism</i> is a particular sceptical philosophy promulgated at RBJones.com.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Historical Notes on Scepticism" >
</secref>
<secref title="Some Kinds of Scepticism and Speculation" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Benefits of Scepticism and Dogmatism" />
<subsec title="Provocation to Doubt" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Historical Notes on Scepticism" doc="xh002" dir="history" />

<section title="Some Kinds of Scepticism and Speculation">
<abstract>
An analysis tailored to explication of our preferred varieties.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="scepticism">
The kind of scepticism adopted is distinguished by the absence of certain defects and is therefore described via a description of the defects.
Since the defects are all varieties of dogmatic pollution, the preferred variety of scepticism is called <i>open scepticism</i> and the undesirable varieties are kinds of <i>dogmatic scepticism</i>.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="speculation">
The kind of speculation which we favour is consistent with and complementary to the preferred scepticism.
It differs from the most common kind of speculative philosophy and is defined both in relation to scepticism and also by contrast with the more common variety.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="sceptical defects">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="scepticism as an end">
</subsec>
<subsec title="dogmatic scepticism">
First we must distance ourselves from dogmatic scepticism, which in a blatently incoherent presentation claims to know that no knowlege is possible.
A consistent scepticism merely doubts.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="open scepticism">
A pure scepticism is the reluctant (if pervasive) doubt of one who has genuinely sought and continues to seel knowledge and understanding.
This scepticism is an open-mindedness which need not, however extreme, fall into incoherence.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody title="speculation">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="dogmatic speculation">
Complementary to dogmatic scepticism is dogmatic speculation, in which on the basis of tenuous evidence claims knowledge of implausible truths.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Speculative Metaphysics">
The term speculative is used in philosophy to refer to metaphysics.
In Kants philosophy metaphysics is concerned primarily with truths which are <i>synthetic a priori</i>.
This kind of speculative philosophy therefore results in purported conclusive demonstration of synthetic truths.
This is therefore a form of dogmatism and incompatible with open scepticism.
<p/>
Though the establishment of sythetic necessities is not admitted, synthetic possibilities are another matter.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="open speculation">
An open speculation involves the exploration of possibilities.
Rather than being an opposite of scepticism it is another aspect of the same attitude.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Open Speculation">
A synthetic possibility is the negation of a synthetic necessity, and is therefore in a sceptical spirit.
To avoid incoherence (falling into dogmatism)  scepticism must neither assert nor deny, there is a symmetry to be respected.
However, the terminology is derived by contrast with the prevalent dogmatism.
Thus we take what is commonly accepted without question and raise doubts about it, and by a kind of contrapositive allow speculative possibilities which would commonly have been rejected as incompatible with some restrictive dogmatic conception debarring such possibilities.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
