<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x014.xml,v 1.1 2006/03/25 22:50:36 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Practical Scepticism"
       created="2006-3-9"
       description=""
       keywords="rbjones philosophy practical scepticism"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
My existential starting point is <i>pragmatic scepticism</i> which liberates through the denial that logic mandates action.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Practical Roots of Pyrrhonean Scepticism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Elements of Pragmatic Scepticism"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Practical Roots of Pyrrhonean Scepticism">
<abstract>
Pyrrhonean scepticism was in its beginnings as much a practical as a theoretical enterprise.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Practical?">
Note that the meaning of practical in this context is its technical meaning in philosophy contrasting with theoretical.
Theoretical scepticism is scepticism about knowledge, e.g. doubts about whether we have any true knowledge.
Practical scepticism is scepticism about morals and action, e.g. doubts about whether there can be any rational basis for choosing one course of action rather than another.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Etymology">
The word sceptic comes from the Greek word <i>skepsis</i> meaning "enquiry".
In the context of ancient Greek philosophy it was used to describe someone who sought knowledge but failed to find it.
Thus it describes someone engaged on an enterprise, the search for knowledge, rather than a body of doctrine, and begins in this rather limited sense as a practical concept.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Pyrrho of Ellis (c 360-270 BCE)">
Though Pyrrho gave his name to the most substantial sceptical tradition, he left no writings and it is therefore uncertain how much of Pyrrhonean scepticism is attributable directly to him rather than his followers.
What seems most certain is his practical scepticism, which consisted in advocating suspension of judgement as a way to peace of mind, and indifference toward external things.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Social Context">
Thoroughgoing scepticism, Pyrrhonean or Academic, appears in ancient Greece only during its period of decline after the crowning achievements of Plato and Aristotle.
Other philosophical schools of this lengthy period of decline, such as Epicurianism, and Stoicism have, like scepticism, a primary aim in providing a philosophy to guide their adherents on how to live their lives.
Greek philosophy has become introspective and pessimistic.
<p/>
Scepticism is in this context a philosopher's consoling philosophy.
The philosophers sees, if he has no more pressing problems, a long history of philosophical disputation in which every conceivable philosophical position has been essayed (so it must have seemed) but none can be seen to have prevailed.
The philosopher is too pessimistic to venture on a new philosophy, but is tormented by the problem of deciding which of the positions of his predecessors are true and which false.
<p/>
Scepticism preaches resignation in the face of this impossible task.
One can never really know.
<p/>
Despite its preoccupation with theory (mainly with the refutation of prior theory), its purpose is practical.
To give peace of mind.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Elements of Pragmatic Scepticism">
<abstract>
Pragmatic scepticism is optimistic, constructive and liberating, rather than resignedly pessimistic.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Practical Defects of Pyrrhonean Scepticism">
A sceptic doubts that there is any conclusive reason for taking one course of action rather than another.
The question then arises how a sceptic can decide what to do.
While suspension of judgement on theoretical might possibly give peace of mind, it does not obviate the need to decide what (if anything) to do (there being no conclusive argument in favour of doing nothing either). 
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>

</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
