<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x014.xml,v 1.5 2007/02/20 22:14:05 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Pragmatic Scepticism"
       created="2006-3-9"
       description=""
       keywords="rbjones philosophy practical scepticism"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
<i>pragmatic scepticism</i> is a variant of <i>practical</i> scepticism, an <i>anti-dogmatic</i> philosophy in relation to <i>what should be done</i>.
It is a personally liberating philosophical position, liberating through the denial that logic (or anything else) provides conclusive grounds for any particular course of action.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Practical Roots of Pyrrhonean Scepticism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Elements of Pragmatic Scepticism"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Practical Roots of Pyrrhonean Scepticism">
<abstract>
Pyrrhonean scepticism was in its beginnings as much a practical as a theoretical enterprise.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Practical?">
Note that the meaning of practical in this context is its technical meaning in philosophy contrasting with theoretical.
Theoretical scepticism is scepticism about knowledge, e.g. doubts about whether we have any true knowledge.
Practical scepticism is scepticism about morals and action, e.g. doubts about whether there can be any rational basis for choosing one course of action rather than another.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Etymology">
The word sceptic comes from the Greek word <i>skepsis</i> meaning "enquiry".
In the context of ancient Greek philosophy it was used to describe someone who sought knowledge but failed to find it.
Thus it describes someone engaged on an enterprise, the search for knowledge, rather than a body of doctrine, and begins in this rather limited sense as a practical concept.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Pyrrho of Ellis (c 360-270 BCE)">
Though Pyrrho gave his name to the most substantial sceptical tradition, he left no writings and it is therefore uncertain how much of Pyrrhonean Scepticism is attributable directly to him rather than his followers.
What seems most certain is his practical scepticism, which consisted in advocating suspension of judgement as a way to peace of mind, and indifference toward external things.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Social Context">
Thoroughgoing scepticism, Pyrrhonean or Academic, appears in ancient Greece only during its period of decline after the crowning achievements of Plato and Aristotle.
Other philosophical schools of this lengthy period of decline, such as Epicurianism, and Stoicism have, like scepticism, a primary aim in providing a philosophy to guide their adherents on how to live their lives.
Greek philosophy has become introspective and pessimistic.
<p/>
Scepticism is in this context a philosopher's consoling philosophy.
The philosophers sees, if he has no more pressing problems, a long history of philosophical disputation in which every conceivable philosophical position has been essayed (so it must have seemed) but none can be seen to have prevailed.
The philosopher is too pessimistic to venture on a new philosophy, but is tormented by the problem of deciding which of the positions of his predecessors are true and which false.
<p/>
Scepticism preaches resignation in the face of this impossible task.
One can never really know.
<p/>
Despite its preoccupation with theory (mainly with the refutation of prior theory), its purpose is practical.
To give peace of mind.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Elements of Pragmatic Scepticism">
<abstract>
Pragmatic scepticism is optimistic, constructive and liberating, rather than resignedly pessimistic.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Introduction">
We proceed as follows.
<ol>
<li>objection to the practical doctrines of Pyrrho.</li>
<li>some parallels with theoretical scepticism to yield a pragmatic position</li>
<li>a first statement of pragmatic scepticism</li>
<li>a refinement of pragmatic scepticism</li>
<li>relations with Tao, Zen and Anarchism</li>
</ol>
</subsec>
<subsec title="2. A parallel with theoretical scepticism">
In theoretical scepticism we doubt all but that "appearances appear".
In observing the world we have sensory experiences, which certainly <i>are what they are</i>, and which provide evidence for something beyond themselves which is invariably inconclusive.
In <i>open scepticism</i> the notion of <i>appearance</i> is interpreted in a completely general way, so that when something appears to be the case, even though this <i>appearance</i> is an intuition far removed from senses, possibly about some abstract or mathematical topic, this too is a datum, if still a fallible indication of anything other than itself.
Note also, in relation specifically to sense data, that conscious appearances will in general be also removed from the primitive data of the senses.
If there are <i>sense data</i> which represent the evidence presented to mind by the senses, they need not be conscious, and the appearances of which we are consciously aware may be the result of much processing of that primitive data.
<p/>
Just as there is in theoretical scepticism a gulf between the appearances and the judgements which we might like to make from them, there is in practical scepticism a gulf between our judgements about what we should do, and the actions which we then perform.
Just as sensory appearances fail to determine beliefs or judgements, so beliefs and judgements fail to provide a conclusive determination of what should be or in fact is done.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="1. A Practical Defect in Pyrrhonean Scepticism">
A sceptic doubts that there is any conclusive reason for taking one course of action rather than another.
The question then arises how a sceptic can decide what to do.
While suspension of judgement on theoretical might possibly give peace of mind, it does not obviate the need to decide what (if anything) to do (there being no conclusive argument in favour of doing nothing either). 
<p/>
Pyrrhonean sceptics have tended to answer this difficulty by advocating adherence by sceptics to local cultural norms.
This is a lapse into <i>dogmatism</i> at the moment of truth.
</subsec>
<subsec title="3. The Pragmatic Alternative">
In <i>pragmatic</i> scepticism the unjustifiable endorsement of local conventions is replaced by a recognition and endorsement of <i>appearances</i>.
A <i>pragmatic sceptic</i> will consider practical questions in good faith, but will fail to find conclusive grounds for any course of action.
<p/>
Notwithstanding this lack of conclusive ground, the sceptic acknowledges that some courses of action <i>appear</i> to be better than others.
The way things appear to be, in these practical matters (as well as in theory) should be the sceptics guide.
<p/>
A pragmatic sceptic may do whatever, under the circumstances, seems to him best.
However, he need not.
The deliberations which might have lead to a determination of the best course of action might instead be thought of as a prelude to action, in the face of indecision.
We never know which course is best, but life goes on.
</subsec>
<subsec title="4. Scepticism and Tao">
It may help in understanding pragmatic scepticism to think of it as sharing aspects of the Chinese way of enlightenment known as Taoism, one of the ingredients of Zen Buddhism.
One of the elements of Tao is spontaneity, and the liberation from the tyranny of rationality which appears in pragmatic scepticism is a kind of spontaneity.
Where we say above that the pragmatic sceptic should do what seems best, this is a crude approximation to our intent, for one might consider matters carefully and come to feel that a particular course of action seems appropriate, and yet do something different.
<p/>
Pragmatic scepticism goes the extra mile, which makes it seem like Tao.
Rather than merely rejecting rational determination of a course of action, in favour of accepting appearances even if they contradict supposedly rational considerations, the practical sceptic accepts <i>what he does</i> even if it appears not to be the right thing to do.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
