<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x015.xml,v 1.3 2006/04/22 19:26:23 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Logic and Emotion"
       created="2006-3-15"
       description="A discussion of the apparent conflict between logic and emotion and its significance in modern philosophy"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy logic emotion"
       up="index.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Two constrasting views of the proper relationship between the rational and emotional elements of the human psyche, which may be thought representative of distinct lines of development of western philosophy are dissected with a view to a synthesis. 
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The Two Positions in Brief" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The Psychology of Reason and Emotion" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="The Synthesis" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Two Positions in Brief">
<abstract>
On the one hand (rational) that emotions, being primitive and bad, should be held in check by the intellect.
On the other (romantic) that, though primitive, they are good and should be freely expressed.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Hume's Summary">
Book II, Part III, Section III of David Hume's "A Treatise of Human Nature" <i>[<bibref name="Hume39"/>]</i> begins:
<blockquote>
Nothing is more usual in philosophy, and even in common life, than to talk of the combat of passion and reason, to give the preference to reason, and to assert that men are only so far virtuous as they conform themselves to its dictates.
</blockquote>
He makes this observation only as a prelude to demonstrating:
<blockquote>
that reason alone can never be a motive to any action of the will
</blockquote>
and
<blockquote>
that it can never oppose passion in the will.
</blockquote>
But Hume's arguments fell on deaf ears and the attitude he describes is alive and well, both in philosophy and common sense.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Romanticism">
Pro-tem, the best I can do here is offer Russell's very unsympathetic description <i>[<bibref name="Russell46"/>]</i>, speaking of the first romantics he says that they:
<blockquote>
"... greatly admired what they called <i>sensibilit&eacute;</i>, which mean a proneness to emotion, and more particularly to the emotion of sympathy.
To be thoroughly satisfactory, the emotion must be direct and violent and quite uninformed by thought."
</blockquote>
Romanticism seems most substantially to have been a literary phenomenon, but in philosophy its most prominent figure was Rousseau.
His most influencial work was "The Social Contract" which was a political tract proclaiming the romantic ideal of individual liberty but describing a political system which became the prototype for totalitarian regimes far removed from these romantic roots.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Psychology of Reason and Emotion">
<abstract>
These positions are both founded in the same fallacious conception of the relationship between reason and emotion and their respective roles.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Caveat">
This is of course a kind of folk psychology, and is tenuous.
It is in response to implicit premises of a similar (and I believe less credible) in the two positions under discussion.
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Synthesis">
<abstract>
The presumed independence of emotion and reason are illusory.
Rather than chosing which is right, we should understand how they relate and let them work together.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
