<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x016.xml,v 1.3 2006/05/27 19:22:20 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Logic and Emotion, Reason and Romanticism"
       created="2006/4/10"
       description="A parallel is drawn between these two apparently irreconcilable pairs"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy logic emotion reason romanticism"
       up="index.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
These two related conflicts are representative of a broader conflict between the rational/empiricist and the romantic tendencies in western philosophical thought.
Rather than choosing one side over the other, a synthesis is sought of elements from each. 
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="A Parallel" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Logic and Emotion" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Reason and Romanticism" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="A Parallel" tag="AP">
<abstract>
The conflict between logic and emotion takes place in the mind of the individual, that between reason and romanticism belongs to society rather than the individual.
Is this essentially the same game in these two different but interrelated arenas?
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Game Plan">
What I have in mind is to discuss these two things separately along similar lines, and also draw out the obvious parallels.
In both cases it seems to me that the conflict in both cases rests upon a misunderstanding and can to some degree can be alleviated by relevant insights.
The relevant insights I believe to be, in the first case psychological, concerning the respective roles and interplay between the intellectual and emotional aspects of the human psyche and in the second case sociological, concerning the respective roles of rational debate and cultural legacy in social evolution.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Rationalism and Romanticism">
We associate logic and reason on the one hand with the rationalist tendency, and emotion and romanticism with the romantic.
Both of these traditions tends to favour one side and deprecate the other.
I take the view not only that the two sides, in both cases, are not, or if properly understood should not, be regarded as conflicting.
It is best to seek to understand more fully how they work together, so that they may each fulfil their proper roles.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Logic and Emotion" doc="x015" tag="LAE" />

<section title="Reason and Romanticism" doc="x017" tag="RAR" />


</xldoc>
