<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x017.xml,v 1.2 2006/06/01 15:47:48 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Rationality and Romanticism"
       created="2006-05-05"
       description="A description of two opposing mindsets in modern philosophical thinking, those of the Enlightenment and of some of its principle opponents"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy logic emotion"
       up="index.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Two constrasting views of the proper relationship between the logical and emotional elements of the human psyche, which may be thought representative of distinct lines of development of western philosophy are dissected with a view to a synthesis. 
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction" />
<secref title="The Enlightenment" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Romanticism" />
<secref title="The Synthesis" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
Until recently my philosophical thinking outside the domain of more-or-less analytic philosophy (and meta-philosophy) has hung around utopianism or futurism.
This was at a time when I did not think of myself as being exclusively engaged in philosophy, and it was this (possibly but not necessarily or exclusively philosophical) interest in <i>how things might or should be</i> which made me style this website as <i>factasia</i>.
</p><p>
Having now come to feel more exclusively interested in (what at least I think of as) philosophical writing, the centrality of the futuristic, utopian factasia theme feels not quite right.
</p><p>
[put this in the factasy column and refer to it perhaps]
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Bertrand Russell">
Here is Russell's very unsympathetic description.
In his <i>History of Western Philosphy</i> <i>[<bibref name="Russell46"/>]</i>, speaking of the first romantics he says that they:
<blockquote>
"... greatly admired what they called <i>sensibilit&eacute;</i>, which means a proneness to emotion, and more particularly to the emotion of sympathy.
To be thoroughly satisfactory, the emotion must be direct and violent and quite uninformed by thought."
</blockquote>
Romanticism seems most substantially to have been a literary phenomenon, but in philosophy its most prominent figure was Rousseau.
His most influencial work was "The Social Contract" which was a political tract proclaiming the romantic ideal of individual liberty but describing a political system which became the prototype for totalitarian regimes far removed from these romantic roots.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Isaiah Berlin">
<p>
I turned to Isaiah Berlin for a fuller discussion of Romanticism, and the material here is largely based on his writings, I made notes on some of his collections of essays which can be found via the biliography [<bibref name="Berlin"/>].
</p><p>
There is far too much detail in Berlin for me to work with.
He himself dispells oversimplifications about what romanticism is, as well as putting forward an interesting 
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

<section title="The Enlightenment">
<abstract>

</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Romanticism">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="The Synthesis">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
