<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x020.xml,v 1.6 2007/04/25 19:10:22 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Naive Philosophy"
       created="2006/06/15"
       description="How to live, how to philosophise"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy scepticism open theoretical pragmatic practical creative expressive"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<maintitle>Na&iuml;ve Philosophy</maintitle>

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Na&iuml;ve philosophy is a collection of <i>attitudes</i> which underpin philosophy at RBJones.com, wwhich is naive, unscholarly, sceptical, anarchistic and utopian.
It is presented in three perspectives, Taoist, Anarchist, and Sceptical.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Philosophical Naivety"/>
<secref title="Aspects of Scepticism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Open Scepticism" />
<secref title="Pragmatic Scepticism" />
<secref title="Creative and Utopian Scepticism" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Philosophy at this level borders on the inexpressible or the paradoxical.
To help express the ideas I gather together a variety of perspectives.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
The first perspective begins with a parallel with na&iuml;ve art.
</p><p>
An important perspective comes as a bundle of aspects of scepticism.
These are presented in four principle aspects: theoretical, practical, creative and utopian.
</p><p>
Another perspective comes through the opposition of rationalistic and anarchistic philosophies.
</p><p>
A fourth through selective misconception of "The Tao".
</p><p>
A fifth comes from the writings of Montaigne.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Philosophical Naivety" tag="pn">
<abstract>
This sceptical philosophy is <i>naive</i> in a manner similar to that of primitive art.
The sceptic seeks wisdom but is acutely aware of the difficulties in its attainment.
He is aware of his own limited ability to comprehend the world and his place in it, and naturally sceptical about received wisdom and accepted methods of attaining it, including academic institutions and the standards they impose.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Introduction">
<p>
Naive or primitive art (see <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Na%C3%AFve_art">wikipedia</a>) is a term applied to art produced by artists who lack formal training in art, and also to the art of children or infants.
The art of children posesses a kind of unsophisticated and unrestrained expressiveness which may be valued. 
</p><p>
Naive philosophy may be thought of by analogy with naive art.
It is philosophy conducted with a naive disregard for or innocence of what others may expect.
A connotation of innocence in some respect in which institutions may be thought corrupting is also intended.
The further connotation of sheer incompetence is not to be glossed over.
</p><p>
The naive philosopher has a child-like curiousity about the great and difficult issues in life (and possibly also about some small and insignificant puzzles).
She wonders about these problems, and explores them in whatever ways seem likely to cast light.
Over long periods of time the naive philosopher may have a sense of continually learning more and coming to deeper understanding, but may nevertheless feel a finer appreciation of just how much there is still to be understood.
This simultaneous sense of <i>moving towards</i> but <i>feeling further away</i>, is one of the characteristic elements which reveals the <i>scepticism</i> inherent in naive philosophy.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Expressive Naivety">
<p>
The tendency to address intractible problems, makes convention modes of philosophical expression problematic.
Sceptical nescience mitigates against the completion of definite statements of results. 
</p><p>
The naive philosopher may therefore seek a means of expressing his incomplete understanding, and the dynamics of its evolution, which is closer to the commission of a work of art than it is to the completion of a dogmatic tract.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Methodological Naivety">
<p>
Delving into the most difficult problems demands methodological innovation.
A naive philosopher begins and ends with inadequate methods.
She continually improves her methods, and continually becomes more aware of their defects.
</p><p>
It is a commonplace that there is now too much knowledge for anyone to encompass it all.
In approaching problems which are not confined to some narrow speciality (and these are the life blood of naive philosophy) very selective knowledge of the relevant specialist domains must suffice.
Naive philosophy is the <i>thinking</i> man's philosophy, in which problems are addressed which might yield to deep and extended thought rather than extensive specialist knowledge and technical expertise.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Practical Naivety">
<p>
At its root, like pyrrhonism, naive philosophy is practical rather than theoretical,
Unlike pyrrhonism the end objective is not <i>peace of mind</i>, an aim best suited perhaps to those who are troubled and pessimistic.
</p><p>
The aim of naive philosophy is for the individual practitioner to determine, or to discover gradually as his life unfolds.
</p><p>
However, we might suggest that it could be summed up in general not as <i>peace</i> but as <i>fulfillment</i> a richer and more personal aim, which might possibly result in peace, but might equally yield dynamism and strife in pursuit of unattainable ideals.
</p><p>
In this we suggest that naive philosophy is not wholly a matter for philosophers, but a philosophy <i>of life</i> which may have something to say even to those of less meditative temperament.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Aspects of Scepticism">
<abstract>
Our scepticism is open not closed, positive rather than negative and active rather than passive.
It is open, pragmatic, creative, and even, utopian.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Pragmatic Motivation">
<p>
Pyrrhonean scepticism is "practical" rather than theoretical in its origin.
This means that rather than being concerned primarily with knowledge, it was concerned with how to live.
Its aim is thought to have been to secure "peace of mind", among a class of people, one infers, whose peace of mind was disturbed primarily by the difficulty of deciding which of the conflicting theories of the Greek philosophers was correct. 
</p><p>
Peace was to be secured essentially by <i>giving up</i>, suspending judgement as a matter of policy.
This however, like the negative attitude towards philosophy sometimes attributed to the later Wittgenstein, leaves the philosopher with nothing to do, and so seemed to be adapted to allow these philosophers to devote themselves to demonstrating conclusively that the dogmas of other philosophers were as unlikely to be true as false.
</p><p>
Its practical effect was therefore rather negative, though perhaps it did secure peace of mind, and I therefore adapt some of the core ideas here to more positive effect.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Open Mind">
<p>
First we step back closer to the etymological roots of scepticism, which word comes from a greek work meaning "enquire",
It is supposed to have been used to refer to those who seek knowledge but fail to find it.</p><p>
Now if you truly seek knowledge, then you will avoid dogma.
A dogma terminates the search for knowledge (in its sphere), so scepticism involves the avoidance of dogma.
Avoiding the dogmatic trap (also conspicuous in Greek scepticism) of regarding any belief however tenuous as a dogma, and translating this into positive terms, we get the idea that scepticism (when not vitiated by itself slipping into dogma) is essentially about keeping an open mind, in a more or less ordinary sense of that phrase.
</p><p>
An open mind leaves all options open, it gives freedom.
This is the practical benefit of our scepticism and a motive for our "pragmatic" scepticism.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Aknowledging Appearances">
<p>
A Greek sceptic might aknowledge no more than that appearances are what they seem to be.
In our case this broadens to the idea that a non-dogmatic search for knowledge, while yielding no absolute certainty does yield as good an account of how things appear to be.
</p><p>
Thus a scientist, rather than chosing what he thinks the best of the available theories and asserting its truth, should simply give a good account of the evidence for and against each of the theories.
Such accounts could of course be given at various levels of detail and aimed at different groups of readers.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">

</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

<section title="Open Scepticism" doc="x012" tag="ssp" />

<section title="Pragmatic Scepticism" doc="x014" tag="ps" />

<section title="Creative and Utopian Scepticism" doc="xe001" tag="ee" />

</xldoc>
