<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x020.xml,v 1.2 2006/07/01 09:04:12 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Naive Philosophy"
       created="2006-06-15"
       description="How to take life"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy scepticism expressionism existialism"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
This is a layer of philosophy in the context of which all other philosophy at RBJones.com is undertaken.
It enjoins a gentle, unhurried approach both to thinking about the world and to acting our part in it.
That part should be our own, reflecting and expressing our inner selves to which attention is desirable. 
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec >
<p>
The term "naive" here is used in recognition of the philosophical value of the wonderful, all embracing, enquiring incomprehension of children.
When a child responds to a first explanation with "why?" and goes on in this enquiry beyond the last we can give, she shows that she has still not learned that adult acceptance as conclusive, of explanations which can never be so.
<p></p>
In sceptics we find grown men who refuse to shed this naivet&eacute;.
</p><p>
Too often they will slip into a negative dogmatism, or loose in the face of endless incomprehension their lust for understanding.
</p><p>
Here we seek to underpin our philosophy with that endless wonderment and with a complementary sense of life as the open expression of what we are become in response to what is.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
The basic ideas here are:
<ol>
<li>Take it with a pinch of salt</li>
<li>Please yourself</li>
<li>Be yourself</li>
</ol>
</subsec>
<subsec>
Which philosophically translate here into:
<ol>
<li>open scepticism</li>
<li>pragmatic scepticism</li>
<li>existential expressionism</li>
</ol>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Open Scepticism" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Pragmatic Scepticism" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Existential Expressionism" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

<section title="Open Scepticism" doc="x012" tag="ssp" />

<section title="Pragmatic Scepticism" doc="x014" tag="ps" />

<section title="Existential Expressionism" doc="xe001" tag="ee" />

</xldoc>
