<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id"
       title="The Essence of Metaphysical Positivism"
       created="2007/07/10"
       description="Central doctrines of metaphysical positivism."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics"
       class="con"
       root="../../"
       up="x010.html"
       path="rbjpub/philos"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
In essence Metaphysical Positivism is a positivisitic philosophy with negative
dogmas excised, with a positive attitude towards metaphysics, based around a
method of logical analysis together with appropriate philosophical (including
metaphysical) underpinnings.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introducing Metaphysical Positivism" />
<secref title="The Method of Formal Logical Analysis" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Liberal Positivism" />
<secref title="Positive Metaphysics" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>

<section title="Introducing Metaphysical Positivism" tag="IMP">
<abstract>
What is the point of Metaphysical Positivism?
</abstract>

<secbody title="Rationality and Social Progress">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Comte's Conception of Progress in Civilisation">
<p>
August Comte, who coined the term "positivism" built systematic philosophy
starting from the idea that civilisation progresses through certain stages.
</p><p>
In his rather simplistic and idealistic conception there had been three such
stages, the first a theological stage in which the world was understood as
controlled by supernatural beings, the second a metaphysical phase in which the
world was "explained" by speculative theories whose evidential basis and
practical utility were at best tenuous.
</p><p>
The third phase was that inaugurated by the ideas of men like Bacon and
Gallileo, that of modern science.
</p><p>
One of things which Comte sought to do was to articulate more fully the
principles on which scientific knowledge is based, and to draw out the contrast
between these methods and those of the theological and metaphysical stages as
he saw them.
</p><p>
Metaphysical Positivism is so called partly because it buys in to the idea that
there is progress in civilisation, and that a significant element of that progress does
concern what we might call "epistemic standards", how we decide what ideas
about the nature of the world around should be taken seriously.
</p><p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Hume's Scepticism">
<p>
David Hume preceded Comte's coining of the term "positivism" but is by some
regarded as having been the first "true" positivist.
</p><p>
His importance for Metaphysical Positivism lies in his having adopted a kind of
mitigated scepticism which hangs around the distinction between logical and
empirical truths (this is sometimes known as "Hume's fork").
Hume affirmed the importance of this distinction, and asserted that only
logical truths (those concerning "relations between ideas") could be known with
certainty.
</p><p>
Hume lived at the same time as Rousseau, a central figure in the romantic
challenge to the rationalistic exesses of the enlightenment, and though Hume
could not be called a romantic, his precise delimitation of the very narrow scope of
deductive argument, and scepticism about the merits of other kinds of argument
(which included both inductive arguments and arguments about values), did
provide ammunition for opponents of enlightenment rationalism, which saw no
bounds on scope of its deliberations.  
</p><p>
Metaphysical positivism, attaches great importance to the delimitation of the
scope of deductive arguments, to their full exploitation wherever they have
something to offer, and to the exposure of all other arguments as varieties of rhetoric.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody  title="Formal Analysis as an Element of Rationality">
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Following Comte">
<p>
Alongside Comte's conception of progress in civilisation, I place another
(equally simplistic).
It is primitive to settle disputes by physical contestation, somewhat better to
do it verbally (let us say, rhetorically), but better still by some method more
honest and reasonable than rhetoric.
</p><p>
We might cautiously use the term "rational" for our best ideas about how this
might be done, hoping to evolve an idea of the rational which recognises the
limits of sound argument and delivers open and honest ways of resolving
problems which fall outside its scope (to a first approximation that would be
any which are not just about logic or mathematics!).
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Following Hume">
<p>
With Hume, we attach great importance to the distinction between logical and
empirical truths, and consider the further exposure of that distinction to be
worthwhile progress.
</p><p>
It is progress to have better ways of knowing when arguments
are deductive, it is progress to have ways of exploiting deductive arguments
to the very limits of their scope, which will go no further, which will
conspicuously fail to endorse arguments having the superficial appearance but not the substance of
deductive soundness.
</p><p>
Metaphysical positivism is a purely analytic philosophy, the analytic core of a
broader conception of philosophy which I call simply "<xlink href="x018.html">Positive Philosophy</xlink>".
As such it centres around a method for formal analysis and the philosophical
ideas which underpin it and its applications.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>

</section>


<section title="Liberal Positivism" doc="x026" tag="LP"/>
<section title="Positive Metaphysics" doc="x006" tag="PM"/>
<section title="The Method of Formal Logical Analysis" doc="fm013" suf="htm" dir="../methods/fm" tag="MFLA"/>

<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
