<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x029.xml,v 1.1 2009/10/05 09:18:19 rbj Exp $"
       title="Critical Rationalism"
       created="2009/09/18"
       description="Notes on Critical Rationalism from a Metaphysical
		    Positivist standpoint"
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics critial rationalism"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Notes on Critical Rationalism from a Metaphysical Positivist standpoint.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Agreements"/>
<secref title="Disagreements"/>
<secref title="Metaphysical Positivism"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>

</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
When I first thought it might be a good idea to say something about critical
rationalism here, that first throught was to produce a comparison with
Metaphysical Positivism, my own philosophical position.
</p><p>
My second thought was that I don't really know enough about critical
rationalism to do a meaningful comparison.
But that I might instead offer a few words on why I am not myself a critical
rationalist, which reasons I could not truthfully represent as based on other
than a superficial knowledge of critical rationalism.
</p><p>
Even this much, however, could not be done without a bit of digging into how
critical rationalism is now presented, and my first impressions reading David
Miller make me wonder whether it might be worth my while taking it a bit more seriously.
</p><p>
So, I have not yet made my mind up which of the two approaches to take.
Perhaps both in turn!
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Agreements" tag="AG">
<abstract>
Descriptions of areas of agreement.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Open Society">
My familiarity with Popper's writings is mainly confined to his volumes on the
Open Society.
I enjoyed these enormously, and am pretty enthusiastic about the idea of an
Open Society.
My own ideas in this area are not well worked out, but there are definite
points of disagreement, for example in relation to utopian thinking.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Problem of Induction">
I agree with Popper in not thinking much of the idea of "inductive inference".
However, I don't much care for Popper's alternative.
I am inclined to consider empirical (but not deductive) science as hypothetical
in perpetuity.
</subsec>
<subsec title="Deductivism">
<p>
This seems to be used by some as an alternative to Critical Rationalism, naming
Popper's philosophy.
</p><p>
The first name I chose for my own conception of analytic philosophy was
"philosophical logicism" and this could be described as a kind of deductivism.
However, it bears little resemblance to Critical Rationalism.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Disagreements" tag="AG">
<abstract>
Descriptions of areas of disagreement.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="The Problem of Demarcation">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Metaphysical Positivism" doc="x010" tag="mp" />

</xldoc>
