<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x030.xml,v 1.1 2009/10/05 09:18:19 rbj Exp $"
       title="Three Dialectics"
       created="2009/09/18"
       description="Some history, some ideas for the future."
       keywords="rbjones logic philosophy positivism metaphysics utopia"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Three dialectical processes in the history of philosophy are used to explore
the origins of some of the key ideas of metaphysical positivism.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
<secref title="Dogmatism versus Scepticism"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Rationalism versus Empiricism"/>
<secref title="Essentialism versus Conventionalism"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
First words on the three dialectics and their connection with metaphysical
positivism and the fundamental triple-dichotomy.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Dialectic">
<p>
There have been many different kinds of dialectic in the history of philosophy,
and our usage here does not refer specifically to any of them.
It refers rather loosely to a long term historical debate between two
supposedly opposite views which may be susceptible of resolution by some kind
of synthesis.
</p><p>
So one of the things I can say about this kind of dialectic is that, though it may
appear (especially to the proponents at the early stages in the dialectic) as a
dichotomy, it is at best a false dichotomy.
It may seem that one must chose one or other of the two opposing viewpoints,
but instead some kind of combination of the key aspects of each will be possible.
</p><p>
Progress in such a dialectical debate may involve a series of attempts to find
the right synthesis.
But what seems like a reasonable position avoiding the indefensible extremes of
two positions poles apart by one philosopher at some time, will later be
opposed by a different synthesis, and these two positions may then become new
extremes demanding resolution in a further synthesis.
</p><p>
Just as dialectic should be distinguished (in this context at least) from
dichotomy, <i>synthesis</i> should not be confused with <i>compromise</i>.
The dialectical process is not a process of mediation between extremes, but a
process of locating and eliminating the flaws in each extreme position to yield
positions which can be united.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Three">
The three dialectics of present interest are:
<ul>
<li>dogmatism versus scepticism</li>
<li>rationalism versus empiricism</li>
<li>essentialism versus conventionalism</li>
</ul>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Dogmatism versus Scepticism">
<p>
This dialectic begins with the pre-socractic dogmatic metaphysicians, whose
diverse view spawn sophistical relativism.
This is answered by Socrates and the great dogmatic philosophical systems of
Plato and Aristotle.
There followed a long tradition of Pyrrhonean and Academic scepticism.
</p><p>
Scepticism is revived in the seventheenth century in religious controversy
leading to a positivistic synthesis in the work of David Hume.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Rationalism versus Empiricism">
From precursors to this dialectic in the philosophical systems of Plato and
Aristotle we pass through the rationalist and empiricist philosophies once more
to a positivistic synthesis in the philosophy of David Hume. 
</subsec>
<subsec title="Essentialism versus Conventionalism">
Once again we begin with Plato and Aristotle.
In its earlier stages the debate is between varieties of essentialism and nominalism.
In this case Hume's positivism is far from a synthesis, but marks a transition
to a dialectic between essentialism and conventionalism.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Dogmatism versus Scepticism">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Rationalism versus Empiricism">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Essentialism versus Conventionalism">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


</xldoc>
