<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x032.xml,v 1.5 2010/03/02 13:35:31 rbj Exp $"
       title="The HOT Philosophy Project"
       created="2010/01/02"
       description="Honest, Open, Transparent Philosophy"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy open transparent positivist scepticsl"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
<p>
Philosophy HOT off the brain.
"flow of cogitation" philosophical writing.
<br />
Also:
<ul>
<li><b>H</b>onest</li>
<li><b>O</b>pen</li>
<li><b>T</b>ransparent</li>
</ul>
</p>
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introductory Sketch"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="HOT Philosophy - the book"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Other Collateral"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introductory Sketch" tag="intro">
<abstract>
A few words about the ideas behind "HOT philosophy".
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="A Big Problem and its Resolution">
<p>
This project is intended to tell the story of a special life-stopping (well, intellectual-life inhibiting) problem which I ran into round about 1995.
It will describe the problem, and why it was, for me, a big problem.
It will describe "the solution", tortuously engineered over many years, which is just beginning to let life (intellectually) flow for me as it should.
</p><p>
However, the main point is not just these anecdotes.
</p><p>
The main point is to subject various aspects of the problem and of my supposed resolution to philosophical analysis.
And the main point of that, is to try out some ideas about the nature of philsophical analysis and see how well they work.
The ideas about analysis are themselves, part of the supposed resolution.
</p><p>
If that all sounds too philosophically introspective, then I can offer two mitigations.
The first part of the project presents the problem, my route to its resolution and the bare bones of the results.
The next two parts develop in greater depth two aspects of the resolution, which may be thought of as answers to the questions:
<ul>
<li>How could it be so?</li>
<li>What should we do about it?</li>
</ul>
The answer to the first, which I think of as analogous to Hume's delivery of "A Treatise on Human Nature" to explain why we believe things which are not deducible from the evidence to hand, is a story about evolution.
This is intended to make intelligible some of the infelicities which we find in the rationality of academic research.
</p><p>
The answer to the second involves "epistemic retreat", a constructive analytic response to scepticism, and the architecture of cognition, a  study of how "knowledge" can be organised for exploitation in an open rather than a dogmatic way.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="'Flow of Cogitation' Philosophical Writing">
<p>
You may think of this as being an extremely tenuous analogue of "stream of consciousness" writing in literature.
</p><p>
The HOT philosophy project is so-called because it is intended to be a vehicle for documenting <i>in the moment</i> an ongoing philosophical investigation.
Better put perhaps, it is my attempt to synthesise the processes of philosophical thinking and creative writing.
</p><p>
HOT is also a recognition of my own personal disabilities; my unsuitability for a more traditional non-fiction writing project in which one presents systematically some subject matter, or even in which one researches thoroughly and presents the results of the research.
I have a hackers attitude toward philosophy, I enjoy the chase, I enjoy thinking about difficult problems, I enjoy coming up with solutions, or partial or putative solutions.
Writing it all up is less exciting, at least, post factum.
A hacker sees the challenge of a problem, he cuts the code, takes pride perhaps in its aesthetic as well as its practical virtues.
But user documentation?
The next problem is too tempting a lure.
</p><p>
Its even worse in philosophy, if you have this kind of mind.
Because the problems are never solved anyway, I have to write as I go, because I'm not actually likely to arrive.
</p><p>
So the idea of HOT philosophy is to find a way of doing philosophy which generates intelligible product in the process, rather than demanding onerous exposition after the fact.
Analysis by the construction of formal models does this, and the HOT philosophy project is intended to explore whether this can be made to work with a more liberal (pre-formal) conception of analysis (I don't rule out formal modelling, but formal material will go elsewhere).
</p><p>
Having said all that, "flow of cogitation" can't work for me as I might hope, because there is too much undocumented past innovation in my haed, on which today's cogitations are built.
So its rather hard to explain what I am thinking <i>now</i>, without unravelling trains of thought which go back a few decades.
A professional philosopher doesn't have this problem so bad as I, because he has been documenting his views all his professional life, and is less likely to have a backlog.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Honest, Open, Transparent">
<p>
Declaring that an aim of the project is to be "Honest, Open, Transparent", is perhaps rather odd.
It is an attempt to engineer an excuse for speaking my mind, for stating honestly why my problem is for me such a big problem.
</p><p>
Why should I need an excuse?
</p><p>
This is an "Emperor's New Clothes" thing.
Does one need an excuse to say that the Emperor is naked?
Or is it courage one needs?
Or what?
</p><p>
To say that analytic philosophers are en-masse irrational, is not novel.
But to publish a volume of philosophy which is essentially inspired or provoked by that kind of perception and the difficulty of doing philosophy in the face of it, is not easy.
</p><p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="HOT Philosophy - the book" doc="xb002" dir="../www/books" />

<section title="Other Collateral" tag="oc">
<abstract>
This section will contain links to pages at RBJones.com which are related to the content of the HOT philosophy project.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="X-Logic" doc="x005">
X-Logic will be the subject of Part III of the HOT Philosophy project.
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
