<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x034.xml,v 1.1 2012/01/23 21:40:03 rbj Exp $"
       title="Positive Philosophy, Fredom and Democracy"
       created="2011/11/20"
       description="An outline of a book project."
       keywords="rbjones philosophy positivism existentialism tao ethics politics economics"
       class="con"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Practical Positive Philosophy is concerned with existential questions, ethics, morality, justice, politics and economics.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Metaphysical Positivism">
<p>
A concise introduction to the theoretical, analytic, aspects of Positive Philosophy sufficient to provide a basis for the practical aspects of Positive Philosophy.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Existential Positivism">
<p>
Practical positive philosophy is called "existential positivism" because it builds outward from core considerations for the individual and his attitude towards life.
This central core is an affirmation of the autonomy of the individual.
From this an individualistic conception of ethics and morality is obtained.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Politics">
<p>
The nature of democracy is considered anew, what it is and what it might become, from the point of view of the autonomous individual and in the context of a critique of present day institutions of democratic government and they way they now operate and of the possibilities that arise from information technology and plausible future developments of it.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Economics">
<p>
On the thesis that the individual seeking to influence the shape of society will seek the most efficient way of exerting that influence, the possibilities for systematic harnessing of individual purchasing decisions to achieve social change are explored.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="HTML" dir="../www/books/ppfd" doc="index" suf="htm"/>
<subsec title="PDF (A4)" dir="../www/books/ppfd" doc="ppfdpam" suf="pdf"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="" tag="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
