<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xe001.xml,v 1.2 2006/07/01 13:54:08 rbj01 Exp $"
       title="Existential Expressionism"
       created="2006-06-13"
       description="The understanding of life as expression of self"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy existential expressionism"
       up="index.htm"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
Existential expressionism is a view of life as expression of self.
Such a life need not be philosophical, but here (at RBJones.com) existential expressionism becomes a philosophical genre in which philosophical thinking is primary, and the written word is intended to express both the resulting <i>weltanschauung</i> and the process by which it evolves.
The expression of self is therefore in this case, not <i>about</i> the self, but of a particular (philosophical) perspective on the world as a whole.
This connects with the sceptical refusal to go beyond appearance into dogma, by providing a mode of expression which survives sceptical doubt.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
<p>
The suggestion "be yourself" is at face value vacuous.
Who else could one be?
Yet most of us are, throughout our lives, trying somehow to be someone else.
</p><p>
It is a quirk of language perhaps, from which we might escape by paraphrase.
When we try to be someone else, what we are really doing is trying to be different in the future than we are today (in some specific ways which we think desirable).
We would be the same person of course, strictly, but in another sense, quite a different person.
</p><p>
So the suggestion, "be yourself", rather than saying nothing, might be understood to proscribe such aspirations to self improvement, to be suggesting personal stasis.
But the dynamic is part of the self, and to proscribe change is to advocate a change.
</p><p>
So neither of these two extreme's (vacuity, proscription of change) comes close to a plausible account of what is intended.
</p>
<p>

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


<section title="" tag=""/>

</xldoc>
