<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: xe002.xml,v 1.1 2009/09/16 09:46:50 rbj Exp $"
       title="Dogma"
       created="2009/9/2"
       description="Kinds of Dogma"
       keywords="rbjones philosophy scepticism open dogma"
       up="x012.html"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
An introduction to dogma, the distinction between positive and negative dogma,
and some examples of each.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Dogma and Positivism" />
<secref title="Dogma and Scepticism" />
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Positive Dogma" />
<secref title="Negative Dogma" />
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Dogma and Positivism" tag="dp">
<abstract>
We motivate the discussion by reference to August Comte.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
It is perhaps more natural to think of skepticism when we talk about dogma,
skepticism having been the ancient philosopy most preoccupied with the
avoidance of dogma.
However, it is worthwhile to put the discussion of dogma in the context of
Comte's conception of progress, since that gives our attitude towards dogma a
place in a positive conception of progress through stages of civilisation.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="The Law of The Three States">
<p>
Comte describes three stages in the development of the human mind (I prefer to
think of these as stages in the evolution of civilisation):
<ul>
<li>Religious</li>
<li>Metaphysical</li>
<li>Positive</li>
</ul>
For Comte these represented stages in our understanding of the world.
For our present purposes they are stages in the liberalisation of human thought
from the most extreme dogmatism to more open minded enquiry.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Religious">
<p>
At this stage, the world is explained via one or more supernatural beings.
Typically the explanation is delivered through some elite priesthood, who
represent themselves as revealing devine truth.
The religious institutions are likely to be heirarchic and authoritarian, and hence ultimately
controlled by one individual. 
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Metaphysical">
<p>
We naturally think of the philosophers of ancient Greece in this matter, who
were free from religious authority and able to speculate freely about how the
works.
</p><p>
Though there is no dogma imposed by religious authority, the various
metaphysical systems are themselved nevertheless dogmatic in character.
They go so far beyond the available evidence that to hold to such a system is
like an act of faith, and hence is likely to be done with greater assurance and
rigidity than is properly warranted by the evidence.
</p>
</subsec>
<subsec title="Positive">
<p>
This stage was Comte's last and embodied his conception of positive science in
which scientific theories are based on observation and experiment and do not go
beyond what is manifest from the evidence.
This is the least dogmatic of Comte's stages because it is expected that
scientific theories are subject to refutation if contrary evidence comes to light.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Dogma and Scepticism" tag="ds">
<abstract>
We define dogma, describe its role in sceptical philosophy, and introduce the
distinction between positive and negative dogma.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="What is A Dogma">
<p>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
<p>
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Positive Dogma" tag="pd">
<abstract>
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Negative Dogma" tag="nd">
<abstract>
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
