<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: SetTheories.xml,v 1.2 2007/04/25 19:10:22 rbj01 Exp $"
       name="SetTheories"
       title="Set Theories"
       created="2002-10-15"
       description="Varieties of Set or Membership Theory"
       keywords="rbjones logic sets"
       class="con"
       root="../../../"
       rbjhome="rbj.htm"
       site="rbjones">

<section title="Overview">
<abstract>
Sets are the simplest way of combining things into collections.
Nevertheless there are many different theories of sets, which differ mainly but not exclusively in their conception of what sets there are.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="Introduction"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<secref title=""/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
The only feature (so far as I am aware) common to all set theories is the primacy of the binary relation of membership.
Some assert that extensionality is essential, but others devise set theories which are not extensional.
Most professional set theorists an other mathematicians work within theories whose ontology is confined to pure well-founded sets, but a minority work work with non-well-founded and/or impure ontologies,
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Classifying Set Theories">
Set theories may be classified using the following characteristic:
<ul>
<li>extensionality</li>
<li>well-foundedness</li>
</ul>
There are of course many others but these are arguably the best basis for a highest level of classification.
I know little about non-extensional set theories, those of which I am aware are constructive set theories and on these I refer the reader to <bibref name="beeson80" />, though this may now be a bit dated.

</subsec>
<subsec title="Well-Founded Set Theories">
<p>
Set theory as formalised by Frege was a "naive" set theory in which an unqualified principle of abstraction was available.
This means that the extension of any property expressible in the formal language corresponded to that of some set, and this liberal ontological principle was shown by Russell's paradox to render the logical system inconsistent.
</p><p>
Two earliest response to this problem, published by Russell and Zermelo in 1908, both effectively realised consistency by constraining the ontology to be well-founded (though Russell's solution was more elaborate, its central principle was the avoidance of "vicious" circularity).
</p><p>
The dominant set theory since those early times is a derivative of Zermelo's system called Zermelo-Frankel set theory, particularly the version with a choice principle (ZFC).

</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>


<section title="">
<abstract>
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
<subsec title="">
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

</xldoc>
