<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ProofPower SYSTEM "pp-symbol.ent">
<xldoc xmlns="http://www.x-logic.org/xmlns/draft/xld"
       xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
       id="$Id: x005.xml,v 1.2 2008/04/06 13:07:17 rbj01 Exp $"
       name="x005"
       title="ProofPower"
       description="Some stuff about ProofPower"
       keywords="x-logic xml logic proofpower"
       class="con"
       root="../../"
       path="rbjpub/pp/"
       up="index.htm"
       author="rbj">

<section title="Introduction">
<abstract>
This page provides some information about ProofPower.
</abstract>
<secbody>
<sbcol>
<secref title="ProofPower and its Logic"/>
<secref title="ProofPower theory listings"/>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title='Famous theorems in ProofPower' href="rda001.html">
Freek Wiedijk is tracking progress on automated proofs of a list of "100 greatest theorems". This page lists the statements of the theorems on the list that have been proved in ProofPower.
</subsec>
<subsec title='The ProofPower character set in HTML' href="ppchartable.html">
ProofPower uses an extended character set so that logic and mathematics comes out a bit nicer.
This page has some tables showing how these render in HTML. 
</subsec>
<secref title="X-Logic sml xtras"/>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="ProofPower and its Logic" tag="PPAIL">
<abstract>
ProofPower is a specification and proof development and checking tool developed by <xlink href="http://www.icl.com/">ICL</xlink> and now owned by <xlink href="http://www.lemma-one.com/">Lemma-1</xlink>.
It is an intellectual descendent of Cambridge HOL, and implements in Standard ML following the LCF paradigm, proof support for exactly the same polymorphic higher order logic as that in Cambridge HOL.
</abstract>

<secbody>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="Why ProofPower?">
<p>
I am using ProofPower for the following reasons:
</p>
<ol>
<li>I am familiar with it, having been involved in its development and application for many years.</li>
<li>It is designed to work with the real logical characters rather then ascii equivalents.</li>
<li>I like higher order logic, especially this variant.</li>
</ol>
<p>
The main claim to fame of ProofPower is its support for the Z specification language and the DERA compliance notation (for refining Z to Ada), however, I'm not making any use of these.
</p>
</subsec>
</sbcol>
<sbcol>
<subsec title="ProofPower Documentation">
For a full understanding of the specifications in ProofPower HOL you need to look at the semantics of HOL and at the theories in the ancestry of the specification.
For the semantics of the language you can either look at the informal mathematical semantics which is available from Cambridge for their system, or else at the formal specifications of ProofPower at the <xlink href="http://www.lemma-one.com/">Lemma-1</xlink> site.
For links to listings of the theories, see below.
This is a simple language, but precise semantics is never easy.
</subsec>
</sbcol>
</secbody>
</section>

<section title="ProofPower theory listings" tag="PPthList" doc="pptheories" />

<section title="X-Logic sml xtras" tag="XLSMLX" doc="pp-smlxtras" />

</xldoc>



